你好，欢迎来到kubernetes课程完整版
hello and welcome to this complete
这门课程将会有
kubernetes course the course is a mix of
生动的理论解释
animated theoretic explanations but also
和易于上手的实践演示
hands-on demos for you to follow along
首先让我们快速浏览一下
so let's quickly go through the topics
我会在这门课中讲到的知识点
i'll cover in this course
第一部分将会
the first part gives you a great
介绍kubernetes(简称k8s)
introduction to kubernetes
我们将从基本概念开始
we'll start with the basic concepts of
解释kubernetes是什么
what kubernetes actually
它解决什么问题
is what problems it solves and the
以及kubernetes的架构
kubernetes architecture
通过展示kubernetes所有的主要组件
you will learn how you can use
你会学到如何使用kubernetes
kubernetes by showcasing
在学习主要概念之后
all the main components after learning
我们将会
the main concepts
学习和安装minikube
we will learn and install minikube for
从而实现一个本地kubernetes集群
a local kubernetes cluster
我们将学习如何通过通过kubectl命令
and we will go through the main commands
来创建调试和删除一个pod
of creating debugging and deleting
kubectl即为kubernetes的
pods using kubectl which is kubernetes
命令行工具
command line tool
在了解kubectl的主要命令后
after knowing kubectl main commands i
我将解释kubernetes yaml
will explain kubernetes yaml
配置文件
configuration files
我们将用它来创建和
which we will use to create and
配置组件
configure components
然后我们将进行实际应用
then we will go through a practical use
我们将部署一个简单的
case where we'll deploy a simple
应用程序
application
在kubernetes集群中进行本地设置
setup in kubernetes cluster locally
来获得您的第一次使用kubernetes的实践经验
to get your first hands-on experience with kubernetes
从而对使用该工具更有信心
and feel more confident about the tool
在第二部分
in the second part
我们会学习更高级且
we will go into more advanced and
重要的概念
important concepts
比如使用命名空间组织你的组件
like organizing your components using namespaces
以及如何使用k8s Ingress
how to make your app available from
让你的应用程序在kubernetes外部依然可用
outside using kubernetes
同时学习helm
ingress and learn about helm which is
它是k8s的包管理器
the package manager
此外，我们还会更加深入地学习三个组件
for kubernetes in addition we will look at three components
首先是如何在kubernetes中使用卷
in more detail first how to persist data
来持久化数据
in kubernetes using volumes
第二，如何部署有状态的
second how to deploy stateful
应用程序，比如
applications like databases
使用状态集组件地数据库
using stateful set component and lastly
最后我们会看到对应不同用例的不同的kubernetes服务类型
we will look at the different kubernetes service types
如果你喜欢这个课程
for different use cases if you like the
记得订阅我的频道
course be sure to subscribe to my
更多类似的视频
channel for more videos like this
参见视频描述
and also check out the video description
从而订阅更多相关的优达课程等
for more related courses on udemy etc
如果你们课程或课程结束后
if you guys have any questions during
有任何问题
the course or after the course
或者你只是想保持联系
or you want to simply stay in touch i
我很乐意在社交网站上与你们联系
would love to connect with you on social media
所以一定要订阅我哦
so be sure to follow me there as well
在这段视频中，我将解释
so in this video i'm going to explain
什么是kubernetes
what kubernetes is
我们将从定义开始
we're going to start off with the
来看它的官方定义是什么
definition to see what
以及发挥了什么作用
official definition is and what it does
然后我们会看一个问题的解决方案作为案例
then we're going to look at the problem solution
来分析kubernetes出现的主要原因
case study of kubernetes basically why
以及它能够解决什么问题
did kubernetes even come around and what problems
那么我们从定义开始
does it solve so let's jump in right
学习kubernetes是什么
into the definition
kubernetes是一个开源的
what is kubernetes so kubernetes is an open source
容器编排框架
container orchestration framework which
最初是由
was originally developed by
谷歌开发
google so on the foundation it manages
它基本功能是可以管理容器，可以是docker容器
containers be docker containers or from
也可以是来自其它技术的容器
some other technology
这基本上意味着kubernetes
which basically means that kubernetes
可以帮助您管理
helps you manage
由数百或者成千上万的容器
applications that are made up of hundreds or maybe
组成的应用程序
thousands of containers
它可以帮助你不同的环境管理它们
and it helps you manage them in different environments
比如物理机环境，虚拟机环境
like physical machines virtual machines
或者云环境，甚至混合环境
or cloud environments or even hybrid
那么k8s解决了什么问题呢
deployment environments so what problems
以及
does kubernetes solve and
容器编制工具需要完成哪些任务呢
what are the tasks of a container orchestration tool
解答之前先来
actually so to go through this
按时间顺序梳理一下需求
chronologically
微服务的兴起引起了
the rise of microservices caused
容器技术使用量的大幅增加
increased usage of container technologies
因为容器可以为一些
because the containers actually offer
小型的独立应用程序
the perfect host
提供完美的主机
for small independent applications like
比如微服务
microservices
同时容器和微服务技术的兴起
and the rise of containers and the micro service technology
导致了一些应用
actually resulted in applications that
现在已经由数百个或者有时甚至
they're now comprised of hundreds or sometimes maybe
数千个容器组成
even thousands of containers now
使用脚本和自制的工具
managing those loads of containers
跨多个环境
across multiple environments using
管理这些容器是非常复杂的
scripts and self-made tools can be really complex
有时对于某些场景
and sometimes even impossible so that
甚至是不可能的
specific scenario actually caused
这带来了对容器编排技术的需求
the need for having container orchestration
所以像k8s这样的编排工具
technologies so what those orchestration
做的工作
tools like kubernetes do
实际上是保证以下特性
is actually guarantee following features
一个是高可用性
one is high availability in simple words
高可用性意味着
high availability means that the
应用程序没有停机时间，所以总是用户可访问的
application has no downtime so it's always
第二个是可伸缩性
accessible by the users a second one is
可伸缩性意味着应用程序
scalability which means that application
具有较高的性能
has high performance
它的加载速度很快，用户从应用程序
it loads fast and the users have a very
可以获得一个非常高的响应率
high response rates from the application
第三个是灾难恢复
and the third one
灾难恢复意味着
is disaster recovery which basically
如果一个设备出现了某些问题
means that if an infrastructure has some problems
比如数据丢失或者服务器爆炸
like data is lost or the servers explode
或者服务器中心出了问题
or something bad happens with the server center
设备必须有某种
the infrastructure has to have some kind
备份数据的机制
of mechanism to back up the data
并将其恢复到最新状态
and to restore it to the latest state so
这样应用程序不会丢失任何数据
that application doesn't actually lose any data
而容器化的应用程序可以在恢复之后
and the containerized application can run from the
回到最新状态
latest state after the recovery and all
所有这些功能
of these are functionalities that
都由像k8s这样的容器编排技术所提供
container orchestration technologies like kubernetes offer
在这个视频中，我想给你们一个
so in this video i want to give you an
关于大部分k8s
overview of the most
基本组件的概览
basic fundamental components of
这些
kubernetes uh but just
足够让你开始在生产中使用kubernetes
enough to actually get you started using kubernetes
作为devops工程师或者一个软件开发人员
in practice either as a devops engineer or a software developer
kubernetes有很多组件
now kubernetes has tons of components but
但大多数时候你都是
most of the time you're going to be
只用其中的一小部分
working with just a handful of them
所以我要建立一个简单的例子
so i'm going to build a case of a simple
使用javascript应用程序
javascript application
搭配一个简单的数据库，我将要
with a simple database and i'm going to
一步一步来揭示
show you step by step
kubernetes的每个组件是如何
how each component of kubernetes
在实际中帮助你部署
actually helps you to deploy
您的应用程序的，以及每个组件
your application and what is the role of
在扮演什么样的角色
each of those components
我们从一个worker节点的基本构造开始
so let's start with the basic setup of a worker node
或者用kubernetes的术语来说，一个节点
or in kubernetes terms a node
节点可以是一个简单的物理的服务器，也可以是一个虚拟机
which is a simple server a physical or virtual machine
k8s中最基本的，或者说最小的单元
and the basic component or the smallest unit
被称为pod
of kubernetes is a pod so what pot is
pod基本上是一个容器的抽象
is basically an abstraction over a container
所以如果你熟悉docker容器
so if you're familiar with docker
或容器镜像
containers or container images
pod所做的就是创造
so basically what pod does is it creates
这样的运行环境
this running environment
或者在容器的顶部加一层
or a layer on top of the container and
这么做的原因是kubernetes想要
the reason is because kubernetes wants to
将容器运行时
abstract away the container runtime or
或容器技术 抽象出来
container technologies
这样你可以在想更换的时候随时更换
so that you can replace them if you want to
同时还有一部分原因是你也许不想直接在k8s中
and also because you don't have to directly uh work
使用docker或其他容器技术
with docker or whatever container technology
所以你可能只想
you use in a kubernetes so you only
与kubernetes层交互
interact with the kubernetes layer
所以我们用pod作为我们自己的应用程序
so we have an application pod which is our own application
它可能会使用数据库
and that will maybe use a database pod
pod有自己的容器，这也是一个重要的知识点
with its own container and this is also an important
pod通常只运行
concept here pod is usually meant to run
一个应用程序容器
one application container inside of it
然而您可以在一个pod里面运行多个容器
you can run multiple containers inside one pod
但通常只有一种情况，即
but usually it's only the case if you
pod中有一个主应用程序容器
have one main application container
和一个辅助容器或一些
and a helper container or some side
必须在pod里面运行的边缘服务
service that has to run inside of that
你看，这没什么特别的
pod and you see this is nothing special
你只是有一个服务器
you just have one server
里面还有两个容器
and two containers running on it with a
在其上有一个抽象层
abstraction layer on top of it
现在我们来看看在k8s的世界里
so now let's see how they communicate
它们是如何通信的
with each other in kubernetes world
kubernetes给出了开箱即用的
so kubernetes offers out of the box a
虚拟网络，即每个pod
virtual network which means that each
有自己的ip地址
pod gets its own ip address
pod获取ip，而不是容器
not the container the pod gets the ip
每个pod之间
address and each pod
可以使用该ip地址互相交流
can communicate with each other using
该ip地址是一个内部ip
that ip address which is an internal ip
显然不是外部可访问的
address obviously it's not the
所以我的应用程序容器
public one so my application container
可以通过ip地址与数据库通信
can communicate with database using the ip address
然而，在k8s中的pod组件
however pod components in kubernetes
还有一个重要的概念是 临时性
also an important concept are ephemeral
也就是说
which means that they can die
这些pod会非常容易“死”
very easily and when that happens for
比如我可能会因为容器崩溃
example if i lose a database container
或者应用程序内部崩溃
because the container crashed because
或者因为我所在的服务器节点资源耗尽
the application crashed inside
那么pod会“死”
or because the nodes the server that i'm running them
此时我们丢失了一个数据库容器
on ran out resources the pod will die
而一个新的pod会被重新创建
and a new one will get created in its
如果这发生了
place and when that happens
它将被分配一个新的ip地址
it will get assigned a new ip address
这显然很不方便，如果你在用ip地址
which obviously is inconvenient if you are
与数据库通信
communicating with the database using
因为现在你必须
the ip address because now you have to
在pod重启时再做调整
adjust it every time
由于这个原因，另一个重要的
pod restarts and because of that another
kubernetes的组件--“Service”派上了用场
component of kubernetes called service is used
service基本上是一个静态ip地址
so service is basically a static ip
或永久ip地址
address or permanent ip address
它可以被赋给每一个pod
that can be attached so to say to each pod
所以我的应用会有自己的service
so my app will have its own service and
数据库pod也将拥有自己的service
database pod will have its own service
好在service的生命周期
and the good thing here is that the life cycles
并不与pod相关联
of service and the pod are not connected
所以即使
so even if the
pod终止服务，service及其ip地址
pod dies the service and its ip address
将会被保留，这样你就不用做调整了
will stay so you don't have to change that
很明显现在
endpoint anymore so now obviously you
你想要你的应用程序
would want your application
可以通过浏览器访问
to be accessible through a browser right
为此你必须创造一个
and for this you would have to create
外部service
an external service so external service
这是一种可以
is a service that
与外部源通信的service
opens the communication from external sources
但显然你不会想让你的
but obviously you wouldn't want your
数据库也对外开放
database to be open to the
因此你将
public requests and for that you would
创建一个所谓的
create something called an
内部service，这也是service的一种类型
internal service so this is a type of a
你可以在创建service时
service that you
指定其类型，但是请注意
specify when creating one however if you notice
外部service的url
the url of the external service is
并不是很实用，基本上就是
not very practical so basically what you have
一个http协议
is uh an http protocol with
节点的ip地址（注意是节点而不是服务）
a node ip address so of the node
和这个service的端口号
not the service and the port number of
这很适合
the service which is
测试目的
good for test purposes if you want to
如果快速测试一些东西的话
test something very fast
但通常对最终产品来说并不好
but not for the end product so usually
您可能希望您的url看起来像这样
you would want your url to look like
你可能想通过
this if you want to
安全的https协议以及一个域名
talk to your application with a secure protocol
与应用程序通信
and a domain name and for that there is
为此，你需要kubernetes的另一个重要组件
another component of kubernetes called
Ingress
而不是service
so instead of service the request goes
请求首先进入Ingress，然后转发到Service
first to ingress and it does the forwarding then
现在我们看到了一些
to the service so now we saw some of the
kubernetes的基本组件
very basic components of kubernetes
正如你看到的，这是一个非常简单的配置
um and as you see this is a very simple
只有一个服务器
setup we just have a one server
还有几个运行的容器
um and a couple of containers running
以及一些服务，这些看起来没什么特别的
and some services nothing really special
看不出kubernetes的优势在哪里
where kubernetes advantages or the
也看不出k8s真正酷的特性
actual cool features
但我们要
really uh come forward but we're gonna
一步一步来
get there step by step
所以我们继续
so let's continue
就像我们说的，pod可以通过使用service
so as we said pods communicate with each other
实现相互通信，我的应用程序将
using a service so my application will
有一个数据库端endpoint
have a database
我们命名其为mongo-db-service
endpoint let's say called mongodb service
它用来和数据库通信
that it uses to communicate with the
然而
database but
您也许可以配置修改
whether you configure usually this
数据库url或
database url or
数据库的端点，通过修改
endpoint usually you would do it in application
程序的属性文件或某种类型的
properties file or as some kind of
外部环境变量
external environmental variable but
然而这些通常需要在已构建的应用程序镜像的内部来实现
usually it's inside of the built
举例来说
image of the application so for example
如果service的端点或service名称
if the endpoint of the service or service name
在本例中被更改为mongo-db
in this case changed to mongodb you
你还需要调整应用程序中的url
would have to adjust that url
所以你通常不得不
in the application so usually you'd have to
重新构建新版本的应用程序
rebuild the application with a new
并更新到仓库中去
version and you have to push it to the repository
之后你要在pod中拉取构建后的新镜像
and now you'll have to pull that new image
并全部重启
in your pod and restart the whole thing
所以
so
因为一点小改动，比如数据库url更改
a little bit tedious for a small change like
而要做这么多工作，着实有点繁琐
database url so for that purpose
为此，kubernetes提供一种
kubernetes has
叫做ConfigMap的组件
a component called config map so what it
它可以从外部来
does is it's basically your external
对应用程序进行配置
configuration to your application
所以ConfigMap通常包含配置数据
so config map would usually contain configuration data
比如您常用的数据库
like urls of a database or some other
或其他service的url
services that you use
在kubernetes中，你只需要把它连接到pod
and in kubernetes you just connect it to the pod
这个pod就可以获得ConfigMap包含的数据
so that pod actually gets the data that config map
现在如果您更改service的名称
contains and now if you change the name of the service
或者service的端点
the endpoint of the service you just
只需要调整ConfigMap
adjust the config map
就这样，你不需要构建一个
and that's it you don't have to build a
新的镜像，不必
new image and have to
经历这整个循环
go through this whole cycle now part of the
外部配置也可以是
external configuration can also be
数据库用户名和密码
database username and password
这些在应用程序部署过程中
right which may also change in the
也可能会发生变化
application deployment process
但是密码之类的
but putting a password or other
凭证信息放在ConfigMap这种
credentials in a config map
纯文本的格式中是不安全的
in a plain text format would be insecure
即使它是外部配置
even though it's an external
为此
configuration so for this purpose
kubernetes有另一个组件叫做
kubernetes has another component called
Secret
Secret就像ConfigMap
so secret is just like config map but
二者区别在于
the difference
Secret是用来存储秘密数据的
is that it's used to store secret data
例如凭证，它被存储起来
credentials for example and it's stored
不是以纯文本格式，而是
not in a plain text format of course but in
64进制编码格式
base 64 encoded format so
所以Secret可以包含凭证之类的数据
secret would contain things like credentials
当然，数据库用户名
and of course i mean database user you
也可以放入ConfigMap中
could also put in config map
但重要的密码凭证
but what's important is the passwords certificates
那些你不想让别人能接触到的东西
things that you don't want other people to have access to
可以放入Secret中，就像ConfigMap
would go in the secret and just like ConfigMap
你只要把它连到你的pod里
you just connect it to your pod so that
pod可以看到这些数据
pod can actually see those data
并从Secret中读取
and read from the secret you can
你可以将
actually use the
pod里的ConfigMap或Secret
data from configmap or secret inside of
用于
your application pod
存储如环境变量
using for example environmental
甚至
variables or even as
作为一个属性文件，现在回顾一下
a properties file so now to review we've
我们已经学习了
actually looked at
几乎所有最常用的kubernetes基本组件
almost all mostly used kubernetes basic components
我们已经学习了
we've looked at the pod we've seen
怎么用Service，什么是Ingress
how services are used what is ingress component
我们也学习了如何从外部进行配置
useful for and we've also seen external configuration
通过使用ConfigMap和Secret
using config map and secrets
现在我们来看另一个非常重要的概念
so now let's see another very important concept
一般来说，就是数据存储
generally which is data storage and how
它在kubernetes中如何工作
it works in kubernetes
我们的应用程序有数据库部分
so we have this database part that our
它有一些数据或者
application uses and it has some data or
它生成一些数据，通过这种设置
it generates some data with this setup that you see now
如果数据库容器或pod被重新启动
if the database container or the pod gets restarted
数据就会消失
the data would be gone and that's
这样有问题
problematic and
而且很不方便，如果你想要
inconvenient obviously because you want
您的数据库数据或日志数据
your database data or log data
可长期可靠地持续使用的话
to be persisted reliably long term
你可以在kubernetes中这样做,通过使用
and the way you can do it in kubernetes is using
kubernetes的另一个组件
another component of kubernetes called
Volumes
它的工作原理是连接
and how it works is that it basically attaches
硬盘上的物理存储器到你的pod上
a physical storage on a hard drive to your pod
存储空间可以在
and that storage could be either on a
本地机器，即pod运行时所处的相同
local machine meaning on the same
服务器节点
server node where the pod is running or
也可能在远程存储器上
it could be on a remote storage
意思是kubernetes集群之外的机器
meaning outside of the kubernetes
它可以是
cluster it could be
云存储或者你自己的
a cloud storage or it could be your own
第三方存储
premise storage
注意，存储并不是kubernetes集群的一部分
which is not part of the kubernetes
所以你只是有一个外部的
cluster so you just have an external
引用
reference on it
现在当数据库pod或
so now when the database pod or
容器被重新启动
container gets restarted
所有的数据都将保存在那里
all the data will be there persisted
重要的是要理解
it's important to understand the
k8s集群与
distinction between the kubernetes cluster
它的所有组件和
and all of its components and the
存储之间的区别
storage
不管它是本地的还是
regardless of whether it's a local or
远程存储
remote storage
可以把存储器看作是一个外部硬盘
think of a storage as an external hard drive
插入到kubernetes集群中
plugged in into the kubernetes cluster
因为kubernetes集群是
because the point is kubernetes cluster
不负责
explicitly doesn't manage
任何数据持久性的，这意味着
any data persistence which means that
您是kubernetes的用户
you as a kubernetes user
或管理员，那您就要负责
or an administrator are responsible for
备份数据
backing up the data
复制、管理并保证数据被
replicating and managing it and making sure that it's
保存在适当的硬件等
kept on a proper hardware etc
因为这不关k8s的事
because it's not taking care of kubernetes
现在让我们看看所有东西都在运行
so now let's see everything is running
运行完全正确，用户可以通过浏览器，在这样的设置下
perfectly and a user can access our application
访问我们的应用程序
through a browser now with this setup
但如果我的应用程序pod死了
what happens if my application pod dies
崩溃了，或我必须重新启动pod时，会发生什么
right crashes or i have to restart the
因为我建了一个新的容器镜像
pod because i built a new container image
基本上我会有一段宕机时间
basically i would have a downtime where
用户不可以访问我的应用程序
a user can reach my application
如果它发生在生产过程中
which is obviously a very bad thing if
这显然是一件非常糟糕的事情
it happens in production
能够恰当处理这类情况正是
and this is exactly the advantage of
分布式系统和容器技术的优势所在
distributed systems and containers
不只依赖一个应用程序pod
so instead of relying on just one application part and
和一个数据库pod等等
one database pod etc we are replicating
我们复制所有东西在多个服务器上
everything on multiple servers
所以我们有另一个节点
so we would have another node where a
作为我们的应用程序的
replica or clone
副本或克隆
of our application would run which will
复制后的也要连接到service上
also be connected to the service
记住之前我们说过
so remember previously we said the
service就像一个
service is like an
带dns的持久静态ip地址
persistent static ip address with a dns name
这样你就不必不断地
so that you don't have to constantly adjust
在pod死亡之后做调整，同时
the end point when a pod dies but
service也是一个负载均衡器
service is also a load balancer
也就是说service会
which means that the service will
捕获请求并转发
actually catch the request and forward
到最不忙碌的地方去
it to whichever part is least busy
所以它有这两种功能
so it has both of these functionalities
但是为了创造
but in order to create the
应用程序所在pod的副本
the second replica of the my application pod
你并不应该再创建一个一样的东西
you wouldn't create a second part but
相反，你应该为应用程序pod
instead you would define a blueprint
定义一个蓝图，指定要有多少份
for a my application pod and specify how many replicas
你想用来执行的pod副本
of that pod you would like to run and
那个组件或者蓝图
that component or that blueprint
被称为Deployment，它是另一个k8s的组件
is called deployment which is another component of
实际场景中你将不会
kubernetes and in practice you would not
直接与多个pod协作，或者说你不会创建pod来做副本
be working with pods or you would not be creating pods
您将创建Deployment
you would be creating deployments
因为这样你可以指定
because there you can specify
有多少个副本，同时你还可以增加或减少
how many replicas and you can also scale up or scale down
你所需的pod副本的数量
the number of replicas of pods that you
所以我们说pod是一个
need so with pod we said that pod is a
在容器之上的层的抽象
layer of abstraction
而Deployment是
on top of containers and deployment is
另一个在pod之上的抽象
another abstraction on top of pots which
使得与pod交互更加方便
makes it more convenient to interact with the pods
用于复制pod，以及做其他的配置
replicate them and do some other configuration
所以在实践中，你大部分时间都在
so in practice you would mostly work
使用Deployment而不是pod
with deployments and not with pods
所以现在如果应用程序pod的一个副本
so now if one of the replicas of your
将要消亡
application pod would die
Service将把请求转发给
the service will forward the requests to
另一个副本，这样你的应用程序
another one so your application would
用户仍然可以访问
still be accessible for the user
现在你可能想知道
so now you're probably wondering what
数据库pod怎么办
about the database pod
因为如果数据库pod死了
because if the database pod died your
应用程序也将不可访问
application also wouldn't be
所以我们需要一个数据库副本
accessible so we need a database
然而我们不能
replica as well however we can't
使用Deployment复制数据库
replicate database using a deployment
原因是
and the reason for that is because database
数据库有状态信息，这意味着如果我们有
has a state which is its data meaning that if we have
数据库的克隆或副本
clones or replicas of the database they
都需要
would all need to
访问相同的共享数据存储
access the same shared data storage
在那里你需要某种机制来管理
and there you would need some kind of mechanism that manages
哪些pod正在写内容到存储中
which pods are currently writing to that storage
或者是哪个pod从
or which pods are reading from the
存储中读取数据以便
storage in order to
避免数据不一致
avoid data inconsistencies and
而这样的补充拷贝的机制
that mechanism in addition to replicating
该功能由另一个kubernetes组件提供
feature is offered by another kubernetes component
这个组件叫StatefulSet
called stateful set so this component
是专门为数据库这样的应用而设计的
is meant specifically for applications like databases
所以mysql mongodb elasticsearch
so mysql mongodb elasticsearch
或任何其他有状态的应用程序
or any other stateful applications or
或数据库
databases
都应该使用StatefulSet创建
should be created using stateful sets
而不是Deployment
and not deployments
这是一个非常重要的区别
it's a very important distinction and
StatefulSet就像Deployment一样
stateful set just like deployment
能帮我复制pod
would take care of replicating the pods
并将副本的规模进行缩放
and scaling them up or scaling them down
但要确保数据库
but making sure the database
读取和写入是同步的
reads and writes are synchronized so
即没有数据库不一致的情况
that no database inconsistencies
但是我必须在这里提到的是
are offered however i must mention here that
使用StatefulSet部署k8s集群中的数据库应用
deploying database applications using stateful sets
是比较枯燥的
in kubernetes cluster can be somewhat tedious
所以这绝对比
so it's definitely more difficult than
使用Deployment更困难，因为后者没有那么多挑战
working with deployments where you don't have
这就是为什么
all these challenges that's why it's
一种常见的做法是
also a common practice
在k8s集群外部托管
to host database applications outside of
数据库应用程序
the kubernetes cluster
k8s集群只部署无状态的应用程序
and just have the deployments or stateless applications
这样在kubernetes集群内部做复制和扩展
that replicate and scale with no problem
就都没有问题
inside of the kubernetes cluster
并可以与外部数据库通信
and communicate with the external
现在我们有两个
database so now that we have two
应用程序pod的副本
replicas of my application pod
和两个数据库的副本
and two replicas of the database and
它们都是负载平衡的
they're both load balanced
我们的配置更健壮，这意味着
our setup is more robust which means
现在
that now
即使节点1的整个节点服务器
even if node 1 the whole node server
重启或崩溃了
was actually rebooted or crashed
没有任何东西可以在上面运行，我们仍然
and nothing could run on it we would
还有第二个节点
still have a second node
可以运行应用程序和数据库pod
with application and database pods running on it
应用程序仍然是
and the application would still be
用户可访问的
accessible by the user
直到这两个副本被重新创建
until these two replicas get recreated
这样你就可以避免停机
so you can avoid downtime so to
总结一下
summarize
我们已经看了最常用的
we have looked at the most used
kubernetes组件
kubernetes components
我们从pod和Service入手
we start with the pods and the services
Service是为了能够实现pod之间的通信
in order to communicate between the pods
Ingress组件用来
and the ingress component which is used
路由接入我们的集群
to route traffic into the cluster we've
同时我们也研究了利用ConfigMap\Secret
also looked at external configuration
进行外部配置
using config maps and secrets and data persistence
以及用volume实现数据持久化，最后我们看了一下
using volumes and finally we've looked at
利用如Deployment和StatefulSet实现的
pod blueprints with replicating mechanisms
副本机制，即pod蓝图
like deployments and stateful sets where
StatefulSet
专门用于有状态应用程序(如数据库）
is used specifically for stateful applications like
当然，还有很多
databases and yes there are a lot more
kubernetes组件
components that kubernetes
但是这些是真正的核心，是最基本的组件
offers but these are really the core the basic ones
只需使用这些核心组件即可
just using these core components you can
构建出非常强大的kubernetes集群
actually build pretty powerful kubernetes clusters
在这段视频中，我们将讨论
in this video we're gonna talk about basic
kubernetes的基本架构，所以我们要学习
architecture of kubernetes so we're gonna look at
kubernetes操纵的两种类型的节点
two types of nodes that kubernetes operates on
一个是master，另一个是slave
one is master and another one is slave
我们来看看
and we're gonna see what is the
它们的区别
difference between those and which
它们各自在集群中扮演什么角色
role each one of them has inside of the cluster
我们来看看最基本的一些概念
and we're going to go through the basic
关于kubernetes做什么，怎么做
concepts of how kubernetes does
集群是怎样进行
what it does and how the cluster is
自我管理和自我修复
self-managed and self-healing
以及自动化工作的，你作为一个
and automated and how you as a operator
kubernetes集群的操作员
of the kubernetes cluster
最后应该有更少的手动操作
should end up having much less manual effort
我们从一个节点的基本设置开始
and we're going to start with this basic
该节点
setup of one node
有两个应用程序部分在上面运行
with two application parts running on it
所以k8s架构一个主要的组成部分是
so one of the main components of kubernetes architecture
它的worker服务器或者说worker节点
are its worker servers or nodes and each
每个节点将有多个
node will have multiple
在该节点运行容器的应用程序pod
application pods with containers running on that node
kubernetes的方法是使用三个进程
and the way kubernetes does it is using three processes
必须安装在每个节点上
that must be installed on every node
用于计划和管理这些pod
that are used to schedule and manage those parts
节点就是实际工作的集群服务器
so nodes are the cluster servers that actually do
这就是为什么有时候管它们叫worker节点
the work that's why sometimes also called worker nodes
所以第一个在每个节点上都需要运行的进程
so the first process that needs to run
是容器运行时
on every node is the container runtime
在我的例子中，是docker
in my example i have docker
但也可能是其他的技术
but it could be some other technology as
因为应用程序pods内有
well so because application pods have
运行的容器
containers running inside a container
运行时需要安装在每个节点
runtime needs to be installed on every node
而实际上对这些pod和容器
but the process that actually schedules
进行调度的进程
those pods and the containers then underneath
则是kubelet，它是k8s的一个进程
is cubelet which is a process of kubernetes
它本身不同于容器运行时
itself unlike container runtime that has
它同时具备既可以与容器运行时
interface with both container runtime
又可以与机器本身，即节点进行交互的接口，因为
and the machine the node itself because
到头来是kubelet
at the end of the day cubelet is
负责接受配置信息
responsible for taking that configuration
并在实际场景中运行或者启动一个
and actually running a pod or starting a pod
里面有容器的pod，然后
with a container inside and then assigning
将该节点的资源分配给容器
resources from that node to the container
比如cpu ram和存储资源
like cpu ram and storage resources so
所以kubernetes集群通常是由
usually kubernetes cluster is made up
也必须由多个节点组成
of multiple nodes which also must have
同时也必须安装好容器运行时和kubelet服务
container runtime and kubelet services
你可以有几百个worker节点
installed and you can have hundreds of
来运行
those worker nodes which will run
其他部分、容器
other parts and containers and replicas
和现有部分的副本
of the existing parts
就像我的应用程序和数据库部分在这个例子里
like my app and database parts in this example
而它们之间交互的方式
and the way that communication between them works
则是使用Service，是一种
is using services which is sort of
基本的负载均衡器
a load balancer that basically catches
能够捕获指向pod
the request
或应用程序的请求
directed to the pod or the application
比如数据库
like database for example
然后把它转发给相应的pod
and then forwards it to the respective
第三个进程
pod and the third process
负责转发请求
that is responsible for forwarding
从服务转发到pod
requests from services to pods
该进程就是kube proxy，其也是必须安装在
is actually cube proxy that also must be installed
在每个节点的，kube proxy事实上
on every node and q proxy has actually
内部有智能转发逻辑
intelligent forwarding logic inside
这确保了通信能够
that makes sure that the communication
以高效、低额外开支的方式进行
also works in a performant
例如如果一个应用程序
way with low overhead for example if an application
my-app副本正在发出数据库请求
my app replica is making a requested database
相比于Service随机
instead of service just randomly
转发请求到
forwarding the request to
任何可能的副本，智能转发机制会
any replica it will actually forward it
将请求转发到运行在相同节点上的副本
to the replica that is running on the same node
作为发起请求的pod
as the pod that initiated the request
因此这样就避免了发送请求给另一台机器
thus this way avoiding the network overhead
所带来的网络开销
of sending the request
做个总结
to another machine so to summarize
两个kubernetes进程，kubelet
two kubernetes processes cubelet
和kubeproxy都必须安装在
and cubeproxy must be installed
每个kubernetes的worker节点上
on every kubernetes worker node along
同时还要有独立的容器运行时
with an independent container runtime
从而使kubernetes集群正常工作
in order for kubernetes cluster to function properly
但现在的问题是你将如何
but now the question is how do you
与这个集群交互
interact with this cluster
你该如何决定哪个节点的
how do you decide on which node a new
应用程序pod或数据库pod应该被调用
application pod or database pod should be scheduled or
或者如果一个pod死亡了，哪个进程可以
if a replica pod dies what process
监控它，然后
actually monitors it and then
重新安排或者重新启动
reschedules it or restarts it again or
抑或添加另一个新的服务器
when we add another
如何让他加入集群
server how does it join the cluster to become
成为另一个节点，并获取
another node and get parts and other
在上面创建的组件的信息
components created on it
答案是所有这些管理工作
and the answer is all these managing
都是由master节点完成的
processes are done by master nodes
所以master服务器或者说master节点
so master servers or masternodes have
在内部是有完全不同的
completely different
运行的进程的
processes running inside and these are
每个master节点有四个进程要运行
four processes that run on every masternode
来控制集群状态和worker节点
that control the cluster state and the worker nodes as well
第一个服务是api服务器
so the first service is api server
所以当你作为一个用户想要部署一个新的应用程序
so when you as a user want to deploy a new application
到kubernetes集群中，您可以通过一些客户端
in a kubernetes cluster you interact
与api服务器进行交互
with the api server using some client it
它可以是图形界面
could be a ui
就像kubernetes dashboard一样
like kubernetes dashboard could be
可以是命令行工具，如kubelet（这里口误，应是kubectl）
command line tool like cubelet
或者kubernetes提供的代码api
or a kubernetes api so api server
api服务器就像一个集群网关
is like a cluster gateway
获取任何更新到集群的初始请求
which gets the initial request of any
甚至集群的查询
updates into the cluster or even the queries
它也作为一个看门人
from the cluster and it also acts as a gatekeeper
进行身份验证以确保
for authentication to make sure that
只有经过认证和授权的请求 requests
only authenticated and authorized
能够进入集群，这意味着
get through to the cluster that means
当你想调度新的pod
whenever you want to schedule new pods
部署新的应用程序
deploy new applications create new
创建新的服务或任何其他组件时
service or any other components
您必须与master节点上的api服务器进行通信
you have to talk to the api server on the master node
然后api服务器会验证你的请求
and the api server then validate your request
如果一切都好，它就会
and if everything is fine then it will
转发你的要求
forward your request
到其它进程，从而
to other processes in order to
调度pod或创建这个
schedule the pod or create this
您要求的组件
component that you requested
如果你想查询状态
and also if you want to query the status of your
如部署或集群运行状况等
deployment or the cluster health etc you
你可以向api服务器发出请求
make a request to the api
它将向您响应
server and it gives you the response
这对安全有好处，因为你只能通过
which is good for security because you just have
一个进入集群的入口点查询
one entry point into the cluster another
另一个重要进程是调度器
master process is a scheduler so as i
就像我之前提到的
mentioned if you
如果你向api服务器发送一个请求来调度
send an api server a request to schedule
一个新的pod
a new pod
api服务器验证了你的请求后
api server after it validates your request
会将它移交给调度器
will actually hand it over to the
接着
scheduler in order to
启动众多worker节点中的
start that application pod on one of the
一个应用程序pod
worker nodes
当然，这不是随机的
and of course instead of just randomly
不会随机分配给任何节点
assigning it to any node
调度器有完善的智能的
schedule has this whole intelligent
决定采用哪个worker的方法
way of deciding on which specific worker node
来决定调度下一个pod
the next pod will be scheduled or next
或下一个组件
component will be scheduled so first it
首先它会看你的请求
will look at your request
看看您想要调度的应用程序
and see how much resources the
需要多少资源
application that you want to schedule
需要多少cpu多少内存
will need how much cpu how much ram
然后它会看
and then it it's going to look at and
worker节点
it's going to go through the worker nodes
并查看各自的可用资源
and see the available resources on each
其中的一个
one of them
如果这个节点
and if it says that one node
最不忙或者
is the least busy or has the most
可用资源最多
resources available
新的部分就会安排在这个节点上
it will schedule the new part on that node
这里重要的一点是
an important point here is that
调度器只是决定
scheduler just decides
新的pod将在哪个节点上被调度
on which node a new pod will be
实际上执行调度操作
scheduled the process that actually
和启动相应带容器的pod
does the scheduling that actually starts
的进程
that pod with a container
则是kubelet，它从调度器
is the cubelet so it gets the request
获得请求
from the scheduler
并在该节点上执行该请求
and executes that request on that node
下一个组件是controller manager
the next component is controller manager
它另一个关键的组件
which is another crucial component
因为当
because what happens when
某一个节点上的部分崩溃了，必须有一种方法能够
parts die on any node there must be a way to
检测到节点死亡
detect that the nodes died and then reschedule
然后尽快重新调度
those parts as soon as possible so what
所以Controller manager的工作就是
controller manager does
检测状态的变化
is detect state changes like
比如pod的崩溃
crashing of pods for example so when
所以当pod死了
pods die
Controller manager检测并
controller manager detects that and
试图尽快恢复
tries to recover
集群状态
the cluster state as soon as possible
因此
and for that
它向调度程序发出请求
it makes a request for the scheduler to
重新调度那些死去的部分
reschedule those dead parts
刚刚提到的流程也会重新发生
and the same cycle happens here where
调度器根据资源计算决定
the scheduler decides based on the resource calculation
哪些工作节点应该重新启动
which worker nodes should restart those spots again
并向相应的对象发出请求
and makes requests to the corresponding
在那些worker节点的
cubelets on those
kubelet实际重新启动pod
worker nodes to actually restart the pods
最后一个主进程是etcd
and finally the last master process is
etcd是一个集群状态的键值存储
etcd which is a key value store of a cluster state
你可以把它想象成一个集群大脑
you can think of it as a cluster brain actually
也就是说集群的每一次变化
which means that every change in the cluster
例如，当一个新的pod被调度
for example when a new pod gets
当一个pod死亡
scheduled when a pod dies
所有这些更改都会被保存
all of these changes get saved or
更新到这个etcd键值存储区
updated into this key value store
为什么说etcd
of etcd and the reason why at cd store
是一个集群大脑
is a cluster brain
是因为所有的这些机制
is because all of this mechanism with
调度器，Controller manager等等都需要数据
scheduler controller manager etc works because
才能工作，比如说
of its data so for example
调度器如何知道在每个工作节点上
how does scheduler know what resources
哪些资源是可用的
are available on on each worker node or how does
Controller manager如何知道
controller manager know that
集群状态以某种方式发生了改变
a cluster state changed in some way for
比如pod死亡
example pods died
或者kubelet重启了新的pod
or that cubelet restarted new pods upon
在响应了调度器的请求后
the request of a scheduler
或者当你向api服务器发出查询请求时
or when you make a query request to api
想要了解关于集群运行状况
server about the cluster health
或者你的应用程序的
or for example your application
部署状态时
deployment state
api服务器从哪里获得所有这些状态
where does api server get all this state information from
所有这些信息都存储在etcd
so all of this information is stored in etcd
那些没有存储在etcd键值存储中的内容
cluster what is not stored in the etcd key value store
就是实际的应用程序数据
is the actual application data for
举个例子，如果你有
example if you have a
数据库应用程序运行在一个集群上
database application running inside of a cluster
数据将被存储在其他地方
the data will be stored somewhere else
而不是在etcd，这里只有
not in the etcd this is just a cluster state
给master进程的
information which is used for master
用于和worker进程通信的
processes to communicate with them work
集群状态信息，反之亦然
processes and vice versa so now you
所以你已经知道master进程
probably already see that master
对于集群操作
processes are absolutely crucial
是至关重要的，特别是etcd存储
for the cluster operation especially the etcd
其中包含一些必须被可靠存储或复制的数据
store which contains some data must be reliably stored
所以在实践中kubernetes集群
or replicated so in practice kubernetes cluster
通常是由多个master组成
is usually made up of multiple masters
其中每个master节点
where each masternode
运行它的主进程
runs its master processes where of
当然，api服务器是负载均衡的
course the api server is
而且etcd在所有master节点间
load balanced and the etcd store forms a
构成分布式存储
distributed storage across all the master nodes
现在我们学习了运行在master节点和worker节点上
so now that we saw what processes run
的进程
on worker nodes and masternodes let's
我们再来看一下
actually have a look at a
一个真实的集群设置案例
realistic example of a cluster setup so
在一个非常小的集群
in a very small
你可能有两个master节点
cluster you would probably have two masternodes
还有三个worker节点
and three worker nodes also to note here
需要注意的是，master节点和worker节点的
the hardware resources of master
主机硬件资源实际上是不同的
and node servers actually differ the
master进程更重要，但是
master processes are more important but
他们实际上有
they actually have
更少的工作负荷，所以他们需要的资源也更少
less load of work so they need less
如cpu ram和存储器
resources like cpu ram and storage
而worker节点执行实际的任务
whereas the worker nodes do the actual
运行包含有容器的pod
job of running those
因此
pods with containers inside therefore
他们需要更多的资源
they need more resources
对着你的应用程序的复杂性以及
and as your application complexity and
对资源的需求增加
its demand of resources increases
你可以需要添加更多的master和worker服务器
you may actually add more master and node
到您的集群，因此
servers to your cluster and thus
形成了更强大、更稳健的集群
forming a more powerful and robust cluster
以满足您的应用程序资源需求
to meet your application resource requirements
在现有的kubernetes集群中
so in an existing kubernetes cluster you
添加新的master和worker服务器
can actually add new master or node
是很容易的
servers pretty easily
如果你想添加一个master服务器
so if you want to add a master server
你只需要一台裸机
you just get a new bare
你安装所有的master进程
server you install all the master
并将其添加到
processes on it and add it to the
kubernetes集群
kubernetes cluster
如果需要两个worker节点，也可以这样做
same way if you need two worker nodes you get
找两台裸机，安装所有的worker进程
bare servers you install all the worker
如容器运行时
node processes like container runtime
kubelet和kube proxy
kubelet and kube proxy on it
并将其添加到kubernetes集群中
and add it to the kubernetes cluster
就是这样，这样你就可以
that's it and this way you can infinitely
无限增加你的kubernetes集群的
increase the power and resources of your
能力和资源
kubernetes cluster
随着您的副本的复杂性和
as your replication complexity and its
对资源需求的增加
resource demand increases
在这个视频中，我将向你们展示
so in this video i'm going to show you
什么是Minikube和Kubectl
what miniKube and Kubectl are
以及如何建立它们，首先
and how to set them up so first of all
让我们看看什么是Minikube
let's see what is
在kubernetes的世界里
mini cube usually in kubernetes world
当你设置一个产品的集群时
when you are setting up a production
它看起来是这样的
cluster it will look something like this
你会有多个Master
so you would have multiple masters
在生产场景中至少有两个
at least two in a production setting and
您将有多个worker节点
you would have multiple worker nodes
master节点和worker节点
and master nodes and the worker nodes have
各司其职
their own separate responsibility
就像你在图表上看到的
so as you see on the diagram you would
会有分离的
have actual separate
虚拟机或物理机各代表一个node
virtual or physical machines that each represent
现在如果你想在本地环境里
a node now if you want to test something
测试一些东西
on your local environment
或者如果你想快速尝试一些东西
or if you want to try something out very
举例来说
quickly for example
部署了新的应用程序或组件
deploying new application or new components
你想要在本地机器测试
and you want to test it on your local
显然要设置一个集群
machine obviously setting up a cluster
像这样
like this
会很困难
will be pretty difficult or maybe even
如果你没有足够的资源，甚至是不可能的事情
impossible if you don't have enough resources
资源如内存和cpu等等
like memory and cpu etc and exactly for
为解决这一问题
the use case
有一个开源工具
there's this open source tool that is
叫做Minikube
called a mini cube so what a mini cube is
它就是可以一个节点上部署集群
is basically one node cluster where
通过它可以在一个节点上部署master进程和worker进程
the master processes and the worker processes
使两者都运行在一个节点上，而这个节点将
both run on one node and this node will
有一个预装的docker容器运行时
have a docker container runtime pre-installed
这样你就能在该节点上运行
so you will be able to run the
容器或带容器的pod
containers or the pods with containers
而其在你的笔记本电脑上的运行方式
on this node and the way it's going to
是通过
run on your laptop is through
Virtualbox虚拟机或其他管理程序实现的
a virtual box or some other hypervisor
所以基本上Minicube会创建一个
so basically minicube will create a
virtual box
在你的笔记本电脑上，你会看到节点
on your laptop and the node that you see here
将在这个虚拟机中运行
as this node will run in that virtual box
所以总结一下，minicube是一个单节点
so to summarize minicube is a one node
kubernetes集群
kubernetes cluster
在你笔记本电脑的Virtual Box里运行
that runs in a virtual box on your laptop which
可以用于在本地
you can use for testing
测试kubernetes的配置，所以现在
kubernetes on your local setup so now
您已经建立了一个集群或者说微型集群
that you've set up a cluster
在你的笔记本电脑或个人电脑上
or a mini cluster on your laptop or pc
即本地机器上
on your local machine
你需要一些与集群交互的方法
you need some way to interact with a
从而创建
cluster so you want to create
组件、配置等等
components configure it etc and that's where
这就需要kubectl登场了
cubectl comes in the picture
现在有了这个虚拟节点
so now that you have this virtual node
在本地机器上
on your local machine
这代表你需要一些方式
that represents mini cube you need some way to
和集群交互，所以你需要在节点上
interact with that cluster so you need a
创建pod
way to create pods
和其他kubernetes组件的方法
and other kubernetes components on the
可以用kubectl
node and the way to do it
kubectl是k8s集群的命令行工具
is using cubectl which is a command line tool
让我们看看如何
for kubernetes cluster so let's see how
使用它
it actually works
记住，我们说过，minikube同时运行两种进程
remember we said that minicube runs both
master和worker进程，其中一个master进程
master and work processes so one of the master
被称为
processes called
api服务器实际上是指向kubernetes集群的
api server is actually the main entry
主要入口点，如果
point into the kubernetes cluster so if
你想在
you want to do
kubernetes里做任何事情都可以
anything in the kubernetes if you want
要配置任何内容
to configure anything create
创建任何组件，你必须先与api服务器交互
any component you first have to talk to the api server
与api服务器交互可以有
and the way to talk to the api server is
多种不同的方式
through different clients so you can
可以用一个像控制面板一样的ui
have a ui like a dashboard
也可以使用kubernetes api与它对话
you can talk to it using kubernetes api or
也可以用kubectl这样的命令行工具
a command line tool which is cubectl
kubectl实际上是
and cubectl is actually the most
三种方式中最强大的一个
powerful of all the three clients
因为使用kubectl你基本上可以做任何事
because with cubecdl you can basically do anything
在kubernetes中
in the kubernetes that you want and
在本视频教程中
throughout this video tutorials
我们将主要使用kubectl
we're going to be using cube ctl mostly
所以一旦kubectl
so once the cube ctl
向api服务器提交命令
submits commands to the api server to
创建组件、删除组件等
create components delete components etc
minikube节点上的worker进程
the work processes on minicube node
会实际执行
will actually make it happen so they
执行命令
will be actually executing the commands
从而创造组件，摧毁组件、
to create the parts to destroy the parts
创造Service等等
to create services etc
这就是Minikube的设置，以及
so this is the mini cube setup and this
kubectl与集群交互的方式
is how cube ctl is used to interact with the cluster
这里需要注意的重要一点是
an important thing to note here is that
kubectl不仅仅适用于minikube集群
kubectl isn't just for minikube cluster
如果你有一个云集群或混合集群
if you have a cloud cluster or a hybrid
kubectl都可以拿来
cluster whatever cube ctl
用于同任何类型的集群
is the tool to use to interact with
进行交互
any type of kubernetes cluster setup so
这是需要注意的一点
that's important to note here
现在我们知道了Minikube和kubectl是什么
so now that we know what minicube and cubectl are
让我们实际安装它们来进行实战
let's actually install them to see them in practice
我正在使用mac所以
i'm using mac so the installation
安装过程可能会更容易
process will probably be easier
但是我要把安装指南的链接
but i'm going to put the links to the
放到视频下方的简介中
installation guides in the description
所以你可以跟着他们
so you can actually follow them to
在您的操作系统上安装它
install it on your operating system
这里需要注意的一点是
just one thing to note here is that
minikube
需要虚拟化，因为我们
needs a virtualization because as we
提到它会运行
mentioned it's going to run
虚拟机或者虚拟机监控程序
in a virtual box setup or some hypervisor
所以您需要安装某种类型的
so you will need to install some type of
hypervisor，可以是virtualbox
hypervisor it could be virtualbox
我要安装一个虚拟机管理工具，但是
i'm gonna install a hyperkit but it's
要根据这些指令
gonna be in those step-by-step
一步步来
instructions as well
我来告诉你们怎么安装到mac上
so i'm gonna show you how to install it on a mac
我有一个MacOS mojave，所以我要
so i have a mac os mojave so i'm gonna
演示如何安装
show you how to install
这个macos版本的minikube，我
mini cube on this macos version and i'm
我要用brew来安装它
going to be using brew to install it
更新
so we're going to update
首先，我要安装
and the first thing is that i'm going to install
叫hyperkit的管理程序
a hypervisor hyper kit
我要使用到hyperkit
so i'm going to go with the hyperkit
继续，安装它
go ahead and install it
我之前已经安装好了
i already had it install it so with you
如果你是第一次做这件事
if you're doing it for the first time it
可能需要更久，因为它要下载所有的
might take uh longer because it has to download all
这些依赖关系
these dependencies and stuff
现在我要安装Minikube
and now i'm gonna install mini cube
minicube有一个kubectl
and here's the thing minicube has kubectl
作为依赖，所以当我执行这条指令时
as a dependency so when i execute this
它也会安装kubectl
it's going to install cube ctl as well
所以我不需要单独安装它
so i don't need to install it separately
我们看这里
so let's see here
安装minikube的依赖项
installing dependencies for mini cube
这是嗯
which is um
kubernetes cli，这就是kubectl
kubernetes cli this is cube ctl
因为我之前已经安装好了
again because i already had it installed before
它还有一个本地副本
it still has a local copy of the
这就是为什么安装得
dependencies that's why it's
非常快，如果你是第一次做
pretty fast it might take longer
可能需要更长的时间
if you're doing it for the first time so
那么现在所有的东西都安装好了
now that everything is installed let's
让我们检查一下命令
actually check the commands
kubectl命令应该可以工作
so cubectl command should be working
所以我得到了这个命令列表
so i get this list of the commands with
所以
cubectl so it's
在那里和minikube应该也能正常工作
there and minicube should be working as well
如你所见，minikube是和这个命令行工具配套的
and as you see minicube comes with this
安装非常简单
command line tool which is
只需要一个命令
pretty simple so with one command it's
能够把
going to bring
整个kubernetes集群塞进一个节点里
up the whole kubernetes cluster in this one node
然后你可以用它来做一些事情
setup and then you can do stuff with it
你可以停止或删除它
and you can just stop it or delete it
这很简单，现在我们把
it's pretty easy so now that we have
两个都安装了
both installed
命令就在这里
and the commands are there let's
让我们创建一个Minikube得k8s集群
actually create a mini cube kubernetes cluster
正如你看到的，这里有一个启动命令
and as you see there is a start command
我们把这些清空
let's actually clear this
这就是我们如何启动一个
so this is how we're going to start a
kubernetes集群
kubernetes cluster
执行minikube start，这里需要
q mini cube start and here is where the
一个安装好的管理程序
hypervisor installed comes in because
因为minikube
since mini cube
需要在虚拟环境中运行
needs to run in virtual environment
我们要
we're gonna
告诉minikube哪个管理程序
tell minicube which hypervisor
应该用于启动集群
it should use to start a cluster so for
所以我们会指定一个选项
that we're going to specify an option
即vm-driver
which is vm driver
这里我要设置之前安装的
and here i'm going to set the hyperkit
hyperkit作为管理程序
that i installed
所以我告诉minikube请使用hyperkit
so i'm telling minicube please use hyperkit
来启动这个虚拟minikube集群
hypervisor to start this virtual mini
当我执行这条命令时
cube cluster so when i execute this
它会再次下载一些东西
it's gonna download some stuff so again
第一次的话
it may take
可能需要
a little bit longer if you're doing it
更长一点的时间
for the first time
正如我提到的，minikube有预装的docker运行时
and as i mentioned minicube has docker
和docker守护进程
runtime or docker daemon
即使你没有安装docker
pre-installed so even if you don't have docker
在你的机器上它仍然可以工作，所以
on your machine it's still gonna work so
你可以
you would be able to
在里面创建容器，因为它
create containers inside because it
已经包含docker，这是一个
already contains docker which is a
很好的东西
pretty good thing
即使你之前没有安装过docker
uh if you don't have docker already installed so
好的现在提示kubectl配置为
done cube ctl is now configured to use
使用minikube，这意味着
mini cube which means
已经完成了minikube和kubectl的配置
the mini cube cluster is set up and kubectl command
它是用来与
which is meant to interact with the
kubernetes集群进行交互的
kubernetes clusters
与那个minikube集群相连
is also connected with that mini cube cluster
也就是说如果我
which means if i
写kubectl get nodes会收到
do cube ctl get nodes which just gets me
k8s节点的状态
a status of the notes of the kubernetes 04,480
它会告诉我这个minikube节点
it's going to tell me that the mini cube node
已经准备好了，如你所见这是唯一的节点
is ready and as you see it's the only node
它的作用是master，因为它
and it has a master role because it
显然需要运行master进程
obviously has to run the master processes
我也可以得到minikube的状态
and i can also get the status with minicube
执行minikube status，使我看到主机
executing minicube status so i see host
正在运行
is running
kubelet是一种Service
cubelet which is a service that actually runs the parts
使用容器运行时，现在运行中
using container runtime is running so
基本上一切都在运行
basically everything is running
顺便说一下，如果你想了解
and by the way if you want to see
更详细的kubernetes架构
kubernetes architecture in more detail
并进一步理解master和worker
and to understand how master
实际上如何工作的
and worker nodes actually work and what
以及所有这些进程都是什么
all these processes are
我有一个单独的视频
i have a separate video that covers
介绍kubernetes架构，你可以
kubernetes architecture so you can check
点击链接学习
it out on this link
我们也可以检查我们安装的
and we can also check which version of
是哪个版本的k8s
kubernetes we have
通常是
installed and usually it's going to be
最新版本
the latest version
通过kubectl version命令，你可以
so with cube ctl version you actually
知道客户端版本
know what the client version of
以及k8s的服务器版本
kubernetes is and what the server
都是多少
version of kubernetes is
这里我们用的是1.17
and here we see we're using 1.17
这就是在minikube集群中运行的
and that's the kubernetes version that
kubernetes的版本
is running in the mini cube cluster
所以如果你在输出中同时看到客户端版本和
so if you see both client version and
服务器版本
server version in the output it means
这意味着minikube
that mini cube
已经被正确安装了
is correctly installed so from this
所以此后
point on
我们将会
we're going to be interacting with the
使用kubectl与minikube集群进行交互
mini cube cluster using cubectl
minicube作为命令行工具
command line tool so minicube is
基本上只是针对启动
basically just for the startup
和删除集群时使用的，但是
and for deleting the cluster but
其他的配置
everything else configuring
我们将通过kubectl来执行
we're going to be doing through cubectl
我所执行的所有这些命令
and all these commands that i executed here
我会把它们放到一个列表里
i'm going to put them in a list in the
写在注释部分，这样你就可以复制了
comment section so you can actually copy them
在这段视频中，我将向你们展示一些
in this video i'm gonna show you some
基本kubectl命令
basic kubectl commands
以及如何在minikube中创建和调试pod
and how to create and debug pods in minicube
现在我们已经安装了minikube和kubectl
so now we have a mini cube cluster and
一旦集群被设置好
kube ctl installed and once the cluster
你要用kubectl
is set up you're going to be using
来做集群中的任何事情
cubectl to basically do anything in the cluster
比如创建组件，获取状态信息等等
to create components uh to get the
首先
status etc so first thing
我们只需要获取节点的状态
we are gonna just get the status of the nodes
我们看到有一个节点
so we see that there is one node which
是一个master
is a master
所有的事都要在那个节点上运行
and everything is gonna run on that node
因为它是minikube
because it's a mini cube
嗯，用kubectl，我可以检查pod
um so with kubectl i'll get i can check
我没有pod，这就是为什么显示
the pods and i don't have any that's why
没有资源
no resources
我可以检查service
i can check the services
get services
我只有一个默认service
and i just have one default service and
所以
so on so
用这个kubectl get，我可以列出任何
this kubectl get i can list any
kubernetes组件
kubernetes components
既然我们没有任何部分
so now since we don't have any parts
我们要创建一个
we're going to create one
创建kubernetes组件
and to create kubernetes components
可以用
there is
kubectl create命令
a kubectl create command
如果我在kubectl create后面输入help选项
so if i do help on that kubectl
我可以看到它的可用命令
create command i can see available commands for it
所以我可以创建所有这些组件
so i can create all these components
使用kubectl create
using cube ctl create
但列表里没有pod，因为
but there is no pod on the list because
在kubernetes的世界里
in kubernetes world the way it works is
pod是
that the pod
kubernetes集群的最小单位
is the smallest unit of the kubernetes
但通常
cluster but usually
实际上你并不是在创造pod
in practice you're not creating pots or
你不是直接和pod打交道
you're not working with the pods directly
在pod之上有一个抽象层
there is an abstraction layer over the
叫做Deployment
pots that is called
这就是我们要创建的
deployment so this is what we are going to be creating
所以需要
and that's going to create the parts
kubectl create deployment命令
underneath and this is a usage
来创建
of kubectl create deployment
还需要给出一个名字
so i need to give a name of the
然后提供一些选项
deployment and then provide some options
这个选择就是
and the option that is
需要的映像，因为pod
required is the image because the pod
需要基于某些
needs to be created based on certain
某些镜像
some image
或者某个容器的图像，让我们
or some container image so let's
继续，创建一个nginx的deployment
actually go ahead and create
所以输入kubectl create deployment
nginx deployment so cubectl
我们命名为nginx-depl
create deployment we let's call it nginx deployment um
image = nginx，它会从dockerhub
image equals nginx it's just going to
下载最新的nginx镜像
go ahead and download the latest nginx image from
这就是它做的事情
docker hub that's how it's going to work
当我执行这个的时候
so when i execute this
你可以看到nginx-depl已被创建
you see deployment nginx-depl
现在如果我写kubectl get deployment
created so now if i do kubectl get deployment
你看，我有一个deployment被创建了
you see that i have one deployment
它的状态是
created i have a status here
还没准备好，所以
which says it's not ready yet so
如果我写kubectl get pod
if i do kube ctl get pod
你看，现在我有一个pod
you see that now i have a pod which has
前缀是部署的名
a prefix of the deployment and some random
后面跟着随机的标签，它说正在创建容器
hash here and it says container creating
也就是它还没有准备好
so it's not ready yet
那么我再输入一次，它现在在运行
so if i do it again it's running and
操作方法就是
the way it works here is that when i
创建一个deployment
create a deployment
deployment有为了创建pod所需的
deployment has all the information or
所有的信息或者蓝图
the blueprint
这是
for creating the pod the for the this is
极简的或最基本的
the minimalistic or the most basic
deployment的配置
configuration for a deployment we're
我们只写了名字和镜像
just saying the name
剩下的按默认设置
and the image that's it the rest is just defaults
在deployment和pod之间
and between deployment and pod there
有另一个层
is another layer
由k8s的deployment自动管理
which is automatically managed by kubernetes
称为ReplicaSet，如果我这样写
deployment called replica set so if i do
kubectl get replicaset
replica和set一起写
written together you see i have
此时我有一个nginx-depl的ReplicaSet的标签
an nginx depl replica set
它还给了我一个状态信息
hash and it just gives me a state
如果你注意到pod的名字
and if you notice here the pod name
前缀是
has a prefix of
deployment名和ReplicaSet的id
deployment and the replica sets id and
然后是
then its
它自己的id，这就是pod的名称组成
own id so this is how the pod name is made up
ReplicaSet基本上是
and the replica set basically is
用于管理一个pod的副本
managing the replicas
在实践中你不必
of a pod you in practice will never
以任何方式
have to create replica set or delete a
创建或删除或更新一个ReplicaSet
replica set or update in any way
你将直接和deployment打交道
you're going to be working with
这会更加方便
deployments directly which is
因为在deployment里
more convenient because in deployment
您可以完整配置pod蓝图
you can configure the pod blueprint
你可以说你想要pod
completely you can say how many replicas
有多少个副本
of the pod you want
你也可以完成其他的配置
and you can do the rest of the
通过这条命令
configuration there here with this command
我们刚刚创建了一个pod，一个副本
we just created one pod or one replica
但如果你想要nginx部分有两个副本
but if you wanted to have two replicas of the
我们可以提供额外的选项
nginx part we can just provide as
这就是这些层是如何工作的
additional options so this is how the layers work
首先你要有deployment
first you have the deployment
deployment管理一个ReplicaSet
the deployment manages a replica set a
replica set管理所有pod的副本
replica set manages all the replicas
pod是
of that pod and the pod is
一个容器的抽象
again an abstraction of a container
deployment之下的一切
and everything below the deployment
应该由kubernetes自动管理
should be managed automatically by kubernetes
你不需要担心任何问题
you don't have to worry about any of
比如它要用的图像
it for example the image
我可以直接把它编辑进deployment里
that it uses i will have to edit that in
而不是在pod
the deployment directly and not in the pod
我们现在就开始吧
so let's go ahead and do that right away
我要这么做
so i'm going to do
kubectl edit deployment
提供名字nginx
and i'm going to provide the name nginx
我们得到一个自动生成的
and we get an auto-generated
deployment的配置文件
configuration file of the deployment
因为在我们刚刚给出的命令行中
because in the command line we just gave
其他选项都是默认选项
two options everything else is default
由kubernetes自动生成
and auto generated by kubernetes
你不需要理解这个
and you don't have to understand this
但是我会一个单独的视频
now but i'm going to make a separate video
将配置文件结构
where i break down the configuration
并分析配置文件的语法
file and the syntax
现在让我们
of the configuration file for now let's
继续
just go ahead
滚动到这个image
and scroll to the image which is
下面的某个地方
somewhere down below
假设我想修改版本为1.16
and let's say i want to fixate the version to 1.16 and
保存更改
save that change
正如你看到的deployment被编辑了
and as you see deployment was edited and
现在当我这么做的时候
now when i do
kubectl get pod
我看到那个旧的pod被终止了
i see that the old pod so
而另一个pod
this one here is terminating and another one
在25秒前被启动
started 25 seconds ago so
如果我再做一次，旧的部分就消失了
if i do it again the old part is gone
这个新的是用一个新的镜像创建的
and the new one got created with a new image
如果我输入kubectl get replicaset
and if i do if i get replica set
我看到旧的已经没有东西了
i see that the old one has no parts in it
新的刚刚被创建了
and a new one has been created as well
所以
so
我们刚刚编辑了deployment的配置
we just edited the deployment configuration
而在它下面的东西
and everything else below that got
也就自动更新了
automatically updated
这就是kubernetes的魔力
and that's the magic of kubernetes and
这就是它的工作原理
that's how it works
另一个非常实用的命令是kubectl logs
another very practical command is kubectl logs
它基本上可以展示
which basically shows you what the
在pod中运行的应用程序
application running inside the pod
记录的东西，如果我写kubectl logs
actually logged so if i do cube ctrl
它需要pod的名字
logs and i will need the pod name
我什么都拿不到，因为
for this um i will get nothing because
nginx没有记录任何东西，所以让我们
nginx didn't log anything so let's
用mongodb创建
actually create
另一个deployment
another deployment
给它命名为mongo-depl
from mongodb so let's call it deployment
指定镜像为mongo
and the image and the image will be
输入kubectl get ppod
on go so let's see ctrl
所以现在我有mongodb的deployment
pod so now i have the mongodb deployment
正在被创建
creating
继续，log一下
so let's go ahead and log that
这里的情况表示pod被创建了
this status here means that pod was
但是里面的容器
created but the container
还没有运转
inside the pod isn't running yet
当我试图log的时候
and when i try to log obviously
告诉我没有容器运行
tells me there is no container running
所以不会显示任何日志
so it can't show me any logs
让我们现在再来看看状态
so let's get the status again at this point if i'm
看到容器还没有启动
seeing that container isn't starting i
我可以
can actually
通过kube describe pod获取一些附加信息
get some additional information by kubectl describe
pod的名字写在这里
pod and the pod name which here shows me
现在它告诉我pod内发生了什么变化
what state changes happened inside the pod
它拉取镜像
so it pulled the image created the
创建并启动了一个容器
container and started container
再来kubectl get pod
so kubectl get pod it should be
应该已经运行起来了
running already
现在我们打印日志kubectl logs
so now let's log it cubectl logs
这里是log输出
and here we see the log output so it
花了一点时间
took a little bit
但这就是mongodb应用程序容器
but this is what the mongodb application container
实际在pod里的日志信息
actually logged inside the pod and
显然如果
obviously if
容器出了点问题
container has some problems it's going
为了帮助调试
to help with debugging
可以看看这个应用程序打印了什么
to see what the application is actually printing
我们把它清除掉，再来get pod
so let's clear that and get the pods again
另一个非常有用的命令是
so another very useful command when
用于当某些东西不工作时进行调试
debugging when something is not working
或者当你只想
or you just want to
看看pod里发生了什么时，所执行的命令
check what's going on inside the pod is
kubectl exec
基本上它所做的就是
so basically what it does is that it
获取mongodb应用程序容器的终端
gets the terminal of that mongodb application container
可以用it表示让kubectl exec
so if i do kubectl exec interactive
获取交互式终端
terminal that's what
需要pod的名称
i t stands for i will need the pod name
破折号
dash dash
通过这个命令，我得到
so so with this command i get the
mongodb应用容器的终端
terminal of the mongodb application container
你们可以看到，我在
and as you see here i am inside the
mongodb的容器里
container of mongodb
作为一个根用户，所以我在一个完全
as a root user so i'm in a completely
不同的设置中
different setting now
就像我说的，这在调试
and as i said this is useful in
或者当你想
debugging or when you want to
测试或尝试一些东西时会很有用
test something or try something you can
进入容器并获取终端
enter the container or get the terminal
并在里面执行一些命令
and execute some commands inside there
我们可以再次退出
so we can exit that again
当然，使用kubectl我可以删除pod
and of course with cubectl i can delete the pods so if i do
get deployment
哎呀deployment拼错了
let me spell that so it keeps it here deployment
可以看到有两个，如果我
i see that i have two of them and if i
输入kubectl get pod
do kubectl
我还是有两个
get pod and replica set i have also two of them
假设我想消掉
so let's say if i wanted to get rid of
所有的pod
all the pods
及其副本，就需要删除deployment
replica sets underneath i will have to delete
所以输入delete deployment
the deployment so delete
还必须提供
deployment and i'll have to provide the
deployment的名称
name of the deployment
让我们删除mongodb
i'm gonna delete let's delete mongodb
删除它，再输入
delete it and now if i'm gonna say
kubectl get pod
这部分应该终止了，如果我
the part should be terminating and if i do
输入get replicaset
get replica set the
mongodb的replicaset也消失了
mongodb replica set is gone as well and
如果我
the same if i
删除nginx-depl的deployment
do delete deployment
并执行get replicaset
nginx-depl and do the replica set
看，一切都消失了
see everything gone so all the crud
所有的操作如创建、删除、更新等
operations create delete update etc
都发生在deployment级别
happens on the deployment level and
该层之下的一切
everything underneath
都在自动进行
just follows automatically and the
我们可以用类似的方式创造
similar way we can create
其他协调资源，如
other coordinates resources like
Service等
services etc
然而，当你注意到我们
however as you notice when we're
创建kubernetes组件，例如
creating kubernetes components like deployment
使用kubectl create deployment创建deployment时
using cubectl create deployment
哦我总是拼错
um and i misspelled it all the time
你必须在命令行中提供所有这些选项
you'll have to provide all these options on the command line
所以你得写名字，然后
so you'll have to say the name and
你必须
you'll have to
指定镜像，接下来可能还有
specify the image and then you have this
选项一
option one
选项二等等
option two uh etc
在deployment或者pod中
and there could be a lot of things that
可能会有很多
you want to configure
您想要配置的东西
in a deployment or in a pod and
很明显
obviously
把这些都写到命令行
it will be impractical to write that all
是不实际的
out on a command line
因此在实践中你通常
so because of that in practice you would
会使用kubernetes配置文件
usually work with kubernetes configuration files
这意味着您正在创建什么组件
meaning what component you're creating
组件的名称是什么
what the name of the component is
它是基于什么镜像像和任何其他选项
what image is it based off and any other options
都可以聚集在一个配置文件中
they're all gathered in a configuration file
你只要让kubectl执行那个配置文件就行了
and you just tell kubectl to execute
你可以
that configuration file and the way you do it is
使用kubectl apply命令
using cubectl apply command
apply将配置文件作为参数
and apply basically takes the file the
来获取文件
configuration file as a parameter
然后按里面你写的内容执行
and does whatever you have written there
所以
so
apply接受一个名为-f的选项
apply takes an option called minus f
那代表文件名，在这里你要写
that stands for file and here you would say
文件的名称
the name of the file so this will be the config
config-file.yaml
file dot yaml this is the format
yaml是格式你经常会用到的
that you're usually gonna use for
配置文件的格式
configuration files
这个命令将会执行
and this is the command that executes
配置文件中的内容
whatever is in the configuration file
我们来调用配置文件
so let's actually call the configuration file
假设其为nginx-deployment.yaml
i don't know nginx deployment
我们继续创建一个非常
and let's go ahead and create a very
简单的基础的配置文件
simplistic super basic
nginx-deployment
uh nginx deployment file so here i'm
创建该文件
create that file
这就是给deployment的基本设置
so this is the basic configuration
在其中我可以指定
for the deployment so here i'm just specifying
我想指定的东西，比如我想创造一个deployment
what i want to create i want to create a
指定deployment的名称
deployment the name of that deployment
你现在可以忽略这些标签
you can ignore these labels uh right now
呃
uh
我想要创建多少个pod的副本
how many replicas of the pods i want to create
这一部分的template
and this plug right here the template
和spec
and specification
就是pod的蓝图
is a blueprint for the pods so
这里是给deployment指定的内容
specification for the deployment
这里是给pod指定的内容
and specification for a pod and here
这里表示我们想要在pod里有一个
we're just saying that we want one container
基于nginx镜像的容器
inside of the pod with nginx
我们要把它绑定到端口80
image and we are going to bind that on port 80.
这就是我们的配置文件
so this is going to be our configuration file
一旦我们有了它，我们就可以应用它
and once we have that we can apply that
来进行配置
configuration
所以
so
deployment创建好了，现在如果我执行get pod
so deployment created so now if i get
可以看到nginx的deployment和pod
pod i see that nginx deployment
已经创建，并且正在运行
pod was created and it's running
可以看到deployment在52秒前被创建
and let's also see the deployment was created
现在如果我想
52 seconds ago and now if i wanted to
在这个deployment中改变一些东西
change something
我实际上可以改变
in that deployment i can actually change
我的本地配置文件
my local configuration
例如，我想要两个副本
for example i wanted two replicas
而不是一个
instead of one
我可以应用它
i can apply that
再一次
again
nginx部署已配置
deployment nginx deployment configured and
你可以看到这里的不同之处在于
as you see the difference here is that
kubernetes可以检测nginx的deployment是否存在
kubernetes can detect if the nginx
若还不存在，它将会
deployment doesn't exist yet it's going
创建一个
to create one
但如果它已经存在，我再apply一次配置文件
but if it already exists and i apply the configuration file again
它会知道它应该更新
it's going to know that it should update
而不是创建一个新的
it instead of creating a new one
所以如果我get deployment
so if i do get deployment
还是旧的deployment
i see this is the old one or the old deployment
如果我写kubectl get pod，我就能看到
and if i do kubectl get pod i see
旧的那个还在那儿
the old one is still there
一个新的被创建了，因为我
and a new one got created because i
增加了副本个数
increased the replica count
也就是说有了kubectl apply，你就可以
which means that with cube ctl apply you
同时创造
can both create
并更新组件，显然你
and update a component and obviously you
还能通过kubctl设置
can do kubectl with
诸如Service volumes这样的任何其他
services volumes any other
kubernetes组件，就像我们对deployment做的一样
kubernetes components just like we did it with the deployment
那么在下个视频中
so in the next video i'm going to break
我将解构配置文件的语法
down the syntax of the configuration
将会非常符合逻辑
file which is
也很易于理解
pretty logical and simple actually to understand
我会解释所有的
and i'm going to explain all the
不同的属性和它们的含义
different attributes and what they mean
这样您就可以为不同组件
so you can write your own configuration
编写自己的配置文件
files for different components
总结一下，我们已经学了一些kubectl命令
so to summarize we've looked at a couple of kubectl commands
在这个视频中，我们看到了如何创建一个组件
in this video we saw how to create a
比如deployment
component like deployment
如何编辑和删除它，我们看到了如何获取
how to edit it and delete it we saw how to get
deployment和ReplicaSet这些组件的状态等等
status of parts deployments replica sets
我们也能获取控制台的日志输出
etc we also logged on the console whatever
无论pod中的应用程序是否正在写入控制台
application is writing it to the console in the pod
我们看到了如何利用kubectl exec获取
and we saw how to get a terminal of a
运行中的容器的终端
running container using kubectl
最后我们看到了如何使用
exec and finally we saw how to use
一个kubernetes配置文件来
a kubernetes configuration file to
创建和
create and
更新组件
update components using the cube ctl
通过使用kubectl apply命令
apply command
最后但同样重要的是我们学习了
and last but not least we saw kubectl
kubectl describe命令
describe command
如果一个pod中的容器还没有启动
which will when a container isn't
你想要一些额外的关于pod的故障排除信息
starting in a pod and you want to get
可以使用该命令
some additional troubleshooting information about the pod
在这个视频中，我将向你们展示
in this video i'm going to show you the
kubernetes配置文件的语法和内容
syntax and the contents of kubernetes configuration file
它是在kubernetes集群中创建和配置组件
which is the main tool for creating and
的主要工具
configuring components in kubernetes cluster
如果您见过大型配置文件
if you've seen large configuration files
似乎
it might seem
令人望而生畏，但实际上
overwhelming but in reality it's pretty
它很简单
simple and
很符合直觉，结构逻辑性也很好
intuitive and also very logically structured
让我们一步一步来
so let's go through it step by step
这里我有一个例子，分别有
so here i have examples of a deployment
deployment和service的配置文件
and service configuration files
首先需要说的是
side by side so the first thing is that
kubernetes中的每个配置文件都由三部分组成
every configuration file in kubernetes has
第一部分是
three parts the first part is where the
您正在创建的组件的
metadata of that
元数据
component that you're creating resides
其中一个元数据显然是组件本身的名称
in one of the metadata is obviously name of the component itself
配置文件的第二部分
the second part in the configuration file is
是每个组件的特别说明(specification)
specification so each component's
所以每个配置文件
configuration file
都会有一个spec块
will have a specification where you
基本上是
basically put
所有你想给这个组件apply的
every kind of configuration that you want to apply
配置
for that component um
如您所见，这里的前两行
the first two lines here as you see is
在声明
just declaring
想要创造什么组件
what you want to create here we are
这里创建的是deployment
creating deployment
这里创建的是service
and here we're creating a service and
这里是
this is basically
你需要每个组件
you have to look up for each component
指定一个不同的api版本
there's a different api version
现在在spec部分
so now inside of the specification part
很明显
obviously
spec块的属性
the attributes will be
因组件类型而异
specific to the kind of a component that you're creating
所以deployment将有它自己的属性
so deployment will have its own attributes
只适用于deployment
that only apply for deployment and the
Service也有它自己的东西
service will have its own stuff
但是我之前说过，配置文件
but i said there are three parts of a
有三个部分
configuration file
我们现在只看到元数据和spec
and we just see metadata and the specification
那么第三部分在哪里
so where's the third part so the third part
第三部分将会是一种状态，但它是
will be a status but it's going to be
自动生成的
automatically generated and
由kubernetes添加，所以它的工作方式是
added by kubernetes so the way it works is that
kubernetes总是比较
kubernetes will always compare what is
理想的状态
the desired state
和实际的该组件的状态
and what is the actual state or the status of that component
如果当前状态和期望的状态不匹配
and if the status and desired state do not match
kubernetes知道有些东西
then kubernetes knows there is something
需要被修复
to be fixed there
所以它会试图修复它
so it's going to try to fix it and this
这是kubernetes提供的基础的自我修复特性
is the basis of the self-healing feature that kubernetes provides
例如，这里您指定您想要
for example here you specify you want
nginx-deployment有两个副本
two replicas
所以当你apply
of nginx deployment so when you apply this
即当您使用此配置文件
when you actually create the deployment
实际创建deployment时
using this configuration file
kubernetes将会在这里添加
that's what apply means kubernetes will add here
你的deployment的状态
the status of your deployment and it will
并持续更新状态
update that state continuously so for
举例来说
example if
在某个时间的状态说，只有一个副本
a status at some point will say just one
正在运行
replica is running
然后kubernetes会比较这个状态与spec之间的差别
then kubernetes will compare that status with the specification
我们就知道这里有问题了
and we'll know there is a problem there
需要创建另一个副本
another replica needs to be created
另一个有趣的问题是
sap now another interesting question here is
kubernetes从哪里得到
where does kubernetes actually get the
状态数据
status data
从而自动添加并不断更新
to automatically add here or update continuously
这个信息来自于etcd
that information comes from the etcd
记得是我们说过的集群大脑
remember the cluster
master进程之一
brain one of the master processes that
它实际上来
actually stores
存储集群数据
the cluster data so etcd holds
所以etcd随时保留
at any time the current status of
任何组件的当前状态
any kubernetes component and that's
而它就是状态信息的来源
where the status information comes from
正如你看到
so as you see the format of the
配置文件是yaml
configuration files is
也是文件扩展名
yaml that's why the extension here and
一般来说它是很直观
generally it's pretty straightforward to
非常简单的格式
understand it's a very simple format
但是yaml对缩排非常严格
but yaml is very strict about the indentations
举个例子，如果你有
so for example if you have something
错误地缩排
wrongly indented here
你的文件将无效
your file will be invalid um so what i
尤其是如果我有一个
do especially if i have a configuration
有200行的配置文件
file that has 200 lines
很长很难办
it's pretty long um i usually use
我通常会找yaml在线验证网站
some yaml online validator to see where
来看看语法有没有什么问题
i need to fix that
但除对缩排严格之外，它就很简单了
but other than that it's pretty simple
另一点需要说的是
um another thing is
你应该把这些配置文件放在哪里
where do you actually store those configuration files
通常的做法是将它们和你的代码一起储存
a usual practice is to store them with your code
因为deployment和service
because since the deployment and service is
将会被apply到你的应用中
going to be applied to your application
在你的应用程序代码中
it's a good practice to store these
储存这些配置文件
configuration files
是一个很好的习惯
in your application code so usually it
所以通常它会
will be part of
作为整套基础代码的一部分
the whole infrastructure as a code concept
或者您也可以拥有自己的git仓库
or you can also have its own git
专门用于保存配置文件
repository just for the configuration files
在之前的视频中我给你们看过
so in the previous video i showed you
deployment管理在其之下的部分
that deployments manage the parts that are below them so
每当你
whenever you
编辑一些deployment内的内容
edit something in a deployment it kind
会级联到
of cascades down
它管理的所有pod
down to all the pods that it manages and
每当你
whenever you
想要创造一些pod
want to create some pods you would
你实际上会创建一个deployment
actually create a deployment
剩下的就交给它了
and it will take care of the rest so how
这一切是怎么做到的
does this happen or where is this
你又要在配置文件的哪里定义所有东西呢
whole thing defined in the configuration
所以在这里
so here in the
deployment中的spec部分
specification part of a deployment you
你会看到一个template字块
see a template
如果我展开它，你会看到template
and if i expand it you see the template
也有自己的元数据和spec
also has its own metadata and specification
它基本上是一个配置文件中的配置文件
so it's basically a config file inside of a config file
之所以这么做是因为
and the reason for it is that this configuration
这个配置文件也会被应用于pod，所以pod应该有它自己的配置
applies to a pod so pod should have its own configuration
在deployment的配置文件中
inside of deployments configuration file
所有的deployment都是要这样被定义的
and that's how all the deployments will be defined and this
这是一个pod的蓝图，里面有
is going to be the blueprint for a pod
比如它应该基于哪个镜像
like which image it should be based
它应该打开哪个端口
on which port it should open what is
它的容器名称是什么等等
going to be the name of the container etc
建立联系的方式是通过使用
so the way the connection is established is using
标签(label)和选择器(selector)
labels and selectors so
如您所见，元数据部分包含labels
as you see metadata part contains the labels
spec部分包含selectors
and the specification part contains selectors
非常简单
it's pretty simple in a metadata you
你要给deploy这样的组件或者pod
give components like deployment
提供键值对，它可以是
or pod a key value pair and it could be
任何键值对
any key value pair that
在这个例子中，我们有app:nginx
you think of in this case we have app nginx
这个标签就粘在组件上面
and that label just sticks to that component
所以我们使用这个有app:nginx标签的蓝图
so we give parts created
创造了组件
using this blueprint labeled app nginx
然后我们告诉deployment连接或者匹配
and we tell the deployment to connect or to match
所有有标签app:nginx的组件
all the labels with app
以建立连接
nginx to create that connection
这样deployment就知道是哪一部分
so this way deployment will know which
属于它
parts belong to it
现在deployment有了自己的标签app:nginx
now deployment has its own label app nginx
这两个标签被service的selector所使用
and these two labels are used by the service
在service的spec部分
selector so in the specification of a service
我们定义了一个selector
we define a selector which basically
以建立Service与
makes a connection between the service and
deployment或其中的一部分的连接
the deployment or its parts because
service必须知道
service must know
哪些pod是被注册以供其使用的
which pods are kind of registered with it
哪些pod属于这个service
so which pods belong to that service and
该连接
that connection
是通过selector和label完成的
is made through the selector
后面的demo我们会看到这一点
of the label and we're going to see that in a
这是另一个
demo so another thing that must be
service和pod必须配置的是
configured in the service and
端口
pod is the ports so
如果我展开这个，我就会看到
if i expand this i see that service has
service有其端口配置
its ports configuration and
pod里的容器
the container inside of a pod is
很明显,运行
obviously running
或者需要正确地运行它的端口
or needs to run its port right so how this is configured
service有一个port
is basically service has a port
也就是service自身
where the service itself is
可以在哪个端口被访问，如果其它服务
um accessible at so if other service
发送请求到
sends a request to
nginx-service，需要发送到端口80
nginx service here it needs to send it on port 80
但是service需要知道转发请求到哪个pod
but the service needs to know to which pod it should
也需知道哪个pod的端口正在监听
forward the request but also at which port
这就是targetPort的意义
is that port listening and that is the target port
所以这个应该和容器端口匹配
so this one should match the container port
这样我们就完成了deployment和service的
and with that we have our deployment and service
基本配置
basic configurations done and
这里要注意
to note here most of these attributes
你在这里看到的这两部分
that you see here in both
属性中的大多数实际上
parts are required so this will actually
是最低的
be the minimum
用于deployment和service的配置
configuration for deployment and service
一旦我们拿到那些文件
so once we have those files
让我们apply它们或用它们创建组件
let's actually apply them or create components
让我们移步控制台
using that so let's head over to the console
这里我要创建deployment和service
and here i'm going to create both
所以kubectl apply nginx-deployment
deployment and service so kubectl apply nginx-deployment
创建好了，然后是nginx-service
created and nginx service
现在如果我get pod
so now if i get the pods i see
看到两个副本正在运行，因为
two replicas are running because that's
那就是我们定义的
how we define it here
我们也有我们的service
and we have our service as well
也就是nginx-service
which is nginx service this is a
这是默认service，它总是在那里
default service it's always there
这是我们创建的
this is the one we created and it's
它在监听端口80
listening on port
正如我们指定的
80 as we specified now
现在我们如何验证该service
how can we validate that the service um
可以转发请求到正确的port呢
has the right ports that it forwards the
我们可以用kubectl describe service
requests to we can do it using kubectl describe
接着是service的名称
service and the service name
这里你可以看到端点
and here you see the endpoints
你在这里可以找到所有状态信息
where you have all this status information here
就像我们在配置中定义的那些
like the things that we define in the
比如selector是app:nginx等等
configuration like app
我们有定义的targetPort
selector etc we have the target port
我们也有端点
that we define and we have the end
这个必须是请求被转发到的
points here and this must be the ip addresses
pod的ip地址
and ports of the pods
和端口
that the service must forward
所以我们怎么知道
the requests to so how do we know that
这些ip地址是正确的呢
these are the ip addresses of the right parts
因为kubectl get pod是不可能
because with kubectl get pod you don't
得到这个信息的
get this information
所以我们的方法
so the way we do it or where we find
就是使用
that out is using
get pod，然后-o用于输出
get pod and then you do dash o which is for
然后我们需要更多的信息
output and then we want more information
所以 -o wide，我们看到了
so o wide and here we see
这里有更多列，我们有名字
more columns here so we have the name
和状态等等
and status ready
我们也有ip地址
etc but we also have the ip address so here
这就是指定的端点ip地址
is the ip address endpoint specified here
这是另一个，我们知道
and this is the other one so we know
service有正确的端点
that the service has right endpoints so
现在我们来看看
now let's see
配置文件的第三部分
the third part of the configuration file
即kubernetes自动生成的状态
which is a status that kubernetes automatically generated
我们可以
and the way to do it
用get nginx-deployment
is we can get the deployment
以yaml格式
nginx deployment in a yaml format
所以当我执行这个命令的时候
so when i execute this command i will
会获取结果或
get the resulting or the updated
我的deployment的配置的更新
configuration of my deployment which
即驻留在etcd中的内容
actually resides in the
因为etcd存储
etcd because etcd stores the status of
整个集群包括每一个组件的状态，所以
the whole cluster including every component so
如果我这样做，我将在我的控制台得到yaml输出
um if i do this i'll get the yaml output
但我想要它在文件中
in my console but i want it in the file
所以我要把它存到
so i'm gonna save it into um
nginx deployment result
我要把它保存在那里
and i'm going to save it there and i'm
在我的编辑器紧邻原始文件，打开它
going to open it in my editor next to the original one
正如你看到的，很多东西都被添加了
so as you see a lot of stuff has been added
让我们看看状态部分
but let's just see the status part so all this
所有这些都是被不断通过kubernetes
is automatically added and updated
自动添加和更新的
constantly by kubernetes
它表示有多少个副本正在运行
so it says how many replicas are running
这些副本的状态如何
what the state of those replicas
还有一些其他的信息，这部分
and some other information so this part
在调试时也会有帮助
can also be helpful when debugging
这就是状态信息，但如果你注意到
so there's a status but also if you noticed
元数据和规范部分中
other stuff has been added in the
还被添加了其他的东西
metadata and specification part as well
例如，创建时间戳
so for example uh creation timestamp
即组件是什么时候创建的
when was the component created is
是kubernetes自动添加的
automatically added by kubernetes
元数据
because it is a metadata
还有一些独特的id等，你不需要
some unique id etc you don't have to
关心它
care about it
在spec部分，它只是
and in the specification part it just
增加了一些默认值
adds some defaults
但是你不需要
for that component but again you don't have to
关心或理解其中的大部分
care or understand most of these
这里有一点需要注意
attributes but one thing to note here
比如你想要复制
is that if you for example want to copy
您已经有的deployment
a deployment that you already have using
嗯，也许自动脚本会
um maybe automated scripts you will have to
把生成的东西中的大部分
remove and get rid of most of this
都去掉
generated stuff
所以你必须首先清理这一deployment的
so you have to clean that deployment
配置文件
configuration file first
然后你可以用这样的蓝图配置
and then you can create another
创建另一个deployment
deployment from that
这就是本视频的内容
blueprint configuration so that's it with this video
所以从现在开始我们要
so from now on we're gonna be working
用配置文件工作了
with the configuration files so for
比如如果我想删除
example if i want to delete the
deployment和service
deployment and the service
我可以用那个配置文件
i can do it using that file um configuration file as well
使用delete
using delete and
这样的话，我们的deployment就没了
like this the deployment will be gone
我也可以对service做同样的事
and i can do the same for service
好的，使用kubectl apply和kubectl delete
all right so using kubectl apply and kubectl delete
你就基本上可以与配置文件配合工作了
you can basically work with the configuration files
在这个视频中，我们将部署两个应用程序
in this video we're gonna deploy two applications
我选择了mongodb和MongoExpress这两个
mongodb and express and i chose these two
因为它很好地验证了典型的
because it demonstrates really well a typical
web应用程序及其数据库的简单设置
simple setup of a web application and its database
所以你可以把这个应用类比到你的任何类似的项目上
so you can apply this to any similar setup you have
我们来看看怎么做
so let's see how we're going to do this
首先我们将创建一个mongodb pod
so first we will create a mongodb pod
为了能和那个pod通信
and in order to talk to that pod we are
我们需要一个service
going to need a service
我们要创建一个内部service
and we're going to create an internal
也就是说
service which basically means that no
外部请求不允许被发送到pod
external requests are allowed to the pod
只有同一集群内的组件
only components inside the same cluster
可以和它通信
can talk to it
这就是我们想要的
and that's what we want then we're going
然后我们创建一个Mongo Express的deployment
to create a express
我们需要
deployment one we're going to need a
mongodb数据库的url
database url of mongodb
这样Mongo Express就能连接上Mongodb
so that express can connect to it
第二个是凭证信息
and the second one is
如数据库的用户名和密码之类的
credentials so username and password of
以便它能够进行身份验证
the database so that it can authenticate
我们传递信息到Mongo Express所在deployment的方式是
so the way we can pass this information
通过环境变量调整
to express deployment is through its deployment
以及deployment的配置文件
configuration file through environmental
因为这就是应用程序配置的方式
variables because that's how the application is configured
我们会创建一个ConfigMap
so we're going to create a config map
其包含数据库url
that contains database url
我们要创造一个Secret
and we're going to create a secret that
包含的凭证信息
contains the credentials
在deployment的配置文件中我们会引用两者
and we're going to reference both inside of that deployment file
一旦我们建立好了，我们就
so once we have that set up we're going
需要express来被
to need express to be accessible
浏览器访问，为此
through browser in order to do that
我们要创建一个外部service
we're going to create an external service
这将允许外部请求
that will allow external requests to
与pod对话
talk to the pod so the url will be
url将是http + 节点的ip地址
http ip address of the node and
以及service的端口，因此有了这个设置
the service port so with this setup the request
请求的流程现在看起来是这样的
flow will now look like this so the
请求来自浏览器
request comes from the browser
给到express的外部service
and it goes to the external service of the express
然后将它转发给Express的pod
which will then forward it to the express pod
pod随后将连接到mongodb的内部service
the pod will then connect to internal service of mongodb
那是这里的数据库url
that's basically the database url here
然后它会转发给mongodb pod
and it will forward it then to mongodb pod where
在那里它将使用凭证信息验证请求
it will authenticate the request using the credentials
现在我们来创建这个整个设置
so now let's go and create this whole
使用kubernetes配置文件
setup using kubernetes configuration files
让我们进入主题
let's dive right into it and create the whole setup
首先，我有一个运行中的minikube集群
so first of all i have a mini cube cluster running if i do
如果我执行kubectl get all命令
cube ctl get all which basically gets me
会让我了解到集群中的所有组件
all the components that are inside the cluster
我只有一个默认的kubernetes service
i only have a default kubernetes service
所以集群是空的
so my cluster is empty
我要从头开始
and i'm starting from scratch so the
我们要做的第一件事是
first thing that i said we're gonna do is create a
创建mongodb的deployment
mongodb deployment
我通常用编辑器，所以
i usually create it in an editor so i'm
打开visual studio code
going to go to visual studio code
粘贴准备好的mongodb deployment文件
and paste a prepared deployment file there
看起来就是这样
for mongodb and this is how it's going to look like
那么类型是Deployment，还有一些元数据
so i have a deployment kind and i have some metadata
我就叫它mongodb-deployment吧
i'm just going to call it mongodb deployment
还有标签和选择器
labels and selectors in the previous
在前面的视频中我已经解释过了
video i already explained the syntax
k8s的yaml配置文件的语法了
of kubernetes yaml configuration file
如果你想知道所有这些属性是什么意思
so if you want to know what all these
你可以看看那个视频
attributes mean then you can check out that video
在template中有一些定义或者说蓝图
and here in the template i have a definition or blueprint
deployment基于此创建pod
for parts that this deployment gonna create
我要有一个副本
and i'm just gonna go with one replica
容器会被叫做mongodb
so the container is gonna be called mongodb
这就是我要用到的镜像
and this is the image that i'm gonna
让我们
take so let's actually go
去查看 mongodb镜像的配置
and check out the image configuration for mongodb so
这个镜像
and i see this image here
打开这个，我在找的是
let's open this and basically what i'm looking for
如何使用容器
is how to use that um container
也就是说它会开放哪些端口
meaning what ports it's going to open and what's
对它进行外部配置需要使用什么
external configuration it's going to take so
mongodb容器默认端口为27017
a default port of mongodb container is
我要用它
27017 so i'm going to use that
我们会用到环境变量
and we are going to use environmental variables the root
有root用户名和root密码
username and root password
所以我可以在容器启动时
so basically i can on the container startup
定义admin用户名和密码
define the admin username and password
让我们继续，来配置所有的
so let's go ahead and configure all of that
在配置文件中的内容
inside the configuration file so here
在这里image属性
below the image of mongodb so we're just gonna leave
只要留镜像名字就好，它会拉取最新的镜像
the name of the image and it's gonna pull the latest one
这也是我们想要的，我还要指定
and that's what we want so here i'm gonna specify
我要暴露什么端口
what port i want to expose so ports
所以加上ports属性，下面要有containerPort属性
that's the attribute name and container port
使用标准端口27017
and that's the standard port so i'm gonna leave it and
在这下面我会指定
below that i'm gonna specify those
两个环境变量，一个叫
two environmental variables so one is
让我们看看它叫什么
called let's see what it's called it's
它叫MONGO_INITDB_ROOT_USERNAME
mongodb root username and here
它对应的值
it's gonna be value so we're gonna
先留空
actually leave it blank for now
另一个叫做MONGO_INITDB_ROOT_PASSWORD
and the other one is called init root password and we're
它的值也留空
gonna leave that blank as well just value and
一旦我们有了这些值
once we have the values here um going to have
我们就有了一个mongodb的完整的deployment
a complete deployment for mongodb this
基本上就是我们所需要的
is basically all we need
现在注意，这是一个
now note that this is a configuration
将签入到存储库的配置文件
file that is going to be checked into a repository
通常你不会在该配置文件中写admin用户名和密码
so usually you wouldn't write admin username and password
而我们会
inside the configuration file so what we're going to do now
在要引用值的地方
is we're going to create a secret from where
创建一个secret
we will reference the values so
也就是说这个secret会在k8s中存活
meaning that the secret is going to live
而git仓库中没人可以访问它
in kubernetes and nobody will have access to it in a git
所以首先我们保存目前这个不完整的deployment文件
repository so we're going to save this incomplete
我们命名其为mongo.yaml
deployment file first of all so let's call it
并保存它
deployment or let's just call it yaml and save it
这样我们就可以高亮显示语法了
here so that we get the syntax highlight and now
现在在我们apply这个配置之前
before we apply this configuration we're
先创建secret
going to create the secret
root用户名和密码将被放在那里
where the root username and password will leave
我们来创建一个新文件
so let's create a new file and i'm going
粘贴secret的配置
to paste in the configuration of a
实际上很简单
secret which is actually
类型为Secret
pretty simple so we have a kind secret
然后我们有一个元数据
then we have a metadata which again is
仅仅是名字
just simply the name
我们称它为mongodb-secret
we're going to call it mongodb secret
type属性为Opaque，这是默认值也是最基本的
the type opec is actually a default type which is the most basic
键值对secret类型
key value secret type other types for example
其他类型，如tls certificates类型
include tls certificates so you can create a
可以用来创建一个指定tls证书的secret
secret specifically with the tls certificate type
还有其他几种类型，但大多情况下
and a couple of more types but mostly
你将使用默认的
you're going to use the default one
这些是实际的内容
and these are the actual contents so you
data属性下有一些键值对
have the data and here you have key value pairs
当然键是你定义的
um which of course are the names you come up with
我们会指定用户名
so we're gonna specify username or we
可以称之为mongo-root-username
can actually call it root
而下面的将其命名为mongo-root-password
username and we're going to call it
有件事需要说
root password and here's the thing the values
当我们创建一个secret时
in in this key value pairs
键值对中的值并不是纯文本
are not plain text so when we are creating a secret
该值必须经过base64编码
the value must be base64 encoded
最简单的转码方法是
so the way you can do that the simplest way is
到终端输入
go to your terminal so here i'm going to say echo
echo -n，后者是很重要的选项别忘了
minus n very important option don't leave it out
否则就没用了
otherwise it's not gonna work and here
然后向其中写一个纯文本值
i'm gonna put a plain text value that i want
这里我想用username
so i'm just gonna go with just username
当然可以是任何更安全的内容
whatever of course you can have something more
我要做base64编码
secretive here and i'm gonna
这里得到的值
base64 encoding and the value that i get here
复制到secret配置文件里，作为键值对的值
i'm gonna copy it into the secret configuration as a value
密码也是一样
and i'm gonna do the same with password so
我还是要简单点的密码
again i'm just gonna go with simple
显然你可以使用更安全的
password obviously you want to have something more secure
我要把它作为一个值复制到这里
and i'm gonna copy that as a value here
文件保存为secret.yaml
and save it is secret dot yaml
现在我们只写了配置文件
okay now we have only written
还没有在集群中创建任何东西
configuration files we haven't created anything yet
所以这只是准备工作
in the cluster so this is just preparation work
如果我们要在deployment里引用该secret
and we have to create secret before the deployment
就需要在创建deployment前创建secret
if we're gonna reference the secret
创建的顺序很重要
inside of this so the order
因为如果我
of creation matters because if i'm
创建一个deployment，它引用一个不存在的secret
creating a deployment that references a secret
我会得到一个报错
that doesn't exist yet i'm gonna get an error
所以也就启动不了
so it's not going to start since we have
既然有第一个组件
our first component let's actually go
让我们用配置文件创建我们的secret
ahead and create our secret from a configuration file
再次回到控制台
so again i'm going to go to my console
清空
let's actually clear all these and i'm gonna go
进入包含了所有这些配置文件的文件夹
into the folder where i'm creating all these configuration files
我这里它的名字为k8s-configuration
i called it kubernetes configuration and
这是我的两个文件
here i have both of my files
我要执行kubectl apply命令
so i'm do i'm gonna do cube ctl apply secret
secret被创建了，再执行kubectl get secret命令
and secret created so i'm gonna do kubectl
就会看到我刚刚创建的secret
get secret and i should see my secret has been created this is
这个是默认创建的东西
something created by default
采用另一种类型，这里是我们的secret
with a different type and this is our secret here
既然我们有了secret，就可以
so now that we have our secrets we can reference it
在我们的deployment的配置文件中引用它
inside of our deployment configuration file
所以我们回到该文件
so let's go back and this is how you reference
这就是你引用secret中键值数据的方式
contents specific key value data
不是在value赋值，而是说明value从哪里来，使用valueFrom
of secret so instead of value we're going to say value from
然后要用secretKeyRef属性，指定引用的secret
and then i'm going to do secret key ref or secret key reference
名字将是secret名字
and name is going to be the secret name
就是这一个
so this one here and
键是data属性中的键
key is going to be the key in the data
我想要这个键值对的值
i want the value of this key value pair
所以我想要data的这部分
so i want this part of the data so i'm
通过键引用它
going to reference it by key
你显然不需要记住
so you don't have to learn it by heart
所有的语法和属性名
obviously all the syntax and attribute names
重要的是你要知道
important thing here is that you know
大概如何引用它
approximately how to reference it
语法你可以随时
the actual syntax you can always look up
在谷歌或者之前的配置文件中查找
in google or maybe from previous configuration files
是的，这就是你引用它的方式
but yeah this is how you reference it
我们也要对密码做同样的事
and we're gonna do the same with
我要复制valueFrom
password so i'm gonna do from and i'm just gonna copy
和其余的内容
the rest here
记住，yaml对缩进是非常严格的
remember yaml is very strict with the indentation
这里有一个相同的secret，但是不同的key
here is the same secret but a different key so i'm gonna
我要在这里使用password作为key
use password key here and
就是这样
that will be it so now we have
现在我们从secret引用了
the root username and password
root用户名和密码
referenced from the secret
但配置文件里面没有具体的值
and no actual values inside the configuration file
这对安全有好处
which is good for security because you
因为你不希望你的凭证信息
don't want your credentials
出现在你的代码库中
in your code repository okay so
好的，我们的deployment文件已经准备好了
our deployment file is actually ready so
让我们apply一下，通过kubectl apply
let's apply that kubectl apply
而这次deployment就被创建了
and the deployment created meaning if i do
如果我执行get all命令
get all i should see the pod
可以看到pod启动了，然后是deployment和ReplicaSet
starting up the deployment and the replica set
所以让我们看看pod怎么样了
so let's actually check how pod is doing
容器创建中，那就watch一下
container creating so let's actually watch
可能需要一些时间来创建容器
it might take some time to create it if
如果花了很长时间
it takes long and if you want to
你想看看哪里是否有问题
see whether there is a problem there you
可以执行kubectl describe + pod的名称
can also do cube ctl describe pod and the pod name
至少我们知道一切正常
so at least we know nothing's wrong there
所以我们看到它在拉取镜像
so we see that it's just pulling the
这就是耗时久的原因
image so that's what it
我们再来看看
takes so long so let's see again
执行kubectl get pod命令，如你所见
cube ctl get pod and as you see
它正在运行，所以我们有了mongodb的deployment
it's running so we have mongodb deployment
还有端口，一个副本正在运行
and the port one replica of its part running
第二步，我们要
now the second step is we're gonna
创建内部service
create an internal service
这样其他组件或端口
so that other components or other ports
就可以和这个mongodb通话了
can talk to this mongodb
让我们继续创建service的配置
so let's go ahead and create service configuration
回到yaml文件，我们可以
so go back to yaml and here we can
要么创建一个单独的给secret用的文件（口误，应是service）
either create a separate yaml configuration file for secret or we
要么可以在同一个yaml文件中把service的内容包含进去
can also include it in the same one
所以实际上在yaml中
so in yaml you can actually put multiple
你可以放多个文档在一个文件中
documents in one file
如果我画三个破折号
so if i put three dashes that's
这是一个语法
basically a syntax
用于yaml中的文档分离
for document separation in yaml so i
从而可以开始写新文档
need new document is starting
我要把两个配置
so actually i'm gonna put both deployment and service
都写在在一个配置文件中
in one configuration file because they
因为它们通常属于彼此
usually belong together
这里我要粘贴service的配置
so here i'm gonna paste the service configuration
顺便说一下，我要把这些配置文件
and by the way i'm gonna put all these
都放进git仓库中
configuration files in git repository
本视频的简介中会有该仓库的链接
and link the repository in the description of this video
这就是mongodb的service
so this is a service for mongodb let's go through
让我们回顾一些属性，这是service的类型
some of the attributes here so it's the service kind
这是我们给它取得名字
just the name we're going to call it
然后是mongodb service的选择器
mongodb service selector
这一点很重要，因为我们想
this is an important one because we want this service to
让此service连接到正确的pod，为此
connect to the pod right and the way to do that
需要使用选择器和标签(label)
is using selector and
用这个deployment和pod有的标签
label so using this here the labels that deployment and
service可以找到
pod have service can find the parts
要依附的pod
that it's going to attach to all right
所以这里要有选择器
so we have the selector here
这里也是很重要的一部分
and this is important part where we
用于开放service的端口
expose service port so this is going to
这将是service的端口
be the service port
而这是容器的
and this is going to be the container
当我们开放了在这个地址的容器的端口
and since we exposed container port at
二者将匹配
this address right here these two have
因此targetPort属性是
to match so target port is
容器或pod的端口，这是service的端口
container or pod port and this is the service port
显然这两个可以是不同的
and obviously these two here can be different
但我还是想用相同的端口
but i'm gonna go with the same port and
基本上
that's basically it
这就是我们的service
that's our service so i'm gonna create
现在我要创建service
the service now
保存这个文件，然后回到控制台
so let's save this file and go back to my
我要在再apply一下
console and i'm gonna apply
刚才那个用于创建deployment的文件
the same file that i applied before to create
让我们看看会发生什么
deployment so let's see what happens see
现在既有deployment又有service
both deployment and service configuration
但我没有改变deployment
but it's going to know that i haven't
就像这里写的
changed the deployment that's what it means here
然后一个service被创建了
and a service is created so if i
如果我要编辑二者，我可以重新apply该文件
were to edit both for example i can reapply the file
deployment和service均会被修改
and deployment of service can be changed
所以我认为
so i think
使用本地配置文件是一种方便的编辑组件的方法
using local configuration files is a handy way to edit
现在我们
your components so now let's actually
用get service命令检查我们的service是否已经创建
check that our service was created get service
这就是我们的service，正在监听端口27017
and this is our service and it's listening at port
我在之前的一个视频中展示过这个
27017 and i showed it in one of the
但我们还能够
previous videos but we can actually
验证service是否连接到正确的pod
also validate that the service is attached to the correct
为此，我要执行
pod and to do that i'm gonna do describe
describe + service名的命令
service and i need the service name for this
这里我有一个端点(endpoint)
so here i have the endpoint which is an
是一个pod的ip地址和端口
ip address of a pod and the
应用程序在pod中监听该端口
port where the application inside the pod is
我们来检查一下
listening it so let's actually check
是否是正确的pod
that this is the right pod
虽说我们只有一个pod，但还是想验证
i mean we just have one but still so if i do get
执行get pod命令，想要额外输出，-o选项设置wide
pod and i want additional output
有一列包含了ip地址
to what i get by default one of the columns
就是这里
includes the ip address which is this one right here
所以172.17.0.6这是pod的ip地址
so 172.17.0.6 that's the pod ip address and this is
而这是pod中的应用程序在监听的端口
the port where the application inside the pod is listening at
所以一切都安排得很完美
so everything is set up perfectly
mongodb的deployment和service已完成创建
mongodb deployment and service has been created
顺便说一下，如果你想看
and by the way if you want to see all
一个应用的所有组件
the components for one
你也可以用kubectl get all命令显示它们
application you can also display them
这将显示所有组件
using cube ctl get all that will show all the components
你可以通过名字来筛选它们，所以输入mongodb
and you can filter them by name so mongodb
这里你可以看到service、deployment、replicaSet和pod
and here you see the service deployment replica set and the pod
所以当你执行get all
so when you do all the component type will be
首先映入眼帘的会是组件类型，这只是辅助信息
the first here okay that's uh just a side info
接下来我们要
so now the next step we're going to
创建Mongo Express的deployment和service
create express deployment and service
还有一个外部配置
and also an external configuration um
在那里我们要放置
where we're going to put
mongodb数据库的url
the database url for mongodb so let's go
继续
ahead and do it
清空，然后
so i'm going to clear that up and go and
创建一个新文件
create a new file
用于Mongo Express的deployment和service
for express deployment and service
这是Express的deployment的草稿
so this is the deployment draft of express
同样的，Express也配拥有姓名
same things here express that's the name
这是pod的定义，镜像名是mongo-express
and here we have the pod definition where the image
我们也来检查一下这个镜像
name is express let's actually go ahead and check that image
我们不需要这个网页，就是这个Express
as well we don't need this this is express
这就是mongo-express镜像的名字
and that's the name of the image mongo
我们来看看同样的数据
express and let's see the same data here
让我们看看Express应用程序的端口
let's see the port the express application
容器内部的会在端口8081启动
inside the container starts at is 8081
这些是一些环境问题变量
and these are some of the environmental
我们一般需要三个变量
variables so obviously we need three things for express
我们需要告诉它应该连接哪个数据库应用程序
we need to tell it which database application
显然我们需要
it should connect to so obviously we
告诉它mongodb的地址
need to tell it the mongodb
即连接到内部service的
address database address it should
数据库的地址
connect to the internal service
我们需要凭证信息
and we we're gonna need credentials so
这样mongodb可以验证连接
that mongodb can authenticate
相应的环境变量是
that connection and the environmental variables to do that
ADMINUSERNAME（管理员用户名）和PASSWORD
is going to be admin username admin
以及mongodb端点，即MONGODB_SERVER
password and the mongodb
这就是
endpoint will be this here so these
我们需要的三个环境变量
three environmental variables we need
继续
so let's go ahead and use that so first
我们首先要开放端口
we're going to open the port
输入containerPort属性
again container ports
为什么在pod内会有多个端口
and the reason why you have multiple ports is that inside of the pod
是因为你实际上可以开放多个端口
you can actually open multiple ports
这里也就是8081，现在我们
so that's going to be 8081 and now we're gonna
要添加环境变量以便连接
add the environment to variables for the
第一个是用户名
connectivity so the first one is the username
这显然要和定义在这里
and this is going to be obviously the
的用户名和密码
same username and password that we
一致
defined right here so what i'm going to
所以我要复制它们
do is i'm just going to copy them
因为它和我们从secret中读出的值
because it's really the same so the value from we're
是一样的
going to read it from the secret
粘贴到这里
that's already there so i'm gonna paste it here
第二个环境变量被称为ADMINPASSWORD
second environmental variable is called admin password
我也要从这里复制这个valueFrom
and i'm also gonna copy that from here
第三个
and the third one
将是数据库服务器(MONGODB_SERVER)
is going to be the database server and
因为它也是外部配置
since this is also an external
我们可以选择
configuration we can either
写value属性，然后直接在这里
do value here and we could write the mongodb server
写mongodb服务器的地址
address directly here or as i showed you
或者也可以像我在开头的图中所说的
in the diagram at the beginning we can
把它放进ConfigMap中，从而进行外部配置
put it in a config map which is an external configuration so
它是将内容集中存储到一个地方的
that it's centralized so it's stored in one place
其他组件也可以使用它
and also other components can also use it
举个例子，如果我有两个
so for example if i have two
使用mongodb数据库的应用程序
applications that are using mongodb
那我就可以引用
database then i can just reference
这个外部配置
that external configuration here and if
如果我必须在某个时候改变它
i have to change it at some point i just
只需更改一处，无需更新其它的东西
change it in one place and nothing else gets updated
因此，我们将保留这个不完整的
so because of that we're going to keep this incomplete
deployment的配置
deployment configuration and
并创建ConfigMap
we're going to create the config map
其中要包含mongodb服务器的地址
which will contain the mongodb server
我要创建一个新的文件
address so i'm going to create a new
让我们先保存这个
file let's actually save this
不完整的deployment，命名为mongo-express.yaml
incomplete deployment let's call it express
我们会在晚些时候回到这里
yaml and we're going to come back to it later
保存，现在我们需要一个ConfigMap
so save that now we need a
复制配置
config map here so i'm going to copy the configuration
这个也很简单，就像secret
and this is also pretty simple just like secret
类型是ConfigMap
you have the kind which is configmap
然后是名称，都是相同的格式
the name and the same construct see just like you saw here
data里是键值对，这里没有type属性
data which is key value pair it doesn't have a type
因为只有一种ConfigMap的type
because they're just one config map type and that's it
这里还有键值对
and here you again have key value pairs
所以数据库url和服务器名
so database url and server name
实际上是service的名称
is actually the name of the service it's
就这么简单
as simple as that
我们调用的service叫mongodb-service
so what do we call our service we called
所以我要复制这个service名
it mongodb service so i'm going to copy
它将是
the service name and that's going to be
数据库服务器url的值
the database server url
然后为了保持文件名的一致性
so i'm going to copy that and let's actually call it
保存文件为mongo-configmap.yaml
config map for consistency and save it
就像secret一样
and just like with secret the order of
执行或创建组件的顺序很重要
execution or creation matters so i have to have
必须先已经在集群中有一个ConfigMap
a config map already in the cluster so
然后才能引用它
that i can reference it
所以当我们写完配置
so when we're done i have to create the
我需要先创建ConfigMap
configmap first and then
然后再是deployment
the deployment so the way that i can
这样才能让deployment内部引用ConfigMap
reference the config map
和Secret非常类似
inside the deployment is very similar to secret
所以我要从secret复制整个内容
so i'm actually gonna copy the whole thing from secret
把它放在这里，唯一不同的是
put it here the only thing different
这部分不是secret
here is that instead of secret i'm gonna say
而是configMap，显然属性名都是驼峰编码
config map it's all camel case and
显然名字是configMap，我们这么给它命名的
obviously the name is gonna be config map that's what we
emmm就是这个名字
called it i think yes that's the name
我们来复制一下
let's actually copy it
接着，键是键值对中的key
and again the key is the key in the key value pair here
我们复制一下，现在我有了我们的
so let's copy that as well so now i have our
Mongo Express的deployment，这些都是标准的格式
express deployment these are just standard stuff
这就是pod的蓝图，或者说已有容器的配置
and this is where the pod blueprint or container
我们开放了端口8081
configuration exists we have exposed
这是标签为最新的镜像
port 8081 this is the image
这些是
with the latest tag and these are the
三个环境变量
three environmental variables
Mongo Express需要它们从而连接
that express needs to connect and
并验证mongodb
authenticate with mongodb
部署完成了，让我们继续
so deployment is done and let's go ahead and
先创建ConfigMap然后再创建deployment
create config map first and then express deployment
执行命令kubectl apply + ConfigMap
ctl apply config map and i'm going to do
接着执行命令kubectl apply创建Express
ctl apply express
我们来看看pod
and let's see the pod
容器创建中，看起来不错
so container creating looks good
再来看看pod
so let's see the pod and it's
运行中，我还想看看日志消息
running and i actually want to see the logs
所以我要执行kubectl logs命令
so i'm going to log the express
显示Express服务器启动了
and here you see that express server started and
并连接到数据库，现在是最后一步
database connected so now the final step
要能让浏览器访问到Express
is to access express from a browser
为了做到这一点
and in order to do that we are gonna
需要给Mongo Express配置外部service
need an external service for mongo express
让我们也来创建这个
so let's go ahead and create that one as well
清空，回到vscode
so let's clear this output go back to visual code
就像我们上次在deployment文件中做的那样
and as we did last time in the same file as the deployment
我要创建Express的service
i'm gonna create express service because
实际上，从来没有不带service的deployment
actually in practice you never have
所以把它们放在一起是很合理的
deployment without the service so it makes sense to
这就是Express的外部service
keep them together and this is express external service
这个配置现在看起来
and this configuration right now looks exactly same
和mongodb的service配置完全相同
as the db service configuration
甚至端口也是一样的
and even ports are the same like here i
比如这里开放了service的8081端口
have exposed service port at 8081
而targetPort就是容器监听的端口
and target port is where the container
为了创建这个外部service
port is listening so how do i make this
需要做两件事
external service is by doing two things
在spec部分
so in the specification section
我要在selector下面
so i'm gonna do it below the selector
输入一个类型
i'm gonna put a type
这个外部service的类型是负载均衡器(LoadBalancer)
and the type of this external service is load balancer
我认为这对外部service来说是个坏名字
which i think is a bad name for external service because
因为内部service也充当了负载均衡器
internal service also acts as a load
如果我有两个mongodb pod
balancer so if i had two mongodb pods
内部服务也将对这些pod来的请求
the internal service would also load
做负载均衡
balance the requests coming to these pods
所以我认为负载均衡器作为一个类型名
so i think the load balancer type name was
选得不是很好，因为它可能让人困惑
chosen not very well because it could be confusing
但是这种负载均衡器所做的主要是
but what this type load balancer does basically is it
通过为service分配外部可访问的ip地址
accepts external requests
接受外部请求
by assigning the service an external ip address
我们要做的另一件事
so another thing that we're going to do
使得这个service可被外部访问
here to make this
就是提供第三个端口
service external is right here we're going to provide
这将是nodePort属性
third port and this is going to be called node port
这基本上就是
and what this is basically is the
此外部ip地址要开放的端口
port where this external ip address will be open
浏览器也要通过此端口
so this will be the port that i'll have to put in the browser
访问service
to access this service and this node port
此端口实际上有一个范围，这个范围是
actually has a range and that range is
在30000到32767之间
between thirty thousand and thirty
所以不能
two thousand something so i can
给它分配和之前一样的端口
not give it the same port as here as i
必须在这个范围内
said it has to be between that range
所以我还是选30000吧
so i'm just going to go with the 30 000
这是在这个范围内的最小值
that's the minimum in that range and that would be it so this
这里的配置将创建一个外部service
configuration here will create an external service
继续，我来演示一下
let's go ahead and do it and i will show you
这些端口到底有什么不同
exactly how these ports differ from each other
所以我要apply一下Express的service
so i'm going to apply express so service created
如果执行get service命令
and if i do get service
可以看到mongodb的service先前被创建
i see that mongodb service that we created previously
类型为ClusterIP
has a type of cluster ip and the
我们刚刚创建的Express的service
express service that we just created
类型是之前明确定义的负载均衡器
is load balancer which is the type that we specifically defined
在内部服务中，我们没有具体指定任何类型
in internal service we didn't specify any type
因为ClusterIP
because cluster ip which is the same as
也就是内部service的类型，是默认的类型
internal service type is default so you
所以在创建内部Service时
don't have to define it when
不需要定义
you're creating internal service and the
不同之处在于
difference here is that
ClusterIP将为service提供
cluster ip will give the service
内部ip地址，即此ip地址
an internal ip address which is this one
这是一个service的内部ip地址
right here so this is an internal ip address
而负载均衡器也给
of the service and load balancer will also give
service提供内部ip地址
service an internal ip address but in
但除此之外，它还会
addition to that it will also
给service一个外部ip地址
give the service an external ip address
其中外部请求
where the external requests
会从这里来，这里在待机
will be coming from and here it says
因为我们在minikube里
pending because we're in mini cube and it
它和常规的k8s设置有一点不同
works a little bit differently in a
这里你也可以看到
regular kubernetes setup here you would also see
一个公共的ip地址
an actual ip address a public one and
这是另一个区别
this is another difference because
因为使用内部ip地址你会有
with internal ip address you just have
给该ip地址的端口
port for that ip address with both
而同时使用内部ip地址和外部ip地址
internal and external ip addresses you have
你也要有相应的两个端口，所以我们必须定义
ports for both of them and that's why we had to define
第三个端口，用于外部ip地址
third port which was for the external ip
如我所说，pending意味着
address as i said pending
它还没有外部ip地址
means that it doesn't have the external ip address yet
所以在minicube中做到这一点的方法是
so in minicube the way to do that is
使用命令
using the command
执行minikube service，我需要service的名称
mini cube service and i'm gonna need the name of the service
那么这个命令会给我的外部service
so this command will basically assign
分配一个公共ip地址
my external service a public ip address
我要执行这个
so i'm gonna execute this
浏览器窗口会打开，我会看到我的Mongo Express的页面
and the browser window will open and i will see my express
如果回到命令行
page so if i go back to the command line you see
可以看到这里给Express的service分配了一个url
that this command here assigned express service
其由公共ip地址
a url with a public ip address or with
或者说外部ip地址
an external ip address
与我们之前通过nodePort定义的端口组成
and the port which is what we defined in the node port
所以我基本上可以复制这个网址
so i can basically copy that command
和这个是一样的
which is the same as this one here
打开了Mongo Express的网页
and i get the page for express
现在有了这样的设置
so now with this setup the way it's
工作就会变成这样
going to work is that
当我在这里做改变的时候
when i make changes here for example i'm
比如我们想创建一个新的数据库叫Test-db
going to create a new database let's call it test db whatever
我将在后台建立一个请求
and i'm going to create a request what
请求会被发送到
just happened in background is that this request landed with
Mongo Express的外部service
the external service of express
然后转交给Mongo Express的pod
which then forwarded it to the express pod
pod连接到mongodb service
and the express part connected to the mongodb
是一个内部service
service and internal service and mongodb
然后，service转发该请求
service then forwarded that request
最后到达mongodb pod
finally to the mongodb pod
然后再往回走，就有了这样的变化
and then all the way back and we have the changes here
这就是如何部署一个简单的
so that's how you deploy a simple
kubernetes应用程序集群
application setup in a kubernetes cluster
在这集视频中，我们将讨论
in this video we're going to go through
命名空间的用法
the usages of a namespace
以及何时和如何使用命名空间的最佳实践
and the best practices of when and how to use a namespace
首先，kubernetes集群中的命名空间
first of all what is a namespace in
是什么，你可以在命名空间中组织资源
kubernetes in kubernetes cluster you can organize
这样您就可以在集群中
resources in namespaces so you can have
拥有多个命名空间
multiple namespaces in a cluster
您可以将命名空间看作
you can think of a namespace as a
在kubernetes集群中的虚拟集群
virtual cluster inside of a kubernetes cluster now when
创建一个集群
you create a cluster
kubernetes默认为您提供开箱即用的命名空间
by default kubernetes gives you namespaces
因此在命令行中
out of the box so in the command line if
我输入kubectctl get namespace
i type cubect ctl get namespaces
我看到了一份清单
i see a list of those out of the box
kubernetes提供的开箱即用的命名空间
namespaces that kubernetes offers
让我们一个一个的看一遍
and let's go through them one by one the
kubernetes-dashboard命名空间
kubernetes dashboard namespace
是在minikube中自动安装的
is shipped automatically in minicube so
这是minikube特有的
it's specific to mini cube
在一个标准集群中你不会有这个
installation you will not have this in a standard cluster
第一个是kube-system
the first one is cube system
kube-system命名空间不是给你用的
cube system namespace is not meant for
所以基本上你不应该
your use so basically you shouldn't
创建也不应该修改
create anything or shouldn't modify
kube-system命名空间中的任何内容
anything in cube system namespace the components
部署在这个命名空间中的是
that are deployed in the namespace are
系统进程
the system processes
他们来自master 管理进程
uh they're from master managing processes
或者kubectl等等，下一个是
or cubectl etc the next one is
kube-public，包含的
kube public and what kube public contains is
基本上是公开可访问的数据
basically the publicly accessible data
它有一个ConfigMap，包含
it has a config map that contains
可访问的集群信息
cluster information which is accessible
即使没有身份验证
even without
如果我在这里输入kubectl cluster-info
authentication so if i type here cube ctl cluster info
这是我得到的输出，一些信息
this is the output that i get through that
第三个是kube-node-lease
information and the third one is cube node lease
是最近才加入kubernetes的
which is actually a recent addition to
这个命名空间的目的是
kubernetes and the purpose of that namespace is that it
保存有关节点心跳的信息
holds information about the heartbeats of nodes so
每个节点基本上都有自己的对象
each node basically gets its own object
它包含了关于那个节点可用性的信息
that contains the information about that node's availability
第四个命名空间是默认命名空间
and the fourth namespace is the default namespace
默认命名空间就是
and default namespace is the one that
在还没有创建新的命名空间时
you're going to be using to create
你将会用它在一开始的时候
the resources at the beginning if you
创建资源
haven't created a new namespace
当然，您可以添加和创建新的命名空间
but of course you can add and create new namespaces
你可以用kubectl create namespace命名实现这个
and the way that you can do it is using kubectl
后面接上命名空间的名称
create namespace command with the name of the namespace
这样我就可以创建我的命名空间
so i can create my namespace
如果我使用kubectl get namespace，我就会看到
and if i do kubectl get namespaces i see
命名空间已经在我的清单上了
that in my list now
另一种创建命名空间的方法是
another way to create namespaces is
使用命名空间配置文件
using a namespace configuration file
我认为这是
which i think
创建命名空间的更好方法
is a better way to create namespaces
因为你可以在配置文件仓库中
because you also have a history
有关于在集群中创建了什么资源的
in your configuration file repository of what resources
历史记录
you created in the cluster okay so now
现在我们了解了命名空间是什么
we saw what namespaces are
你可以创造新的
and that you can create new ones and
kubernetes也提供了一些默认的
that kubernetes offer some of them by default
但问题是为什么需要命名空间
but the question is what is the need for namespaces
你应该何时创建它们
when should you create them and how you
如何使用它们
should use them and the first
第一个使用或创建自己的命名空间的用例如下
use case of using or creating your own namespaces
想象你只用
is the following imagine you have only
kubernetes提供的默认命名空间
default namespace which is provided
在默认名称空间中，你创建了所有你的资源
by kubernetes and you create all your resources
如果有一个
in that default namespace if you have a
复杂的应用程序
complex application
它有多个deployment
that has multiple deployments which
会创建许多pod的副本
create replicas of many pods
你还有很多资源，比如service和ConfigMap等等
and you have resources like services and config maps etc
很快您的默认命名空间
very soon your default namespace is
将充斥着
going to be filled with
不同的组件
different components and it will be
很难有一个对里面的东西的概览
really difficult to have an overview
尤其是我们有
of what's in there especially we have
多个用户在里面创建东西
multiple users creating stuff inside
所以这种情况下使用命名空间是更好的方法
so a better way to use namespaces in this case
将资源分组到不同命名空间中
is to group resources into namespaces so
例如，你可以有一个数据库命名空间
for example you can have a database namespace where
在那里部署你的数据库和它的所有需要的资源
you deploy your database and all its
你可以有一个监控命名空间
required resources and you can have a monitoring
在其中部署prometheus
namespace where you deploy the prometheus
和它需要的所有东西
and all the stuff that it needs
您还可以有elasticstack命名空间
you can also have elasticstack namespace where
部署ElasticSearch Kibana等等
all the  etc resources go
剩下的资源可以放在nginx-Ingress命名空间中
and you can have nginx ingress resources
这是对集群内的资源
so just one way of logically grouping your
进行逻辑分组的一种方式
resources inside of the cluster now
根据kubernetes官方文件
according to the official documentation
在项目较小，10个用户以下时
of kubernetes you shouldn't use
你不应该使用命名空间
namespaces if you have smaller projects and up to 10 users
我个人认为利用命名空间中对资源进行分组
i personally think that it's always good idea to
总是一种好的方法
group your resources in namespaces because
因为就像我说的，即使你有一个小项目，用户只有10个
as i said even if you have a small project and
对于你的应用程序
10 users you might still need some
你可能还需要一些额外资源
additional resources for your
就像日志系统
application like you know logging system
和监控系统
and monitoring system
即使使用最小的设置
and even with the minimum setup you can
你也已经
already get
把太多东西都扔进一个默认名称空间里了
too much to just throw everything in a default namespace
另一个需要用到命名空间的用例是
another use case where you will need to use namespaces
如果你有多个团队，想象一下
if you have multiple teams so imagine
这样的场景
the scenario you have
使用同一个集群的两个团队
two teams that use the same cluster
其中一个团队部署了一个应用程序
and one team deploys an application
被称为
which is called
my-app deployment，这是
my app deployment that's the name of the
他们创造的deployment的名字
deployment they create
这个deployment有它特定的配置
and that deployment has its certain configuration
如果另一队不小心弄了
now if another team had a deployment that
相同名字的deployment
accidentally had the same name but a
但是配置不同
different configuration
他们创造了deployment或apply了它
and they created the deployment or they applied it
他们会覆盖第一队的deployment
they would overwrite the first team's deployment
如果他们用的是
and if they're using for example a
jenkins或者其他自动部署的方式
jenkins or some automated way to deploy those
来创建或部署那个应用程序
that application or to create that
他们甚至都不会知道
deployment they wouldn't even know that
它们覆盖或破坏了另一个
they overwrote or disrupted another
团队的deployment
team's deployment
所以要避免再次发生这样的冲突
so to avoid such kind of conflicts again
您可以使用
you can use
命名空间，这样每个团队都可以
namespaces so that each team can
在它们自己的命名空间中工作
work in their own namespace without
以免破坏了另一个deployment
disrupting the other
使用命名空间的另一个用例是
another use case for using namespaces is
假设你有一个集群
let's say you have one cluster and you
你想要让
want to host
生产环境和开发环境
both staging and development environment
在同一集群中，这么做的原因是
in the same cluster and the reason for
举个例子，如果你在用
that is that for example if you're using
比如nginx控制器或者elasticstack
something like nginx controller or elasticstack
用于日志管理，您可以
used for logging for example you can
将它部署在一个集群中并让两种环境都使用它
deploy it in one cluster and use it for both environments
这样你就不用部署
in that way you don't have to deploy
这些公共资源两遍
these common resources
在两个不同的集群中各部署一遍
twice in two different clusters so now
所以现在生产环境
the staging can use
可以用这些资源
both resources as well as the
开发环境也可以
development environment
使用命名空间的另一个用例是
another use case for using namespaces is
当您的应用程序使用蓝绿部署方法时
when you use blue-green deployment for application
即在同一个集群中，你想要
which means that in the same cluster you want to have
产品有两个不同版本
two different versions of production
当前生产版本处于激活状态
so the one that is active that is in production now
另一个是版本是
and another one that is going to be the
下一个生产版本
next production version
应用程序的版本
the versions of the applications in
对应蓝色和绿色
those blue and green production
命名空间将有所不同
namespaces will be different
但是和我们之前看到的一样
however the same as we saw before in
生产环境和开发环境的例子
staging and development
命名空间可能需要使用
this namespaces might need to use the
相同的资源
same resources
比如nginx控制器或elasticstack
like again nginx controller or elasticstack
这样它们就可以同时使用
and this way again they can both use
这种常见的
this common
无需设置的共享资源
shared resources without having to set
而无需建立一个单独的集群
up a separate cluster
还有一个使用命名空间的用例是
so one more use case for using namespaces
是当你在与多个团队合作时
is to limit the resources and
限制对命名空间资源的访问
access to namespaces when you're working with multiple teams
再一次，我们有这样一种情形
so again we have a scenario where we
集群有两个团队在一起工作
have two teams working in the same cluster
每一个都有自己的命名空间
and each one of them has their own
在这种情形下你可以
namespace so what you can do in this scenario is that
只给其它团队访问权限
you can give the teams access to only
所以他们只能
their namespace so they can only be able to
在他们自己的名称空间中创建更新删除资源
create updates delete resources in their own namespace
但是他们在另一个命名空间里什么也做不了
but they can't do anything in the other name spaces
在这种情况下，你可以限制或甚至
in this way you even restrict or even
最小化一个团队
minimize the risk of one team
意外干扰另一个团队工作的风险
accidentally interfering with another team's work
所以每个人都有自己的安全的
so each one has their own secured
孤立的环境
isolated environment additional thing
此外
that you can do
你能在命名空间级别上做的是
on a namespace level is limit the resources
限制每个命名空间使用的资源
that each namespace consumes because if
假设你有一个集群
you have a cluster with
想给每个团队分配有限的资源
limited resources you want to give each team
想让他们的应用程序共享资源
a share of resources for their application
假设有一个团队消耗了太多资源
so if one team let's say consumes too much resources
然后其他团队的资源最终会少得多
then other teams will eventually have much less
他们的应用可能也就无法调度
and their applications may not schedule
因为那样集群资源就会耗尽
because the cluster will run out of the
所以你能做的就是
resources so what you can do is that
给每个命名空间定义资源配额
per namespace you can define resource quotas that
限制一个命名空间可以用多少cpu ram存储资源
limit how much cpu ram storage resources
所以我希望
one namespace can use so i hope walking
通过这些场景帮助您
through these scenarios helped you
分析在哪些用例，以及
analyze in which use cases and how you
在您的具体项目中应该如何使用命名空间
should use namespaces in your specific
有几个
project there are several
你应该考虑的特征
characteristics that you should consider
在决定如何分组和如何使用命名空间之前
before deciding how to group and how to use namespaces
第一个是你无法从另一个名称空间
the first one is that you can't access
访问大部分资源
most of the resources
例如如果你有
from another namespace so for example if you have
项目a中的ConfigMap
a configuration map in project a namespace
引用数据库的service
that references the database service you can't
你不能在项目b中使用这个ConfigMap
use that config map in project b namespace
但相反，你必须在项目b创建
but instead you will have to create the
相同的ConfigMap
same config map
也引用数据库的service
that also references the database service so each
所以每个命名空间将定义或必须定义
namespace will define or must define
它自己的ConfigMap，即使它们引用相同的service
its own config map even if it's the same reference
这同样适用于secret
and the same applies to secret so for
举个例子
example if you have
如果你有共享service的凭据
credentials of a shared service you will
必须在每个需要该凭据的命名空间
have to create that secret in each
都创造那个secret
namespace where you are going to need that however
然而可以跨命名空间共享的资源
a resource that you can share across namespaces
只有service，这是我们在之前的幻灯片中看到的
is service and that's what we saw in the previous slide
所以在项目b命名空间中的ConfigMap
so config map in project b namespace
引用service
references service that is going to be
最终在pod中使用
used eventually in a pod
它的工作原理是
and the way it works is that in a
在configmap的定义中，数据库url
configmap definition the database url
是它的名字，即mysql-service加上
in addition to its name which is mysql service
命名空间的名称
will have namespace at the end so using
使用这个url你可以从另一个命名空间
that url you can actually access services
访问service
from other namespaces which is a very
这是一件非常实际的事情
practical thing
这就是你可以从另一个命名空间
and this is how you can actually use
使用共享资源
shared resources like
如elasticsearch或nginx等
elasticsearch or nginx from
的方法
other namespaces and one more
另一个特点是
characteristic is that
我们看到了大部分的组件资源
we saw that most of the components
可以在一个命名空间中被创建
resources can be created
但是k8s中还有一些组件
uh within a namespace but there are some
是不可以放在命名空间中的
components in kubernetes they're not
它们基本上
namespaced so to say um so basically they live
在整个集群中全局生存
just globally in the cluster and you can't
不能把他们隔离起来，或者把他们放在某个命名空间中
isolate them or put them in a certain namespace and
这类资源的例子有volume或
examples of such resources are volume or
可持久化volume以及
persistent volume and
节点，所以基本上当你创建volume
node so basically when you create the
它是可被整个集群访问的
volume it's going to be accessible
因为
throughout the whole cluster because
它不在命名空间中
it's not in a namespace
你可以列出没有绑定到名称空间
and you can actually list components
的组件
they're not bound to a namespace
通过使用kubectl api-resources命名
using a command cubectl api resources
命名空间选项为false，同样地
namespaced false and the same way you can also
你也可以列出所有被绑定到一个命名空间的资源
list all the resources that are bound to a namespace
通过将namespace选项置为true，现在您已经
using namespace true so now that you've
了解了名称空间是什么
learned what the namespaces are
为什么要使用它们，在什么情况下使用它们有意义
why to use them in which cases it makes sense to
同时还有一些
use them in which way and also some
你应该考虑的特征
characteristics that you should consider
让我们来看看如何创建
let's actually see how to create
命名空间中的组件
components in a namespace
在上一个示例中
in the last example we've created
我们使用配置文件创建了组件
components using configuration files
但是没有定义一个命名空间
and nowhere there we have defined a namespace
默认情况下，如果你
so what happens is by default if you
不为组件提供命名空间
don't provide a namespace to a component
它在默认命名空间中创建它们
it creates them in a default namespace
如果我apply这个ConfigMap组件
so if i apply this config map component
现在我们来做一下
and let's do that actually right now so
kubectl apply -f configmap
如果我apply那个，接着做kubectl get
if i apply that and i do cube ctl get config map
我的ConfigMap是在默认命名空间中被创建的
my config map was created in a default namespace
注意，即使是用kubectl get configmap命令
and notice that even in the cubectl getconfigmap command i
也没有使用命名空间，因为
didn't use a namespace because cubectl
get或kubectl命令默认使用默认命名空间
get or cubectl commands they take the default namespace
所以kubectl get configmap实际上
as a default so kubectl get configmap is actually
和kubectl get configmap -n default一样
same as kubectl get configmap dash default namespace so
它们是相同的指令，只是简写的方式
these are the same commands it's just a
会默认采用
shortcut because it takes
默认(default)命名空间
default as a default namespace okay so
为了在特定的命名空间中
one way that i can create this config map
创建这个ConfigMap
in a specific namespace is using
可以用kubectl apply命令
kubectl apply command
但是要添加命名空间选项 --namespace
but adding flag namespace
接上命名空间的名字
and the namespace name so this will
这会在我的命名空间中
create config map
创建ConfigMap，这是一种方法
in my namespace and this is one way to
做这件事的另一种方法是
do it another way is
在配置文件内进行修改
inside the configuration file itself so
我可以调整这个configmap
i can adjust this configmap configuration file to
来包括关于
include the information about the
目标命名空间的信息
destination namespace itself
因此，我可以在元数据中添加一个namespace属性
so in the metadata i can add a namespace attribute
如果我apply这个配置文件
so if i apply this configuration file
再次使用kubectl apply，现在我想get这个
again using cubectl apply and now if i want to get the
刚刚创建的组件
component that i created
在这个特定的命名空间中
in this specific namespace then i have to add
就需要在kubectl get加上选项
the option or the flag to kubectl get command
因为就像我说的，默认情况下它会
because as i said by default it will
只检查默认命名空间
check only in the default namespace
因此，我建议
so i recommend using the namespace
在配置文件中使用命名空间
attribute in a configuration file
而不是提供到
instead of providing it
kubectl命令中
to the cube ctl command because one
因为一来，这是一个更好的书写方式
it's it's better documented so you know
只看配置文件就知道
by just looking at the configuration file
组件是在哪里创建的
where the component is getting created
这是重要的信息
because that could be an
二来
important information and second if
如果您正在使用自动部署
you're using automated deployment
来apply配置文件
where you're just applying the
这将是
configuration files then again this will
一个更方便的方法
be a more convenient way to do it
现在我们举个场景的例子
now if for example we take a scenario
一个团队有自己的名称空间
where one team gets their own namespace
并且必须
and that has to
完全在命名空间中工作
work entirely in the namespace it could
这是很烦人的
be pretty annoying to have to
如果在每个kubectl命令添加这个命名空间标记的话
add this namespace tag to every cubectl command
所以为了让它更方便
so in order to make it more convenient
有一个办法
there is a way to
更改这个默认或激活状态的名称空间
change this default or active namespace which is
到其它你选择的任何名称空间
default namespace to whatever namespace
kubernetes或kubectl并没有
you choose and kubernetes or cubactl doesn't have
提供任何开箱即用的工具
any out of the box solution for that but
但是有一种工具叫做kubens
there is a tool called
你可以安装它来解决
cubens or cubans and you have to install the tool
在mac上，我要执行brew install kubectx
so on mac so i'm going to execute brew install
这样就可以安装kubens工具
cube ctx so this will install
所以一旦我安装了kubens
cubans tool as well so once i have the
我就可以
kubens installed i can
执行kubens命令
just execute kubens command
这会给我一份所有
and this will give me a list of all the
命名空间的列表，高光显示的就是激活状态的命名空间
name spaces and highlight the one that is
这里是默认命名空间
active which is default right now and if
如果我想要改变激活状态的命名空间
i want to change the active
我可以执行kubens my-namespace
namespace i can do kubens my namespace
这将会改变激活状态的命名空间
and this will switch the active namespace so if i do
再做kubens，现在我看到激活的是my-namespace
kubens now i see that active one is my namespace
现在我可以执行kubectl命令
so now i can execute cubectl commands without
而不需要提供my-namespace命名空间了
providing mynamespace namespace
但很明显，如果你在命名空间中转换多次
but obviously if you switch a lot between the namespaces
这样就不太方便了
this will not be so much convenient
对于您自己的操作系统和环境
for your own operating system and
可能会有不同的安装过程
environment there will be different installation
所以我要在简介下方
process so i'm going to link the cube
加上kubectx安装指南的链接
ctx installation guide in the description below
在这段视频中，我们会讲
so in this video we're going to talk
什么是Ingress
about what ingress is
你应该如何使用它，还有
and how you should use it and also what are
Ingress有哪些不同的用例
different use cases for ingress so first
首先让我们想象一个简单的
of all let's imagine a simple
kubernetes集群，我们有一个应用程序的pod
kubernetes cluster where we have a pod
以及相应的my-app service
of my application and its corresponding
首先
service my app service so the first
你的ui应用需要
thing you need for your ui application
可通过浏览器访问
is to be accessible
所以为了外部请求能够
through browser right so for external requests to be able to
到达您的应用程序
reach your application so one way to do that
一个简单的方法是通过外部service
an easy way is through an external
也就是您可以使用
service where basically you can access the application using
http协议 + ip地址
http protocol the ip address of
加上节点和端口
the node and the port however this is
这有利于测试用例，如果你想
good for test cases and if you want to try
非常快地尝试一些东西的话
something very fast
但这不是最终的产品的样子
but this is not what the final product should look like
最终的成品应该是这样的
the final product should be like this so
你有一个给应用程序的域名
you have a domain name
你想要通过https实现安全连接
for application and you want a secure connection
实现这个的方式是
using https so the way to do that is
使用kubernetes组件
using kubernetes component
叫做ingress，你将会有my-app ingress
called ingress so you'll have my app
而不是外部service
ingress and instead of external service
相反你会有内部service
you would instead have an internal service so you
这样不会通过ip地址和端口开放您的应用程序
would not open your application through the ip address and the port
现在，如果请求来自浏览器
and now if the request comes from the
它会首先到达Ingress
browser it's going to
然后Ingress
first reach the ingress and ingress then
会把它重定向到内部Service
we'll redirect it to the internal service
然后它最终会到达pod
and then it will eventually end up with
现在我们看一看
the pod so now let's actually take a look and see how
外部service怎么配置
external service configuration
这样你就有一个实际的理解
looks like so that you have a practical understanding
你有一个负载均衡器类型的service
so you have the service which is of type load balancer
这意味着我们要向公众开放
this means we are opening it to public by assigning
通过给Service分配一个外部ip地址以及端口号
an external ip address to the service and this is
用户就可以通过你在这里指定的
the port number that user can access the application
外部ip地址以及端口号
at so basically the ip address the external ip address
访问应用程序
and the port number that you specify here
现在有了Ingress
now with ingress of course it looks
当然它看起来很不同
differently so let's go
看一下Ingress的语法
through the syntax of ingress basically
类型是Ingress而不是Service
you have a kind ingress instead of a service and in the
在spec部分
specification where the whole configuration
你有所谓的规则或者路由规则
happens you have so-called rules or routing rules
这基本上定义了域名地址
and this basically defines that the main address or
或者对该主机的所有请求都必须
all the requests to that host must be
转发给内部service
forwarded to an internal service
这就是用户在浏览器中要输入的域名
so this is the host that user will enter in the browser
在ingress中，用户这样定义映射
and in ingress users define a mapping so what happens when
如果向该主机发出请求出现了问题
that request to that host gets issued
内部就会将其重定向到service
you redirect it internally to a service
这里的路径是指url
the path here basically means the url path
域名之后的所有东西
so everything after the domain name
要在这条路径加上斜杠
so slash whatever path comes up to that
您可以在这里定义这些规则，稍后我们会看到一些
you can define those rules here and we'll see some different
关于路径配置的示例
examples of the path configuration later
正如你在这个配置中看到的
and as you see here in this configuration
我们用的是http协议
we have a http protocol so later
稍后在这段视频中，我将向你们展示如何配置https连接
in this video i'm going to show you how to configure https
通过使用Ingress组件
connection using ingress component so
现在在spec中我们没有任何关于安全连接的配置
right now in the specification we don't have anything configured
它只是http
for the secure connection it's just http
这里需要注意的一点是
and one thing to note here is that
这里的http属性
this http attribute here does not correspond
和这个并不对应，这是一个协议
to this one here this is a protocol that
传入的请求被转发到
the incoming request gets forwarded to
给内部service
to the internal service so this is
所以这实际上是第二步
actually the second step and
不要把它和这个弄混了
not to confuse it with this one and now
让我们看看
let's see
内部service与Ingress是怎么运作的
how the internal service to that ingress will look like
所以基本上backend就是目标
so basically backend is the target
传入的请求将被重定向到那里
where the request the incoming request will be redirected
serviceName应该对应内部service的名称
and the service name should correspond
如下所示
the internal service name like this
并且servicePort应该是内部Service的端口
and the port should be the internal service port
你可以看到在外部和内部service之间
and as you see here the only difference
唯一的区别
between the external and internal services
就是在内部service中我不再有
is that here in internal service i don't
第三个端口
have the third port which is the node
也就是从30000开始的节点端口
ports starting from thirty thousand we
现在在这里的属性
now have that attribute here
类型是默认类型，不是负载平衡器
and the type is a default type not a load balancer but
而是内部service类型，即集群ip
internal service type which is cluster ip so
这应该是一个有效的域名地址
this should be a valid domain address so you can just
只要满足有效，在这里可以写任何东西
write anything here it has to be first of all valid
你应该把域名映射到
and you should map that domain name to
节点的ip地址
ip address of the node that represents
也就是你的kubernetes集群的入口
an entry point to your kubernetes cluster
举个例子，如果你决定
so for example if you decide that one of
kubernetes集群中的一个节点
the nodes inside the kubernetes cluster
将会是入口，那么你
is going to be the entry point then you
应该把这个映射到该节点的ip地址
should map this to the ip address of that node or
我们待会儿就会看到
and we will see that later if you
如果你在kubernetes集群之外配置一个服务器
configure a server outside of the kubernetes cluster that
让它成为到你的kubernetes集群的入口点
will become the entry point to your kubernetes cluster then you
应该让这里的主机名映射到该服务器的ip地址
should map this host name to the ip address of that
现在我们学习了
server so now that we saw
kubernetes的Ingress组件的基本内容
what kubernetes ingress components looks
让我们看看如何
like let's see how to actually configure
在集群中配置Ingress
ingress in the cluster so remember this
记住这张我在一开始给你们看的图
diagram i showed you at the beginning
基本上你有一个pod、service
so basically you have a pod service and
和相应的Ingress
corresponding ingress
现在，如果你仅创建了这个ingress组件
now if you create that ingress component
是不足以
alone that won't be uh enough
使Ingress路由规则工作的
for ingress routing rules to work
此外你需要的是一个Ingress的实现
what you need in addition is an implementation for ingress
这个实现被称作Ingress控制器
and that implementation is called ingress controller
第一步是安装一个
so the step one will be to install an
Ingress控制器
ingress controllers which is
基本上是另一个或另一组
basically another pod or another set of
在您的kubernetes集群的节点上运行的pod
parts that run on your node in your kubernetes cluster
从而评价和处理Ingress规则
and thus evaluation and processing of ingress
所以我向您展示过的ingress组件的yaml文件
rules so the yaml file that i showed you with the
基本上就是这个部分
ingress component is basically this part right here
是要额外安装在kubernetes集群中的
and this has to be additionally installed in kubernetes cluster
所以什么是Ingress控制器，确切地说
so what is ingress controller um exactly
Ingress控制器的功能是
the function of ingress controller is to
评估所有你在集群中定义的规则
evaluate all the rules that you have defined in your cluster
用这种方式来管理所有的重定向
and this way to manage all the redirections so basically
这将是你配置过的
this will be the entry point in the cluster for all the
对集群内所有域名和子域名请求的入口点
requests to that domain or subdomain rules that you've
它将评估所有规则
configured and this will evaluate all the rules because
因为你可能有50条规则或者50个Ingress组件
you may have 50 rules or 50 ingress
在您的集群中
components created in your cluster it
它会评估所有的规则并在此基础上决定
will evaluate all the rules and decide based on that
哪条转发规则适用于此具体的请求
which forwarding rule applies for that specific request
为了安装这个Ingress的实现
so in order to install this implementation of
进入你的集群，你必须
ingress in your cluster you have to
在很多不同的第三方实现中选择
decide which one of many different third-party implementations
我会在简介中
you want to choose from i'll put a link
放一个链接，里面是
of the whole list in the description where you see
不同种类的Ingress控制器的列表
different kinds of ingress controllers
你可以从中选择
you can choose from
有一个来自kubernetes自己的
there is one from kubernetes itself
叫做kubernetes nginx ingress控制器
which is kubernetes nginx
但是还有其他的
ingress controller but there are others
一旦你在集群中安装了Ingress控制器
as well so once you install ingress controller in your cluster
你可以
you're good to go
创造Ingress，整个配置就可以工作了
create ingress roles and the whole configuration is going to work
现在我已经向你们展示了如何
so now that i've shown you how ingress
在kubernetes集群中使用Ingress
can be used in a kubernetes cluster
有一件事我认为是很重要的
there is one thing that i think is important to understand
就设置整个集群
in terms of setting up the whole cluster
能够接收外部请求而言
to be able to receive external requests
首先你要考虑的是
now first of all you have to consider
kubernetes所在的环境
the environment where your kubernetes
如果您正在使用一些云服务供应商
cluster is running if you are using some cloud
比如亚马逊网络服务
service provider like amazon web services
谷歌云以及更多
google cloud lino there are a couple more that have
它们都有现成的kubernetes解决方案
out of the box kubernetes solutions um
或者它们有自己的虚拟化、负载均衡等等
or they have their own virtualized load balances
你的集群配置会
etc your cluster configuration would
看起来像这样
look something like this
你会有一个云负载均衡器
so you would have a cloud load balancer
这是由云供应商特别实现的
that is specifically implemented by that cloud provider and
从浏览器来的外部请求
external requests coming from the browser will first
将首先到达负载均衡器
hit the load balancer and that load
负载均衡器将重定向该请求
balancer then will redirect
到Ingress控制器
the request to ingress controller now this is not
这不是唯一的方式
the only way to do it even in cloud
即使是在云端
environment you can do it in
也有很多不同的方式，但是这个是最常见的策略
in a couple of different ways but this is one of the most common
采用云供应商做这个的优势
uh strategies an advantage of
是你不必
using cloud provider for that is that you don't have to
自己实现一个负载均衡器
implement a load balancer yourself so
只用付出最少的努力
with minimal effort probably on most
大多数云供应商会给您提供负载均衡器
cloud providers you will have the load
启动并运行
balancer up and running
并准备好接受那些请求
and ready to receive those requests and
然后把这些请求转发给你的kubernetes集群
forward those requests then to your kubernetes cluster
这是很简单的配置
so very easy setup now if you're
如果你要将kubernetes集群部署到裸机环境
deploying your kubernetes cluster on a bare metal environment
那你就得自己做那部分
then you would have to do that part
所以基本上你必须自己配置
yourself so basically you would have to configure
kubernetes集群的某种入口点
some kind of entry point to your kubernetes cluster yourself
有一大堆不同的方式做这件事
and there's a whole list of different
我要把它们放在简介中
ways to do that and i'm going to put that also in the description
但一般来说，要么在集群里
but generally speaking either inside of a cluster
或者在集群用一个单独的服务器
or outside as a separate server
你必须提供一个入口点
you will have to provide an entry point
其中一个类型是外部代理服务器
and one of those types is an external proxy server
可以是软件或硬件解决方案
which can be a software or hardware solution
它将承担负载均衡器和集群入口点的角色
that will take the role of that load balancer and entry point
所以基本上这意味着
to your cluster so basically what this would mean
你会有一个单独的服务器
is that you will have a separate server
你会给它一个公共ip地址
and you would give this a public ip
你可以开发端口
address and you would open the ports
从而让请求被接受
in order for the requests to be accepted
然后这个代理服务器就会
and this proxy server then will act
作为集群的入口点
as an entry point to your cluster so
成为唯一一个
this will be the only one
可以从外部访问的服务器
accessible externally so none of the
所以kubernetes集群中的其他服务器没有可以
servers in your kubernetes cluster will have
可公开访问的ip地址
publicly accessible ip address which is
显然这是一个很安全的实践
obviously a very good security practice
因此，所有请求都将进入代理服务器
so all the requests will enter the proxy server
然后将重定向请求
and that will then redirect the request
到Ingress控制器
to ingress controller
然后Ingress控制器会决定
and ingress controller will then decide which
哪一个规则适用于这个特定的请求
ingress rule applies to that specific request
然后全部内部请求转发将会发生
and the whole internal request forwarding will happen
就像我说的，有不同的方法来配置和建立它
so as i said there are different ways to configure that
取决于你在使用哪个环境
and to set it up depending on which environment you are
还有你选择的方法
and also which approach you choose but i
但我认为这是一个
think it's a very important concept to
理解整个集群配置的非常重要的概念
understand how the whole
在我的例子中
cluster setup works so in my case since i'm using
我在笔记本电脑上用minikube来演示这一切
a mini cube to demonstrate all this on my laptop
设置将非常简单
the setup will be pretty easy and even
尽管它可能并不完全适用于你的集群设置
though this might not apply exactly to your cluster setting
不过在实践中你会看到这些东西是怎么工作的
still you will see in practice how all these things work
第一件事是在minikube中安装ingress控制器
so the first thing is to install ingress controller
方法是
in mini cube and the way to do that is by
执行minikube addons enable ingress命令
executing mini cube add-ons enable
这会自动配置
ingress so what this does is automatically configures
或者自动启动ingress控制器的
or automatically starts the kubernetes
k8s nginx实现
nginx implementation of ingress controller so that's one
这是众多第三方实现中的一种
of the many third-party implementations
你也可以
which you can also
在生产环境中安全使用它
safely use in production environments
而不仅仅是在迷你方块中
not just mini cube but this is what
minikube实际上提供给你
minicube actually offers you out of the box so with one
一个简单的现成的命令
simple command ingress controller will
让Ingress控制器在集群中被配置
be configured in your cluster
如果你在kube-system命名空间执行kubectl get pod
and if you do cube ctl get pod in a cube system namespace
你会看到nginx ingress controller pod已经在集群中运行了
you will see the nginx ingress controller pod
所以一旦安装了Ingress控制器
running in your cluster so once i have ingress controller
现在我可以创建一个Ingress规则
installed now i can create an ingress
可以由控制器评估
rule that the controller can
移步命令行
evaluate so let's actually head over to the command line
我要在那里创建用于kubernetes面板组件
where i'm going to create ingress rule
的Ingress规则
for kubernetes dashboard component
在我的minikube集群中
so in my minicube cluster i have
有kubernetes面板
kubernetes dashboard which is right now
现在还无法被外部访问
not accessible externally
所以我要做的是既然我已经
so what i'm gonna do is since i already
为kubernetes面板提供了内部service
have internal service for kubernetes dashboard
以及一个相应的端口
and a port for that i'm going to
我就要为面板配置Ingress规则
configure an ingress rule
这样我就能使用一些域名
for the dashboard so i can access it from a browser
通过浏览器访问它了
using some domain name
这展示了我的所有在k8s面板的
so i'm gonna so this shows me all the components that
组件
i have in k8s dashboard
既然我已经有给k8s面板的内部sersvice
and since i already have uh internal service
pod也正在运行
for kubernetes dashboard and the pod that's running
我现在可以创建一个Ingress规则
i can now create an ingress uh rule
以便通过一些主机名访问k8s面板
in order to access the kubernetes dashboard using some
让我们继续
host name so let's go ahead and do that
所以我要给k8s面板创建一个Ingress
so i'm gonna create an ingress
kubernetes的仪表盘，这些是元数据
for kubernetes dashboard um so these are just metadata
名字是dashboard-ingress
the name is going to be dashboard
命名空间将会是
ingress and the namespace is going to be
和service以及pod在同一个命名空间中
in the same namespace as the service and pod
在spec中，我们会定义规则
so in the specification we are going to define
第一条规则
the rules so the first rule
是我要调用的主机名
is the host name i'm just gonna
我要定义dashboard.com
call i'm gonna define dashboard.com
以及http转发到内部service
and the http forwarding to internal service
path
path let's leave it at all path
然后就是service的backend
and this is the backend of the service
所以serviceName将是
so service name will be
我们在这里看到的service的名字
what we saw here so this is the service name
以及servicePort
and service port
这里service监听的端口80
is where the service listens so this is actually 80
就在这里
right here and this will be it that's
这就是Ingress的配置
the ingress configuration
转发所有被指向dashboard.com
for uh forwarding every request
的请求
that is directed to dashboard.com
转发到内部kubernetes dashboard service
to internal kubernetes dashboard service
我们知道它是内部的
and we know it's internal because its
因为它类型为“ClusterIp”
type is cluster ip so
没有外部ip地址
no external ip address so obviously
显然我只是编了个主机名dashboard.com
i just made up host name dashboard.com
它没有注册在任何地方
it's not registered anywhere and i also didn't
我也没有配置任意ip地址
configure anywhere which ip address
用于主机名的解析
this host name should resolve to and
而这是你必须配置的东西
this is something that you will always have to configure
首先让我们来创建这个ingress规则
so first of all let's actually create that ingress rule
输入kubectl apply
so kubectl apply
文件名为dashboard-ingress.yaml
and it's called dashboard ingress
可以看到Ingress被创建了
yaml see ingress was created so if i do
所以如果我在命名空间get ingress
get ingress in the namespace
我应该在这里看到我的ingress
i should see my ingress here and as you see
如你所见，地址现在是空的，因为它需要
address is now empty because it takes a
还有一点时间
little bit of time to
将地址分配给ingress
assign the address um to ingress
所以我们得等着
so we'll have to wait for that to get
等着ip地址映射到这个主机
the ip address that will map to this host
所以我要watch一下
so i'm just gonna watch this
现在看到那个地址是被分配了
and it's i see that address was assigned
所以我现在要做的是
so what i'm gonna do now is that i'm gonna
把这个地址写进/etc/hosts文件
take that address and in my etc hosts file
写在最后，定义这个映射
at the end i'm going to define that mapping
这样ip地址就会映射到dashboard.com，可以本地工作了
so that ip address will be mapped to dashboard.com and again this works
如果我要
locally if i'm going to
在浏览器中输入dashboard.com
type dashboard.com in the browser this
就会去被映射的ip地址
will be the ip address that it's going to be
它基本上意味着
mapped to which basically means that the
进入我的minikube集群的请求将会
request will come in to my mini cube cluster will be
移交给Ingress控制器
handed over to ingress controller and ingress
接着Ingress控制器将会评估
controller then will go and evaluate
我在这里定义的规则
this rule that i've defined here
并将请求转发给service
and forward that request to service
这就是我们需要的配置
so this is all the configuration we need
现在我要输入dashboard.com
so now i'm gonna go and enter dashboard.com
我将在这里看到我的kubernetes面板
and i will see my kubernetes dashboard here
Ingress还有一个叫默认backend的东西
so ingress also has something called a default backend
如果我做kubectl describe ingress
so if i do cubectl describe ingress
接上ingress的名字和命名空间
the name of the ingress and the namespace
我会得到这个输出
i'll get this output and here
有一个名为default backend的属性
there is an attribute called default backend
映射到默认的http后端，端口80
that maps to default http backend
这意味着
port 80. so what this means is that
每当请求进入
whenever a request comes into the
kubernetes集群
kubernetes cluster
它没有映射到任何后端
that is not mapped to any backend so
也就没有规则
there is no rule
将请求映射到其它service
for mapping that request to an to a service
那么这个默认后端就会
then this default backend is used
被用于处理这个请求
to handle that request so obviously
所以很明显，如果您没有在集群中创建或定义此service
if you don't have this service created or defined
kubernetes将尝试
in your cluster kubernetes will try to
转发给它找不到的service
forward it to the service it won't find it
你会得到一些默认错误响应
and you would get some default error response
例如，如果我输入一些
so for example if i entered some
我没有配置的路径
path that i haven't configured i just
就会找不到页面
get page not found
一个很好的用法是
so a good usage for that is to define
当页面无法找到时，定义自定义错误消息
custom error messages when a page isn't found
当有请求时，你可以或者程序可以
when a request comes in that you can
处理错误消息
handle or the application can handle
这样用户仍然可以看到一些有意义的错误消息
so that users still see some meaningful error message
或者只是一个定制页面
or just a custom page where you can
将它们重定向到您的主页
redirect them to your home page
或者类似的东西
or something like this so all you have to do is
要做到这些你需要创建一个具有名字的内部service
create an internal service with the same name
也就是default-http-backend以及端口号80
so default http backend and the port number
还可以创建一个pod或应用程序
and also create a pod or application
发送那个自定义错误消息响应
that sends that error custom error message response
所以到目前为止，我已经向你们展示了
so till now i have shown you what
什么是Ingress，如何使用它
ingress is and how you can use it i've
我还演示了如何在minikube中创建一个ingress规则
also shown you a demo of how to create an ingress rule
但我们只使用了
in minicube but we've used only
一个非常基本的ingress yaml配置
a very basic ingress yaml configuration
只是简单的转发到一个内部service
just a simple forwarding to one internal service
只有一条路径，但你还可以
with one path but you can do much
做更多关于Ingress配置的事情
more with ingress configuration than just
相比于基本的转发。在下一个部分
basic uh forwarding and in the next section
我们会讲更多的用例
we're gonna go through more use cases of
关于你如何给kubernetes集群中的应用程序
how you can define more fine granular routing for
定义更细粒度的路由
applications inside kubernetes cluster
首先是给相同主机
so the first thing is defining multiple
定义多条路径
paths of the same host so consider
考虑如下用例，谷歌有一个域名
following use case google has
却提供了众多服务
one domain but has many services that it offers
例如，如果你有一个谷歌账户
so for example if you have a google
你可以使用它的分析
account you can use its analytics
你可以用它购物，用它的日历
you can use it shopping you you have a calendar
你有一个gmail等等这些都是
you have a gmail etc so all of these are
单独的应用程序
separate applications
却可以通过相同的域名访问
that are accessible with the same domain
所以假设您有一个应用程序
so consider you have an application that
与之类似
does something similar
所以你提供了两个不同的应用程序
so you offer two separate applications
他们是同一个生态系统的两部分，但你仍然
they're part of the same ecosystem but you still
想要把它们放在不同的url上
want to have them on separate urls so what you
所以你可以在规则中可以定义主机myapp.com
can do is that in rules you can define the host
而在路径部分
which is myapp.com and in the path
可以定义多条路径
section you can define multiple path so if user
如果用户想要访问你的analytics应用程序
wants to access your analytics application
他们必须进入myapp.com/analytics
then they have to enter myapp.com analytics
然后将请求转发给内部的
and that will forward the request to internal and
analytic service及其pod，如果他们想要
analytic service and the pod or if they want to
访问shopping应用程序
access the shopping application then the
那么url将是myapp.com/shopping
url for that would be myapp.com
这样你就可以
shopping so this way you can do
利用同一台主机的一个ingress
forwarding with one ingress
通过多条路径
of the same host to multiple
转发到多个应用程序
applications using
另一个用例是
multiple path another use case is
不使用url
when instead of using urls
区分可访问的不同的应用程序
to make different applications accessible
有些公司使用子域名
some companies use sub-domains so
不用myapp.com/analytics这样的分支
instead of having myapp.com analytics they create
而是用子域名analytics.myapp.com取代
a sub-domain analytics.myapp.com
所以如果你的应用程序是这样配置的
so if you have your application configured that way
您的配置将像这样
your configuration will look like this
不再像前面的例子
so instead of having one host
用一个主机名和多条路径
like in the previous example and multiple path
这里有多个主机名
here inside now you have multiple hosts
每个主机代表一个子域名
where each host represents a subdomain and
在里面你只有一条路径
inside you just have one path that again
将该请求重定向到analytics service
redirects that request to analytic service
很直接
pretty straightforward so now in the
同样的你可以将analytic的请求设置和pod
same request setting you have analytic service
应用到下面，现在请求会看起来像这样
and a pod behind it now the request will look like
通过子域名代替路径
this using the subdomain instead of path
最后一个我提到的话题
and one final topic that i mentioned
我们将在这里讨论
that we'll cover here
就是配置tls证书
is configuring tls certificate till now
到现在我们只看到
we've only seen
http请求的Ingress配置
ingress configuration for http requests but it's
但其实配置https的Ingress转发是非常简单的
super easy to configure https forwarding in
所以你唯一需要的就是
ingress so the only thing that you need to do is
在rules部分上面定义名为tls的属性
define attribute called tls above the rules
hosts主机名还是一样的
section with host which is the same host as right here
secretName是一个secret的引用
and the secret name which is a reference
在一个维持着tls证书的集群中
of a secret that you have to create in a
创建的
cluster that holds that tls certificate so the secret
因此secret的配置看起来像这样
configuration would look like
所以secretName是引用这里
this so the name is the reference right here
数据或实际内容
and the data or the actual contents contain
包含tls证书和tls密钥
tls certificate and tls key
如果你看过我其他的视频
if you've seen my other videos where i
创建不同的组件，如secret
create different components like secret
您可能会注意到这里的type属性
you probably notice the type additional type attribute here
在kubernetes中有一个特定secret的type类型
in kubernetes there is a specific type of a secret
叫做tls，我们得用它
called tls so we'll have to use that type
当你创建一个tls secret时
when you create a tls secret and there are three
有三个小贴士
small notes to be made here one is that
第一，data部分的密钥必须和这里的命名一模一样
the keys of this data have to be named exactly like that
第二，这些值是实际的文件内容
the values are the actual file contents
证书或密钥的内容和
of the certificate or key contents and
而不是文件路径或位置
not the file path or location
所以你必须把所有内容都放进去
so you have to put the whole content
这是编码前的基本知识
here basics before encoded
第三点是你必须
and the third one is that you have to
在与Ingress组件相同的命名空间中
create the secret in the same namespace
创建secret
as the ingress component for it to be
从而能够使用它
able to use that
否则你就不能从另一个命名空间
otherwise you can't reference a secret
引用Secret
from another namespace
这四行就是你所需要的所有配置
and these four lines is all you need to configure
将对该主机的https请求映射到内部service
mapping of an https request to that host to internal service
在这个视频中，我将解释所有的
in this video i'm going to explain all
关于helm的主要概念
the main concepts of helm
这样你就能在你自己的项目中使用它
so that you are able to use it in your own projects
而且helm的版本变化很大
also helm changes a lot from version to
所以理解基本的共同原则
version so understanding the basic
以及更重要的用例
common principles and more importantly
即
its use cases to
何时和为什么使用helm
when and why we use helm will make it
可以使其在实践中更容易使用
easier for you to use it in practice
无论你选择哪个版本
no matter which version you choose so
我要在这个视频中讲的主题分别是
the topics i'm gonna go through in this video are
helm和heml chart是什么
helm and helm charts uh what they are
如何使用它们
how to use them
以及在什么情况下会用到它们
and in which scenarios they're used and
还有什么是Tiller
also what is tiller
以及它在helm体系结构中扮演的角色
and what part it plays in the helm architecture
所以什么是helm? helm有几个主要特征
so what is helm helm has a couple of main features
第一个是
that it's used for the first one is as a
作为kubernetes的包管理器
package manager for kubernetes
你可以把它想象成给kubernetes用的
so you can think of it as ept yum
apt yum或者是hombrew等工具
or hombrew for kubernetes so it's a
所以它是一种方便的方式
convenient way
用于打包kubernetes的yaml文件
for packaging collections of kubernetes yaml files
以及在公共或私人registry分发它们
and distributing them in public and private registry
现在这些定义听起来有点抽象
now these definitions may sound a bit
让我们把它们分解一下
abstract so let's break them down
举一些具体的例子
with specific examples so let's say
您已经将应用程序部署在kubernetes集群中
you have deployed your application in kubernetes cluster
您希望在集群中额外部署elasticsearch
and you want to deploy elasticsearch
这样您的应用程序就可以
additionally in your cluster
收集日志信息
that your application will use to collect
为了在您的kubernetes集群中
its logs in order to deploy
部署Elastic Stack
elastic stack in your kubernetes cluster
你需要几个kubernetes组件
you will need a couple of kubernetes
您需要一个StatefulSet用于
components so you would need a stateful set which is
像数据库这样的有状态应用程序
for stateful applications like databases
您将需要一个ConfigMap
you will need a config map
从而能够从外部配置
with external configuration you would
您需要一个Secret，在那里保存一些凭据
need a secret where some credentials
和秘密数据
and secret data are stored you will need
你要创建kubernetes用户
to create the kubernetes user with
其各有各自的权限
its respective permissions and also
还需要创建一些Service
create couple of services
现在，如果你要手动创建所有这些文件
now if you were to create all of these files manually
通过在互联网上单独搜索它们中的每一个
by searching for each one of them
将是乏味的工作
separately on internet would be a tedious job
直到你集齐所有这些yaml文件
and until you have all these yaml files collected
并进行了测试和试验
and tested and tried out it might take
而且elasticstack在所有集群中的部署
some time and since elasticstack deployment
可以相当标准化
is pretty much the standard across all clusters
但其他人可能不得不
other people will probably have to go
通过同样的方式再部署一次
through the same so it made perfect sense that
所以如果有人曾经创建了这些yaml文件
someone created these yaml files once
然后把它们打包，做成其他人也可用
and packaged them up and made it
将是非常有意义的
available somewhere
这样其他人也会使用
so that other people who also use the
同样的部署，可以使用它们
same kind of deployment could use them
在他们自己的kubernetes集群中
in their kubernetes cluster and that
而这样的yaml文件集
bundle of yaml files
被称为helm chart
is called helm chart so using helm you
所以使用helm你可以创建自己的
can create your own
helm chart或yaml文件集
helm charts or bundles of those yaml files
把它们推到一些helm仓库
and push them to some
使它对其他人可用
helm repository to make it available for others
或者你可以使用它们
or you can consume so you can use
下载并使用现有的
download and use
其他人推到仓库的helm chart
existing helm charts that other people pushed
并使其在不同的仓库中可用
and made available in differentrepositories so
所以一些常用的部署，如数据库应用程序
commonly used deployments like database applications
elasticsearch mongodb mysql or
或者像prometheus这样的监控应用程序
monitoring applications like prometheus
它们都有复杂的配置
that all have this kind of complex setup
也都在一些helm仓库中有可用的helm chart
all have charts available in some helm repository
所以使用一个简单的“helm install chart名”命令
so using a simple helm install chart name command
您可以重用
you can reuse the configuration that
别人已经做完了的配置
someone else has already made
不需付出额外的努力
without additional effort and sometimes
有时那个发布者
that someone is
甚至是创造了那个软件的公司
even the company that created the
这样的分享chart的功能
application and this functionality
在被广泛使用
of sharing charts that became pretty
事实上也是为什么
widely used actually was one of the
helm相比于其它可用工具
contributors to why
要更受欢迎的原因之一
helm became so popular compared to its alternative tools
所以现在如果你有一个集群
so now if you're if you have a cluster and you
你需要一些部署
need some kind of deployment that you
并且认为别人已经做过了
think should be available out there you
应该可以用命令行查到
can actually look it up
那么你可以执行
either using command line so you can do
“helm search ”命令
helm search with a keyword
或者你可以选择任意一种
or you can go to either helms on
公共仓库如helmhub或helm chart主页
public repository helmhub or on helm charts pages
或其他可用的仓库
or other repositories that are available
我会把所有相关的链接都放在
and i will put all the relevant links
这段视频的简介中
for this video in the description so you
你可以去查看一下
can check them out
helm chart除了有那些公共registry
now apart from those public registries for
也有私人registry
helm charts they're also private registries because
因为当公司开始创建这些chart
when companies start creating those
他们也开始在
charts they also started distributing them
在组织内部发布它们
among or internally in the organization
所以在公司内部，而不是公开
so it made perfect sense to create
共享这些chart
registries to share those charts
就很有意义
within the organization and not publicly
所以有一些工具
so there are a couple of tools out there
它们被用作helm chart的
they're used as helm charts
私有仓库
private repositories as well another
helm的另一个功能是
functionality of
模板引擎
helm is that it's a templating engine
这是什么意思呢
so what does that actually mean imagine you have
想象你有一个应用程序
an application that is made up of
由多种微服务组成
multiple microservices and you're
在你的kubernetes集群中要把它们全部部署
deploying all of them in your kubernetes cluster
这些微服务中的每一个deployment和service
and deployment and service of each of those microservices
是非常一致的
are pretty much the same with the only
区别仅在于应用程序名称和版本
difference that the application name and version
或docker镜像名称
are different or the docker image name
和docker镜像版本标签不同
and version tags are different so
没有helm时
without helm
您需要为每一个微服务
you would write separate yml files
编写单独的yaml配置文件
configuration files for each of those microservices so
那样你会有多个deployment和service的文件
you would have multiple deployment service files where
每一个都有自己的应用程序名称和版本
each one has its own application name and version
但它们唯一区别是
defined but since the only difference
yaml文件中的
between those
仅仅几行或
yaml files are just couple of lines or
几个数值
couple of values
用helm你能做的就是给所有这些微服务
using helm what you can do is that you can define
定义一个共同的蓝图
a common blueprint for all the microservices
这些值是动态的
and the values that are dynamic or the values that
将会被占位符取代
are going to change replace by
也就是定义一个模板文件
placeholders and that would be a template file
模板文件看起来像这样
so the template file would look
你会得到标准yaml文件
something like this you would have a
作为模板文件
template file which is standard yaml
但是某些地方会有Value...
but instead of values in some places you would have
这个语法意味着
the syntax which means that you're
要从外部配置中
taking a value
获取一个数值
from external configuration and that
语法中Value.后面的
external configuration if you see the
就是
syntax here dot
外部配置中值的来源
values that external configuration comes from
此时需要一个叫value.yaml的额外文件
an additional yaml file which is called values.yemo and
在这里，您可以定义所有这些
here you can define all those values
你会在模板文件中用到的值
that you're going to
例如
use in that template file so for example
这里定义了这四个值
here those four values are defined
在values.yaml文件中
in a values yaml file and
.Value是一个对象
what dot values is it's an object that
基于values.yaml文件
is being created
所提供的值
based on the values that are supplied by
被创造出来的对象
a values yaml file
同样可以通过命令行使用
and also through command line using
--set选项，所以无论哪种方式
dash dash set flag so whichever way you
你定义这些附加值
define those
它们被组合起来放在一起
additional values they're combined and put together
放到.Value对象中
in dot values object that you can then
你就可以在模板文件中使用这些值了
use in those template files to get the values out
所以现在不再有那么多yaml文件了
so now instead of having yaml files for
你只有一个微服务的文件
each microservice you just have one
你可以简单地动态替换这些值
and you can simply replace those values
这在您要对应用程序使用持续交付
dynamically and this is especially practical
持续集成时
when you're using continuous delivery
是尤其实用的
continuous integration
因为你能
for your application because what you
使用那些yaml模板文件
can do is that in your build
构建流水线
pipeline you can use those template yaml files
并在部署它们之前
and replace the values on the fly
即时替换这些值
before deploying them another use case
除了包管理器
where you can use
和模板引擎
the helm features of package manager
另一个你可以使用helm的用例是
and templating engine is when you deploy
当您要在不同kubernetes集群中
the same set of applications across
部署相同的应用程序集时
different kubernetes clusters
所以考虑这样的用例
so consider use case where you have your microservice
你有应用程序
application that you want to deploy on development
要部署在开发环境、模拟环境和生产环境集群中
staging and production clusters so
相比于在每个集群中
instead of deploying the
部署单独的yaml文件
individual yaml files separately in each cluster
你可以把它们打包成你自己的chart
you can package them up to make your own application
包含所有特定部署所需要的
chart that will have all the necessary yaml files
yaml文件
that that particular deployment needs
然后你可以用它们在不同k8s集群环境中
and then you can use them to redeploy the same
重新部署应用
application in different kubernetes cluster environments
使用一个命令即可
using one command which can also make
这使得整个部署过程更加容易
the whole deployment process
所以现在你知道了
easier so now that you know what helm
helm chart是用来干什么的
charts are used for it let's actually
让我们看看一个helm charm结构的例子
look at an example helm chart structure
这样才能更好的理解
to have a better understanding so typically
典型的helm chart是由这样的目录结构组成的
chart is made up of such a directory structure
最上层的是
so would have the top level will be the
chart名称
name of the chart
在这个目录中
and inside the directory you would have
就会有下面的
following so
Chart.yaml，它基本上是一个文件
chart.yaml is basically a file that
包含关于chart的所有元信息
contains all the meta information about the chart
可以是名字和版本，也可能是依赖关系列表等等
it could be name and version maybe list of dependencies
values.yaml我之前提到过
etc values.yaml that i mentioned before
里面放所有为模板文件
is place where all the values are cons
配置的数值
configured for the template files
这里就是默认值
and this will actually be the default
你可以稍后
values that you can
重写里面的值
override later the charts directory will have
charts目录里有chart的依赖关系
chart dependencies inside meaning that
意味着如果这个chart
if this chart
依赖于其他chart
depends on other charts then those chart
那么这些chart的依赖关系
dependencies will
将会被存储在这里，templates文件夹
be stored here and templates folder is
基本上存储模板文件
basically where the template files are stored
所以当你执行helm install命令时
so when you execute helm install command
要将这些yaml文件实际部署到k8s中
to actually deploy those yaml files into kubernetes
这里的模板文件将
the template files from here will be
被values.yaml的值填充
filled with the values from
产生有效的k8s清单
values.yaml producing valid kubernetes
然后就可以部署到kubernetes
manifest that can then be deployed intokubernetes
也可以选择让其他的文件放进这个文件夹中
and optionally you can have some other files in this
如readme或许可文件等等
folder like readme or license file
以便更好地了解
etc so to have a better understanding of how values
数值是如何注入到helm模板中的
are injected into helm templates
考虑到
consider that
values.yaml是默认配置值
in values.yaml which is a default value configuration you have
你要有三套值、镜像名称、端口和版本
following three values image name port and version
就像我提到的，定义的默认值可以
and as i mentioned the default values that are
被以不同的方式覆盖
defined here can be overridden in couple of different ways
一种方法是在执行helm install命令时
one way is that when executing helm install
提供一个可选的values.yaml文件
command you can provide an alternative
通过在命令中加入--values选项
values yaml file using values flag
例如，如果values.yaml文件
so for example if values yaml file
将有以下三个值
will have following three values which
镜像名称、端口和版本
are image name port and version
您可以定义自己的values.yaml文件
you can define your own values yaml file
命名为my-values.yaml
called myvalues.yaml and you can override
你可以覆盖这些值
one of those values or you can even add
甚至加上一些新的属性
some new attributes there
这两个会被合并到.Values对象
and those two will be merged which will result
看起来像这样
into a dot values object that will look like this
会有来自values.yaml的镜像名和端口
so would have image name and port from values.yaml
以及你自己的values文件的版本信息
and the one that you overwrote with your own
你还可以提供
values file alternatively you can also provide
额外的独立的值
additional individual values using
通过直接在命令行
set flag where you can define the values
加上set选项
directly on the command line
但是当然把所有这些值存储进文件
but of course it's more organized and
而不是仅仅在命令行中提供它们
better manageable to have
会更有组织性
files where you store all those values
更易于管理
instead of just providing them on a command line
helm的另一个特点是版本管理
another feature of helm is release management
这是根据它的配置提供的
which is provided based on its setup but
这里需要注意的是
it's important to note here
helm版本2和版本3的区别
the difference between helm versions 2 and 3.
在helm的第二版中
in version 2 of helm the helm
安装分为两个部分
installation comes in two parts
你有helm客户端和服务器
you have helm client and the server and
服务器部分被称为tiller
the server part is called
所以当你使用helm install
tiller so whenever you deploy helm chart
部署helm chart的时候，helm客户端将会
using helm install my chart helm client
把yaml文件发送给tiller
will send the yaml files to tiller
tiller在kubernetes集群中运行
that actually runs or has to run in a kubernetes cluster
tiller会执行这些请求
and tiller then will execute these requests and create
并利用这些yaml文件
components from these yaml files
在kubernetes集群内部创建组件
inside the kubernetes cluster and
这个架构
exactly this architecture
提供额外有价值的helm特性
offers additional valuable feature of
即版本管理
helm which is
所以helm客户端服务端的工作方式就是
release management so the way helm client
当你创建或更改部署时
server setup works is that whenever you
tiller将会
create or change deployment tiller will store
存储每个客户端发送的配置的副本
a copy of each configuration client send
为将来引用，因此创建一个
for future reference thus creating a history of
chart执行的历史记录，这样当你执行helm upgrade chartname的时候
chart executions so when you execute helm upgrade chartname
更改将应用到
the changes will be applied to the
现有的部署
existing deployment instead of
而不是删除它并创建一个新的
removing it and creating a new one and also
同样的，为防升级出现问题
in case the upgrade goes wrong for example
比如某些yaml文件是错误的
some yaml files were false or some
或者一些配置错了
configuration was
你可以回滚版本
wrong you can roll back that upgrade using
通过helm rollback chart name命令
helm rollback chart name command
正因为tiller每当你
and all this is possible because of that chart
从helm客户端发送请求到tiller保存了chart执行的历史记录这一切才成为可能
execution history that tiller keeps
tiller保存了chart执行的历史记录
whenever you
这一切才成为可能
send those requests from helm client to
然而，这样的设置
tiller however this setup has a big
有一个很大的隐患
caveat which is
kubernetes集群里
that tiller has too much power inside
tiller的权力太大了
the kubernetes cluster
它可以创建、更新、删除组件
it can create update delete components and it has
有太多的权限，这使得它
too much permissions and this makes it
实际上这是一个很大的安全问题
actually a big security issue and this
这也就是在helm版本3
was one of the reasons why
实际上移除了tiller的原因之一
in helm3 they actually removed the tiller part
现在它只是一个简单的helm二进制文件
and it's just a simple helm binary now and
这里有必要提一下，因为
it's important to mention here because a
很多人
lot of people
听说过tiller
have heard of tiller and when you deploy
当你部署helm版本3时
a helm version 3 you shouldn't be confused that
你不应该因没有tiller而感到困惑
tiller isn't actually there anymore
在这段视频中，我将告诉你如何
in this video i will show you how you
在kubernetes中
can persist data
使用volume保存数据
in kubernetes using volumes we will cover
我们会讲解kubernetes存储的三个组成部分
three components of kubernetes storage
persistent volume
persistent volume claim和storage class
persistent volume claim and storage class
看看每个组件是做什么的
and see what each component does and how
如何创建
it's created and
以及如何用于数据持久化
used for data persistence
考虑您的应用程序需要
consider a case where you have a mysql database pod
一个有mysql的数据库pod
which your application uses data gets added
数据在数据库中创建和更新
updated in the database maybe you create
也许你创建了一个新的数据库和一个新的用户等等
a new database with a new
但默认情况下，当你重新启动时
user etc but default when you restart the pod
所有这些改变都会消失
all those changes will be gone because
因为kubernetes没有给你
kubernetes doesn't give you
提供开箱即用的数据持久化
data persistence out of the box that's
你必须在重启前为每个
something that you have to explicitly
需要保存数据的应用程序
configure for each application that
显式配置
needs saving data between
基本上你需要一个
pod restarts so basically you need a storage
并不依赖于pod的生命周期的存储器
that doesn't depend on the pod lifecycle
所以当pod死了的时候
so it will still be there when pod dies a
一个新的会被创建
new one gets created
这样新的pod就能使用
so the new part can pick up where the
上一个pod留下的数据
previous one left off
因此，它将从存储器中读取现有数据
so it will read the existing data from that storage
从而获取最新的数据，然而你并不知道
to get up-to-date data however you don't know
新pod会在哪个节点上重新启动
on which node the new part restarts so
你的存储也必须是
your storage must also be
在所有节点上可用的，而不仅仅是特定的一个节点可用
available on all nodes not just one specific one
这样当新的pod想要读取现有数据时
so that when the new pod tries to read the existing data
最新的数据就在那里
the up-to-date data is there on
集群中的任何节点可用
any node in the cluster and also you need
你还需要一个高度抗毁的存储器
a highly available storage that will survive
即使整个集群崩溃，仍能生存
even if the whole cluster crashed
这些是你的存储器的标准或者说要求
so these are the criteria or the requirements that
要求你的存储器（如数据库存储器）
your storage for example your database storage
需要是可靠的
will need to have to be reliable another
另一个持久化存储的用例是
use case for persistent storage which is
不是为了给数据库用的，而是给目录用
not for database is a directory maybe you have an
也许你有一个应用程序
application that writes and reads
从预配置目录中读写文件
files from pre-configured directory this could be session
可能是程序的会话文件或配置文件文件等等
files for application or configuration files etc
你可以配置以上任何一种类型的存储
and you can configure any of this type of storage
通过使用叫做“Persistent Volume”（持久卷）的kubernetes组件
using kubernetes component called
将持久卷看作
persistent volume think of a persistent volume as a
集群的资源
cluster resource
就像ram或cpu一样，只是它用来存储
just like ram or cpu that is used to store
数据持久卷就像任何其他组件
data persistent volume just like any other component
使用kubernetes yaml文件创建
gets created using kubernetes yaml file
你可以指定kind是
where you can specify the kind which is
persistent volume
在spec部分，你必须定义
and in the specification section you have to define
不同的参数，比如多少
different parameters like how much
应该为卷创建多大的存储
storage should be created for the volume
但是由于持久卷只是一个抽象组件
but since persistent volume is just an abstract component
它必须从实际的物理存储器中获取存储空间
it must take the storage from the actual physical storage right
比如来自集群节点的本地硬盘
like local hard drive from the cluster nodes
或者集群外部nfs服务器
or your external nfs servers outside of the cluster
又或者像aws这样的云存储
or maybe cloud storage like aws
谷歌云存储等等
block storage or from google cloud storage etc
所以问题是这个存储后端来自
so the question is where does this storage back-end come from
本地，远程，还是云端；谁来配置它
local or remotes or on cloud who configures it
谁使它对集群可用
who makes it available to the cluster
这就是kubernetes中数据持久化的复杂之处
and that's the tricky part of data persistence
因为kubernetes并不关心你的实际存储情况
in kubernetes because kubernetes doesn't care about your
它给了你Persistent volume
actual storage it gives you persistent
作为接口接入到实际的存储空间
volume component as an interface
而你作为维护人员或者管理人员
to the actual storage that you as a maintainer
必须考虑这样的问题
or administrator have to take care of
所以你得决定你的服务或应用程序
so you have to decide what type of storage your cluster
需要哪种类型的存储
services or applications would need and
并自己创建和管理它们
create and manage them by yourself
管理的意思是
managing meaning do
备份，并确保它们不会被破坏等
backups and make sure they don't get corrupt etc
所以kubernetes中的存储可以看作是
so think of storage in kubernetes as an external
插入到您的集群中的插件，无论它是
plug-in to your cluster whether it's a local storage
运行中的集群所在的实际节点上的本地存储
on the actual nodes where the cluster is
还是远程存储
running or a remote storage
都没关系，它们都是集群的插件
doesn't matter they're all plugins to the cluster
你可以为您的集群
and you can have multiple storages
配置多个存储器
configured for your cluster
在您的集群中的一个应用程序使用本地磁盘存储
where one application in your cluster uses
另一个使用nfs服务器
local disk storage another one uses the nfs
另一个使用一些云存储
server and another one uses some cloud storage
或者一个应用程序也可以使用多种类型的存储
or one application may also use multiple of those storage types
通过创建持久卷
and by creating persistent volumes you
可以使用这些实际的物理存储
can use these actual physical storages so in the
所以在持久卷的spec部分
persistent volume specification section
您可以定义
you can define which storage
您想用哪个存储后端
back-end you want to use to create that storage
来为您的应用程序创建存储抽象或存储资源
abstraction or storage resource for your applications
这是我们使用nfs存储后端的例子
so this is an example where we use nfs
基本上是我们定义的
storage backend so basically we define
我们需要多少空间
how much storage we need
一些额外的参数
um some additional parameters so that
存储应该被读写或只读等
storage like should it be read write or read only etc
还有存储后端的参数
and the storage back end with its parameters
这是我们用的另一个例子
and this is another example where we use
用谷歌云作为存储后端
google cloud as a storage backend again
同样地要在sepc部分指定容量和访问模式等等
with the storage backend specified here and capacity and access modes here
显然，因存储后端的类型不同
now obviously depending on the storage type
一些在spec部分的属性
on the storage backend some of the attributes in the specification
会有所不同，因为他们是
will be different because they're
特定于存储类型的
specific to the storage type
这是另一个本地存储的例子
this is another example of a local
存储在节点本身上
storage which is on the node itself
有一个额外的nodeAffinity属性
which has additional node affinity
现在你不需要一次去记
attribute now you don't have to remember
去知道所有这些属性
and know all these attributes
因为你可能不需要全部这些属性
at once because you may not need all of them and also
此外我将单独做一个视频
i will make separate videos covering
讲解一些最常用的volumes
some of the most used
并逐一通过示例来解释
volumes and explain them individually with examples
在那里我会详细地解释
and demos so there i'm going to explain
哪些属性
in more detail which
应该被用于特定的volume
attributes should be used for these
以及它们是什么意思
specific volumes and what they actually mean
在kubernetes官方文档中
in the official kubernetes documentation
你可以看到完整的列表
you can actually see the complete list
关于kubernetes支持的超过25个存储后端
of more than 25 storage back-ends that kubernetes supports
这里要注意的是持久卷
note here that persistent volumes
不受命名空间束缚
are not namespaced meaning
整个集群都可以访问它们
they're accessible to the whole cluster
不像我们看到的其他部件如pod或service
and unlike other components that we saw like pods and services
它们不在任何命名空间中
they're not in any namespace they're
对所有命名空间的整个集群都可用
just available to the whole cluster to all the namespaces
很重要的一点是要区分
now it's important to differentiate here
在两类volume
between two categories of the volumes
本地和远程
local and remote each volume type in
这两个类别中的volume的每种类型
these two categories
都有自己的用例，否则它们不必存在
has its own use case otherwise they won't exist
我们稍后在本视频中
and we will see some of these use cases
会看到一些用例
later in this video
但是，本地volume类型违反了
however the local volume types violate
我在开始时提到过的
the second and third requirements of data persistence
数据库数据持久化的第二个和第三个要求
for databases that i mentioned at the beginning
即不绑定到特定的节点
which is one not being tied to
而是每个节点雨露均沾
one specific node but rather to each
因为你不知道
node equally because you don't know
新的pod会在哪里启动
where the new pod will
第二个，在集群崩溃的场景中要能够存活
start and the second surviving in cluster crash scenarios
由于这些数据库持久化需求的原因
because of these reasons for database persistence
你应该总是使用远程存储
you should almost always use remote storage
那么由谁 何时 创建这个持久卷呢
so who creates this persistent volumes and when
正如我所说的，持久卷是资源
as i said persistent volumes are resources like
如同cpu或ram
cpu or ram so they have to be already
所以当依赖于或要使用该持久卷的pod
there in the cluster
被创建时，该卷必须已经存在于集群中
when the pod that depends on it or that uses it
所以要备注一下
is created so a side note here is that
kubernetes有两个主要角色
there are two main roles in kubernetes
其中一个是创建并维护集群的管理员
there's an administrator who sets up the cluster
他还要确保
and maintains it and also makes sure the
集群有足够的资源
cluster has enough resources
这些人通常是系统管理员
these are usually system administrators
或公司中的devops工程师
or devops engineers
第二个角色是kubernetes用户
in a company and the second role is kubernetes user
在集群中部署应用程序
that deploys the applications in the
要么直接要么通过CI pipeline构建
cluster either directly or through
是开发人员和devops团队
ci pipeline these are developer devops teams
谁创建和部署应用程序
who create the applications and deploy
在这个例子中，kubernetes管理员
them so in this case the kubernetes
将是那个
administrator would be the one to
负责配置实际存储的人
configure the actual storage
确保nfs服务器存储的安好
meaning to make sure that the nfs server
并进行配置
storage is there and configured or maybe
或者也许创建和配置一个
create and configure a cloud storage
对集群是可用的云存储
that will be available for the cluster
接着，来自开发团队关于应用需要的存储类型的的信息
and second create persistent volume components
从这些存储后端
from these storage backends based on the
创建持久卷
information from developer team of what types of storage
然后开发人员
their applications would need and the developers then
会知道存储器在那里并且可以
will know that storage is there and can
被他们的应用程序使用
be used by their applications
但为了实现这一点，开发者必须
but for that developers have to
显式配置
explicitly configure the application
那些使用持久卷组件的应用程序的yaml文件
yaml file to use those persistent volume components
换句话说，应用程序必须声明那个volume
in other words application has to claim that
你可以使用
volume storage and you do that using
kubernetes的另一个组件实现这一点
another component of kubernetes
它叫做persistent volume claim(PVC)
called persistent volume claim
PVC同样是通过yaml配置的
persistent volume claims also pvcs are also created
这里有一个例子
with yaml configuration here's an example
别担心
claim again don't worry about
不必理解这里定义的每一个属性
understanding each and every attribute that is defined here
但要理解更高的层次，即它是如何运作
but on the higher level the way it works
PVC声明在其中已定义好的
is that pvc claims a volume with certain storage
具有特定存储大小或容量的卷
size or capacity which is defined in the persistent volume claim
还有一些额外的特征，比如访问类型
and some additional characteristics like access type
应该是只读还是读写等等
should be read only or read write or the type
只要持久卷
etc and whatever persistent volume
符合这个标准，或者说满足这个声明
matches this criteria or in other words satisfies this
它就会被应用程序所用
claim will be used for the application
但这还不是全部，你必须在你的pod的配置中
but that's not all you have to now use that claim
使用这个声明，就像这样
in your pods configuration like this
所以在pod的spec部分
so in the pod specification here you
会有volumes属性
have the volumes
通过PVC名称引用该PVC
attribute that references the persistent volume claim with its name
现在pod和其中的所有容器
so now the pod and all the containers inside the pod
都能访问到那个持久卷存储了
will have access to that persistent volume
为了能够一步步穿透
storage so to go through those levels of
不同层级的抽象
abstraction step by step
pods通过使用PVC作为volume来访问存储
pods access storage by using the claim as a volume
所以他们通过PVC发出请求
right so they request the volume through claim
PVC会在集群中
the claim then will go and try to find a
寻找一个满足声明要求的
volume persistent volume in the cluster
持久卷
that satisfies the claim
volume将会有一个
and the volume will have a storage the actual storage
实际的存储后端
backend that it will create
从那里创建存储资源
that storage resource from and this way
这样pod就可以
the pod will now be able
使用实际的存储后端了
to use that actual storage backend
注意，PVC必须存在于
note here that claims must exist in the
与pod相同的命名空间
same namespace as the pod
正如我之前提到的
using the claim while as i mentioned
持久卷不受限于命名空间，所以一旦
before persistent volumes are not namespaced so once the pod
pod通过PVC
finds the matching persistent volume
找到匹配的持久卷
through the persistent volume claim the
然后volume接着就会挂载到pod上
volume is then mounted
像这样，这就来到了pod级
into the pod like this here this is a pod level
然后这个volume可以被挂载到pod中的容器
and then that volume can be mounted into the container
也就是这一级
inside the pot which is this level right here
如果pod里有多个容器
and if you have multiple containers here in the pot you can
你可以决定将volume挂载到所有容器
decide to mount this volume in
或者只挂载到其中的一些
all the containers or just some of those
现在容器
so now the container
以及容器内的应用程序
and the application inside the container
可以读写那个存储器了
can read and write to that storage
并且一旦pod崩溃，新的创建取而代之
and when the pod dies a new one gets created
它将访问相同的存储空间
it will have access to the same storage
并查看之前pod或者是之前容器
and see all the changes the previous pod
所做的所有更改
or the previous containers made again
这里的属性像volumes和volumeMounts
the attributes here like volumes and volume mounts etc
在后面的演示视频中
and how they're used i will show you more specifically
我会更具体地告诉你它们是如何使用的
and explain in a later demo video
现在你可能想知道使用volume为什么有这么多抽象
now you may be wondering why so many abstractions
管理员角色要创建持久卷
for using volume where admin role has to
而用户角色要创建PVC（声明）
create persistent volume and user role creates a claim
来声明那个持久卷
on that persistent volume and that isn't used in pod
我不可以只用一个组件配置所有东西
can i just use one component and configure everything there
这其实对用户来说是有好处的
well this actually has a benefit because as a user
这意味着开发人员只需要
meaning a developer who just wants to
在集群中部署它们的应用程序
deploy their application in the cluster
而不用关心实际的存储器
you don't care about where the actual storage is
您知道您希望您的数据库具有持久性
you know you want your database to have persistence
数据是被放到
and whether the data will leave on the
gluster fs
或aws ebs或本地存储
or aws ebs or local storage
对你来说无所谓，只要数据被安全存储
doesn't matter for you as long as the data is safely stored
或者如果你需要一个目录存储文件
or if you need a directory storage for files
你不关心目录在哪里
you don't care where the directory
只要有足够的空间
actually leaves as long as it has enough space
还能正常工作就行，但你肯定不想
and works properly and you sure don't want to care about
亲自设置这些实际的存储
setting up these actual storages yourself
你只想要50g的存储空间给你的elastic
you just want 50 gigabyte storage for
或者10GB给你的应用程序
your elastic or 10 gigabyte for your application
这样你就可以利用PVC声明一个存储
that's it so you make a claim for storage using pvc
并假设集群中已经有存储资源
and assume that cluster has storage
这使得
resources already there and this makes
对开发人员来说部署应用程序更容易
deploying the applications easier for developers
因为他们不需要关心
because they don't have to take care of
部署的应用程序之外的东西
the stuff beyond deploying the applications
现在有两个volume类型
now there are two volume types that i
我认为需要单独提及
think needs to be mentioned separately
因为它们和其它的有些许不同
because they're a bit different from the
它们是ConfigMap和Secret
rest and these are config map and secret now if you have
如果你看过我的其它的kubernetes的视频
watched my other video on kubernetes components
那么你对两者都已经很熟悉了
then you are already familiar with both
它们都是
both of them are
本地volume，但不像其他那些
local volumes but unlike the rest these two
这两个不是通过pv(持久卷)和pvc产生的
aren't created via pv and pvc
而是独立的组件并且由kubernetes自己管理
but are rather own components and managed by kubernetes itself
考虑一个场景
consider a case where you need a
你需要给prometheus对应的pod一个配置文件
configuration file for your prometheus
或者一个类似于mosquito的消息代理服务
pod or maybe a message broker service like mosquito
或者考虑一下当你需要一个证书
or consider when you need a certificate file
安装在您的应用程序中，在这两种情况下
mounted inside your application in both cases
您需要一个文件可被pod使用
you need a file available to your pod
为使这些发生，你要自己创建
so how this works is that you create
configmap或secret组件
configmap or secret component
你可以把它安装到你的pod里
and you can mount that into your pod and
以及你的容器里
into your container
与你安装PVC的方式一样
the same way as you would mount
所以你会有一个ConfigMap或Secret属性
persistent volume claim so instead you would have a config map or
在我介绍本地volume类型的视频中
secret here and i will show you a demo of this
会给你们看一个关于此的演示
in a video where i cover local volume types
快速总结一下
so to quickly summarize what we've
我们到目前为止所讲的内容
covered so far
正如我们看到的，在它的核心，volume就是一个目录
as we see at its core a volume is just a directory
里面可能有一些数据
possibly with some data in it which is
能够被pod中的容器所访问
accessible to the containers
我们学习了该目录是如何被创建可用的
in a pod how that directory is made available
以及什么样的存储介质是受支持的
or what storage medium actually backed by
目录的内容是
and the contents of the directory are
由您定义的特定volume类型
defined by a specific volume type you use
为了使用一个volume，一个pod会在spec的volumes属性中指定
so to use a volume a pod specifies what volumes
什么样的volume要被提供给pod
to provide for the pod in the specification
在pod内
volumes attribute and inside the pod
你可以
then you can decide
通过containers部分的volumeMounts属性
where to mount that storage into
把存储器挂载到哪里
using volume mounts attribute inside the container section
这是容器内部的路径
and this is a path inside the container
应用程序可以利用其访问
where application can access whatever
我们挂载到容器中的存储器
storage we mounted into the container
就像我说的，如果有多个容器
and as i said if you have multiple
你可以决定
containers you can decide
哪个容器有权访问存储器
which container should get access to that storage
有趣的是，一个pod可以同时使用
interesting note for you is that a pod can actually use
不同类型的多个volume
multiple volumes of different types simultaneously
假设你有一个ElasticSearch应用程序
let's say you have an elasticsearch application
或者在您的集群中运行的pod
or pod running in your cluster that
需要通过ConfigMap挂载一个配置文件
needs a configuration file
或者需要一个证书
mounted through a config map needs a certificate
比如通过Secret安装了一个客户端证书
let's say client certificate are mounted as a secret
它还需要数据库存储
and it needs database storage let's say which is
比如用aws Elastic Block Storage
backed with aws elastic
在这种情况下你可以配置
block storage so in this case you can configure
这三个全都在你的pod或deployment里
all three inside your pod or deployment
这就是我们之前看到的pod的spec部分
so this is the pod specification that we saw before
在这里volumes属性这一级，你可以列出
and here on the volumes level you will just list
所有想要挂载到pod的volume
all the volumes that you want to mount into your pod
这里你在后台有一个PVC
so let's say you have a persistent
其在声明aws块存储的持久卷
volume claim that in the background claims persistent volume from
这里你有一个ConfigMap
aws block storage and here you have the config map
这里有个Secret
and here have a secret and here in the
这里的volumeMounts中你可以通过名称
volume mounts you can list
列出所有存储挂载点
all those uh storage mounts using the names
这就是持久化存储
right so you have the persistent storage
然后你有了ConfigMap和Secret
then you have the config map
每一个都被挂载到容器内指定的路径
and the secret and each one of them is mounted to a certain
我们现在看到
path inside the container now we saw that
为了kubernetes中持久化数据
to persist data in kubernetes admins
管理员需要为集群配置存储
need to configure storage for the cluster
创建持久卷
create persistent volumes and developers
开发人员然后就可以通过PVC声明
then can claim them
但是考虑
using pvcs but consider a cluster with
一个有数以百计的应用程序的集群
hundreds of applications
每天都要进行部署
where things get deployed daily and
这些应用程序都需要存储
storage is needed for these applications
因此开发人员需要要求管理员
so developers need to ask admins to
在部署应用程序之前
create persistent volumes they need
创建所需的持久卷
for applications before deploying them and
然后，管理员可能不得不手动请求
admins then may have to manually request
来自云或存储器供应商的存储资源
storage from cloud or storage provider
并手动创建数百个持久卷
and create hundreds of persistent volumes for
以满足所有需要存储的应用程序的需求
all the applications that need storage
那是一段乏味的时间
manually and that can be tedious time consuming
而且很快就会变得一团糟
and can get messy very quickly so to
为了让这个过程更有效率
make this process more efficient
kubernetes持久化还有第三个组件可以用
there is a third component of kubernetes persistence
称为Storage Class
called storage class storage class
它基本上就是在pvc声明它时
basically creates or provisions
动态地创造或提供持久卷
persistent volumes dynamically whenever
用这种方式在集群中
pvc claims it and this way creating or
创造或者提供volume
provisioning volumes in a cluster
可以是自动化的
may be automated storage class
Storage Class(SC)也使用yaml配置文件创建
also gets created using yaml configuration file
这是一个例子文件
so this is an example file where we have
kind属性是Storage Class
the kind storage class storage class creates
SC在后台动态创建持久卷
persistent volumes dynamically in the background so
记得我们在PV组件中
remember we define storage
定义了存储后端
backend in the persistent volume component
现在我们必须在SC中也定义它
now we have to define it in the storage class component
为此，我们需要provisioner属性
and we do that using the provisioner attribute
它是SC配置的主要部分
which is the main part of the storage class configuration
因为它告诉了kubernetes
because it tells kubernetes which
选用哪一个特定的存储平台供应商
provisioner to be used
或云服务供应商
for a specific storage platform or cloud provider
来创建持久卷
to create the persistent volume component out of it
因此每个存储后端都有自己的
so each storage backend has its own
kubernetes在内部分配的供应商
provisioner that kubernetes offers internally
它们的前缀是kubernetes.io
which are prefixed with kubernetes.io
比如这个，这些是内部供应商
like this one here and these are internal provisioners
对于其他存储类型
and for others or other storage types
他们是外部的供应商
they're external provisioners that you have to
你必须在SC中明确地查找并使用它们
then explicitly go and find and use that
除了provisioner属性
in your storage class and in addition to provisioner attribute
我们配置
we configure parameters of the storage
想请求的持久卷的参数，像这样
we want to request for our persistent volume like this
SC基本上是另一个抽象层
one's here so storage class is basically another abstraction
它抽象了底层的存储器供应商
level that abstracts the underlying storage provider
以及该存储的参数
as well as parameters for that storage
存储的特性
characteristics for the storage
比如什么磁盘类型等等
like what disk type or etc
所以它是怎么工作的，或者说你怎么在pod配置中用SC呢
so how does it work or how do you use storage class
和持久卷相同
in the pod configuration same as
它是被请求
persistent volume it is requested or
或者说被pvc声明的，所以在pvc中
claimed by pvc so in the pvc configuration
这里我们添加了额外的属性
here we add additional attribute
这就是所谓的storageclassName
that is called storage class name that
它引用要使用的SC
references the storage class to be used to create
以创建满足PVC声明要求的持久卷
a persistent volume that satisfies the claims of this
所以现在当pod通过PVC声明一个存储
pvc so now when a pod claims
PVC将会从相应的SC
storage through pvc the pvc will request
请求存储
that storage from
SC将通过provisioner对应实际的存储后端
storage class which then will provision
提供或
or create persistent volume that
创建持久卷
meets the needs of that claim using provisioner
以满足该声明使用的需要
from the actual storage backend now this
这个高水平的概览应该可以帮助你理解
should help you understand the concepts of how
在kubernetes中数据持久化的众多概念
data is persisted in kubernetes is a high level overview
在这集视频中，我们将讨论
in this video we're going to talk about
kubernetes中的StatefulSet是什么
what stateful set is in kubernetes
它的目的是什么
and what purpose it has so what is
那么什么是StatefulSet呢
stateful set
它是一种kubernetes组件
it's a kubernetes component that is used
专门用于有状态的应用程序
specifically for stateful applications
为了理解这一点，首先你
so in order to understand that first you
需要了解什么是有状态的应用程序
need to understand what a stateful application is
有状态应用程序的例子是所有数据库
examples of stateful applications are all databases
像mysql elasticsearch mongodb等
like mysql elasticsearch mongodb etc
或任何存储数据以跟踪状态的
or any application that stores data to
应用程序
keep track of its state
换句话说，这些都是
in other words these are applications
通过保存信息到存储器以跟踪状态的应用
that track state by saving that information
而无状态的应用程序
in some storage stateless applications
另一方面
on the other hand
则不保留以前交互的记录
do not keep records of previous interaction
每个请求或交互都是
and each request or interaction is handled
作为一个全新的孤立的交互来处理的
as a completely new isolated interaction
完全基于
based entirely on the information that
伴随它而来的信息
comes with it and sometimes
有时无状态应用程序会连接到
stateless applications connect to the
有状态应用程序
stateful application
并转发请求
to forward those requests so imagine a
所以想象一个简单的应用程序设置
simple setup of a node.js application
node.js被连接到mongodb数据库
that is connected to mongodb database
当一个请求进入node.js应用程序时
when a request comes in to the node.js application
它不依赖于任何先前的数据
it doesn't depend on any previous data
来处理这个传入请求
to handle this incoming request
它可以根据请求本身的有效载荷来处理
it can handle it based on the payload in the request itself
现在，一个典型的这样的请求将
now a typical such request will
另外需要根据数据库中的数据进行更新
additionally need to update some
或查询数据库中的数据
data in the database or query the data
这就是mongodb发挥作用的地方
that's where mongodb comes in so when
node.js将请求转发给mongodb
node.js forwards that request to mongodb
mongodb将基于以前的状态更新数据
mongodb will update the data based on its previous state
或者从它的存储中查询数据
or query the data from its storage so
所以对于每个请求，它都需要处理数据
for each request it needs to handle data
显然总是取决于
and obviously always depends on the
最新的数据或状态从而使结果可用
most up-to-date data or state to be available
而nodejs只是一个传递器
while nodejs is just a pass-through for
传递数据更新或查询的请求
data updates or queries
它只处理代码
and it just processes code
因为有状态和无状态应用程序
now because of this difference between
两者之间的差异
stateful and stateless applications
它们都使用kubernetes中的不同组件
they're both deployed different ways using
以不同的方式部署
different components in kubernetes
无状态应用程序
stateless applications are deployed
使用deployment组件
using deployment component
deployment是pod的抽象
deployment is an abstraction of pods
并允许你复制应用程序
and allows you to replicate that application
即可以在集群中
meaning run two five ten identical parts of the same
运行两个、五个、十个相同的无状态应用程序
stateless application in the cluster so
无状态应用程序使用deployment
while stateless applications are deployed using
而有状态应用程序在k8s中
deployment stateful applications in kubernetes
是使用StatefulSet组件部署的
are deployed using stateful set components
就像deployment
and just like deployment statefulset
StatefulSet一样使得复制成为可能
makes it possible to replicate
或者也能运行多个副本
the stateful app parts or to run multiple
换句话说，它们都是管理副本
replicas of it in other words they both manage
基于同一个指定规格容器的副本
parts that are based on an identical container
你也可以以同样的方式
specification and you can also configure
为它们二者都配置存储
storage with both of them equally
既然它们都是
in the same way so if both
管理pod的副本
manage the replication of pods and also configuration of
并且以相同的方式保存数据
data persistence in the same way the question
那么问题来了，这是很多人问的，也是很多人常常困惑的
is what a lot of people ask and are also often confused about
两者有什么区别
what is the difference between those two
为什么我们对于每种类型的应用程序
components why we use different ones
使用不同的组件，所以下一节
for each type of application so in the next section
我们来谈谈不同之处
we're gonna talk about the differences
现在复制有状态的应用程序
now replicating stateful application
是更困难的，因为有几个
is more difficult and has a couple of requirements
无状态应用程序所没有的需求
that stateless applications do not have
我们首先来看看
so let's look at this
一个mysql数据库的例子
first with the example of a mysql database
假设您有一个mysql数据库的pod
let's say you have one mysql database part
处理来自java应用程序的请求
that handles requests from a java application
该应用程序是由deployment组件部署的
which is deployed using a deployment component
假设你扩展了java应用到三个pod
and let's say you scale the java application to three parts
这样他们就能并行处理更多的客户请求
so they can handle more client requests
同时，你想要扩展mysql应用程序
in parallel you want to scale mysql app
因此它可以处理更多的java请求
so it can handle more java requests as
扩展java应用程序的方式是很直接的
well scaling your java application
java应用程序副本
here is pretty straightforward java applications replica parts
会是相同的和可互换的
will be identical and interchangeable so
所以你可以很容易地
you can scale it
利用deployment进行扩展
using a deployment pretty easily
deployment将按任意顺序创建pod
deployment will create the pods in any
按任意随机的顺序
order in any random order
最后会得到随机的哈希值作为pod名称
they will get random hashes at the end of the pod name
他们将获得一个service来做负载均衡
they will get one service that load
来让合适副本处理对应请求
balances to any one of the replica pods
同样地，当你删除它们时
for any request and also when you delete
它们会在同一时间被按随机顺序删除
them they get deleted in a random order or at the same time
或者当你缩小它们规模的时候
right or when you scale them down
例如，从三个副本减到两个
from three to two replicas for example one
某个随机的副本pod会被选择删除
random replica part gets chosen to be deleted
所以并不复杂，但另一方面
so no complications there on the other hand
mysql副本无法在同一时刻
mysql part replicas cannot be created
被按任意次序创建或删除
and deleted at the same time
它们不可以被随机处理
in any order and they can't be randomly addressed
原因是那些副本
and the reason for that is because the replica
事实上，并不完全相同
parts are not identical in fact
它们从共同的pod构建
they each have their own additional identity
但在共同的蓝图之上
on top of the common blueprint of the pod
又有各自额外的身份标识
that they get created from and giving each
并且赋予了每个pod一个自己的私人标识
part its own required individual identity
这就是StatefulSet与deployment的不同之处
is actually what stateful set does different from
对于StatefulSet来说，其中的每一个pod
deployment it maintains a sticky
都维持着一个紧紧相连的标识
identity for each of its pots
就像我说的，这些pod被创建时
and as i said these pods are created
来自同一规范
from the same specification
但它们是不可互换的
but they're not interchangeable each has
每一个都有一个持久的标识符
a persistent identifier
它在任何重调度时都会保持着
that it maintains across any rescheduling
也就是说当一个pod死了，并被新的取代时
so meaning when pod dies and it gets replaced
它仍会保持这个身份表示
by a new part it keeps that identity so
你现在可能要问的问题是
the question you may be asking now is
为什么这些pod需要它们自己的身份标识？
why do these parts need their own identities why they can't be
为什么它们不能就像deployment一样可互换？
interchangeable just like with deployment
所以这是为什么呢
so why is that and this is a concept
你需要理解的一个关于扩展数据库应用程序的概念是
that you need to understand about
一般
scaling database applications in general
当你启动单个mysql pod时
when you start with a single mysql pod
它将同时用于两者读写数据
it will be used for both
但当你再添加一个时
reading and writing data but when you add a second one
它不能采取同样的方式，因为如果
it cannot act the same way because if
你允许两个mysql的独立实例
you allow two independent instances of mysql to
均能改变相同的数据
change the same data
将以数据不一致告终
you will end up with data inconsistency
所以要有一种机制决定
so instead there is a mechanism that decides
只有一个pod被允许写或更改数据
that only one part is allowed to write or change the data
同时多个mysql实例共享
which is shared reading at the same time by multiple
共享对同一堆数据的读权限
parts mysql instances from the same data
完全没问题
is completely fine and the pod that is allowed to
那个被允许更新数据的pod被称为master
update the data is called the master the others
其它的被称为slave
are called slaves so this is the first
所以这是第一个区分这些pod的点
thing that differentiates these parts from each other
所以不是所有pod都是一样的
so not all pods are same identical but
有一个master pod
there is a master pod
剩下的是slave pod
and they're the slave parts right and
从存储的角度看
there's also difference between those
slave pod之间也有区别，这是第二个点
slave parts in terms of storage which is the next point
所以问题是这些pod
so the thing is that these pods do not
并不能访问相同的物理存储器
have access to the same
即使他们使用相同的数据
physical storage even though they use the same data
他们也没在用相同的物理存储器来存储数据
they're not using the same physical storage of the data
他们都有自己的存储副本
they each have their own replicas of the storage
每个都可以访问自身
that each one of them can access for itself
这意味着每个pod的副本任何时候
and this means that each pod replica at any time
必须与另一个pod副本都有相同的数据
must have the same data as the other
为了达到这个目的，他们
ones and in order to achieve that they
必须持续同步他们的数据
have to continuously synchronize their data
既然master是唯一被允许改变数据的
and since master is the only one allowed to change data
而slave们需要关心它们自己的数据存储
and the slaves need to take care of their own data storage
显然slave们一定知道每一个更改
obviously the slaves must know about each
这样就可以自己更新数据到最新状态
such change so they can update their own data storage
为下一次查询请求做准备
to be up to date for the next query requests
这样的集群数据库需要一个机制
and there's a mechanism in such clustered database setup
允许连续数据同步
that allows for continuous data synchronization
master更改数据并且所有slave更新自己的数据存储
master changes data and all slaves update their own data
保持同步并确保每个pod都有相同的状态
storage to keep in sync and to make sure that each pod
现在假设
has the same state now let's say you
你有mysql的一个master和两个slave pod
have one master and two slave
一个新的pod副本加入现有设置
parts of mysql now what happens when a new pod
会发生什么
replica joins the existing setup because now
因为新的pod需要创造自己的存储
that new pod also needs to create its own
然后数据同步
storage and then take care of synchronizing it
所以它首先要从之前的pod
what happens is that it first clones the
克隆数据
data from the previous part not just
不是从集群中的任意一个pod
any pod in the in the setup but always
而是从上一个pod
from the previous part
一旦它克隆了最新的数据
and once it has the up-to-date data cloned
它开始连续同步
it starts continuous synchronization as
监听master pod所做的任何修改
well to listen for any
这也意味着
updates by masterpod and this also means
我想指出这一点
and i want to point this out since it's
很有趣的一点
pretty interesting point
这意味着你的有状态应用程序
it means that you can actually have a
可以得到的是一个临时存储
temporary storage for a stateful application
而不是保存的数据
and not persist the data at all since
因为pod之间在复制数据
the data gets replicated between the pods
理论上有可能
so theoretically it is possible to just
只依赖数据复制维持集群
rely on data replication
但这也意味着
between the pots but this will also mean that
当所有pod死了
the whole data will be lost when
所有数据都会丢失
all the parts die so for example if
比如若StatefulSet被删除或
stateful set gets deleted or
集群或所有节点崩溃
the cluster crashes or all the nodes
而pod副本都在那里运行
where these pod replicas are running crash
或者所有pod都在同一时间死亡
and every pod dies at the same time the
数据就会消失
data will be gone
因此，使用数据持久化
and therefore it's still a best practice
仍然是有状态应用程序的最佳实践
to use data persistence
丢失数据在大部分数据库用例上
for stateful applications if losing the data will be
都是无法接受的
unacceptable which is the case in most database applications
而有持久化存储，数据将幸存
and with persistent storage data will survive
即使StatefulSet的所有pod都死了
even if all the parts of the stateful set die
或者即使你删除了整个StatefulSet组件
or even if you delete the complete
所有pod也会紧跟着被消灭
stateful set component and all the parts get
而持久化的存储和数据
wiped out as well the persistent
将得到保留
storage and the data will still remain because
因为持久卷的生命周期
persistent volume uh life cycle isn't connected
与其它组件如deployement或StatefulSet
or isn't tied to a life cycle of
的生命周期无关
other components like deployment or
实现这个的方法是
stateful set and the way to do this is
为您的StatefulSet配置持久卷
configuring persistent volumes for your stateful set
因为每个pod都有自己的数据存储
and since each pod has its own data storage
意味着它们自己的持久卷
meaning it's their own persistent volume
由它自己支持的物理存储器做备份
that is then backed up by its own physical storage
其中包括同步数据或
which includes the synchronized data or
复制数据库数据
the replicated database data
还有pod的状态
but also the state of the pod
每个pod都有自己的状态
so each pod has its own state which has
关于它是master还是slave
information about whether it's a masterpod or a slave
或其他各自的身份标识
or other individual characteristics and
所有这些都被存储到
all of this gets stored
pod自己的存储器中
in the pot's own storage and that means
当一个pod死了，被替换了
when a pot dies and gets replaced
其持久化的标识将确保
the persistent pot identifiers make sure that the
存储卷被替代pod重新挂载
storage volume gets reattached
就像我说的，因为
to the replacement pod as i said because that storage
存储除了有复制的数据外，还包含了pod的状态
has the state of the pod in addition to
你可以再一次克隆数据
that replicated data i mean you can clone the data
不会有问题
again that will be no problem but it shouldn't lose
但是不应该丢失它的状态或者说是身份标识
its state or identity state so to say
为了能够重新挂载
and for this reattachment to work it's
使用远程存储很重要
important to use a remote storage
因为如果pod被重新调度
because if the pod gets rescheduled from
从一个节点调度到另一个节点
one node to another node
之前的存储必须
the previous storage must be available
在另一个节点上也是可用的
on the other node as well
你不能用本地卷来做这个
and you cannot do that using local
因为它们通常是
volume storage because they are usually
绑定到特定的节点上的
tied to a specific node
deployment和StatefulSet间的最后一个区别
and the last difference between deployment and
是我之前提到的
stateful set is something that i mentioned
即pod标识
before is the pod identifier meaning that
每个pod都有自己的标识
every pod has its own identifier so
不像deployment那样最后得到随机散列
unlike deployment where pods get random hashes at the end
StatefulSet的pod会有固定次序的名字
stateful set pods get fixed ordered names which is made up
由StatefulSet的名字以及
of the stateful set name
是从0开始的序数组成
and ordinal it starts from zero and each
每个额外的pod将得到下一个数字
additional part will get
如果你创建一个StatefulSet名为mysql
the next numeral so if you create a stateful set called mysql
里面有三个副本，名字分别
with three replicas you'll have parts with names
等于0 1和2
must equal zero one and two the first one is
按启动顺序，第一个是master，然后是slave
the master and then come the slaves in
一个重要的注意事项是
the order of startup an important note
StatefulSet将不会
here is that the stateful set
在副本中创建下一个pod
will not create the next part in the replica
如果前一个还没准备好并运行的话
if the previous one isn't already up
如果第一个pod创建失败了
and running if first pod creation for example failed
或者在待机状态，下一个也不会被创建
or if it was pending the next one won't
而只是会等待
get created at all it would just wait
同样的，删除也是按顺序的
and the same order is held deletion
但是顺序相反
but in reversed order so for example if
如果您删除了StatefulSet
you deleted the stateful
或者把它规模从3缩小到1
set or if you scaled it down to one for example from
删除将从最后一个pod开始
three the deletion will start from the
所以第一个将被删除的是mysql-2
last part so my sql two will get deleted first
直到该pod成功删除
it will wait until that part is successfully deleted
才会删除mysql-1
and then it will delete my sql one
然后它会删除mysql-0
and then it will delete must equal zero and again
所有这些机制都是
all these mechanisms are in place in
为了保护数据
order to protect the data
还有有状态应用程序依赖的状态
and the state that the stateful application depends on
除了这个固定的可预测的名字
in addition to this fixed predictable names
StatefulSet中的每个pod都有来自一个service的
each part in a stateful set gets its own
自己的dns端点，所以对于有状态应用程序
dns endpoint from a service so there's a service name
也会有serviceName属性，就像deployment一样
for the stateful application just like for deployment for example
从而定位到任何副本的pod
that will address any replica pod
除此之外在StatefulSet中的每个pod
and plus in addition to that there is individual dns name
还有个人dns名称，这是deployment中的pod所没有的
for each pod which deployment pods do not have
个人dns名称由pod的名字
the individual dns names are made up of pod name
以及管理service的名称组成
and the manage or the governing service
后者基本上是
name which is basically
您在StatefulSet内部定义的service的名称
a service name that you define inside the stateful set
这两个特征意味着有
so these two characteristics meaning having
可预测的或固定的名字
a predictable or fixed name as well as
它是固定的个人dns名称
it's fixed individual dns name means that
意味着当pod重新启动时，ip地址将改变
when pod restarts the ip address will change
但名字和端点保持不变
but the name and end point will stay the same
所以我才说pod有着紧密相连的身份标识
that's why i said pods get sticky
即使在重启
identities so it gets
也会与该标识绑定
stuck to it even between the restarts
绑定标识保证了每个副本的pod
and the sticky identity makes sure that each replica pod
能够保持它的状态和它的作用
can retain its state and its role
即使它死了，被重新创建了
even when it dies and gets recreated and
最后我想提一个重要的知识点
finally i want to mention an important
如您所见，利用持久化存储复制有状态应用程序
point here as you see replicating stateful apps
如数据库时
like databases with its persistent storage
需要一个复杂的机制
requires a complex mechanism and
kubernetes会帮助你并支持你
kubernetes helps you
设置所有东西
and supports you to set this whole thing
但你还是需要一个人做很多
up but you still need to do a lot by yourself where kubernetes
k8s并没有实质的帮助
doesn't actually help you or doesn't
或者说没有为您提供现成的解决方案
provide you out-of-the-box solutions
例如，你需要配置
for example you need to configure the
克隆和数据同步
cloning and data synchronization
在StatefulSet中，也要
inside the stateful set and also make
让远程存储可用
the remote storage available
还要管理和备份
as well as take care of managing and backing it up
所有这些你都得自己做
all of these you have to do yourself and the reason
因为有状态的应用程序不是
is that stateful applications are not a
完美的适合容器化的环境
perfect candidate for containerized environments
事实上，docker kubernetes和更一般的容器化工具
in fact docker kubernetes and generally containerization
完美适配无状态应用程序
is perfectly fitting for stateless applications
没有任何状态和数据依赖
that do not have any state and data dependency
并且只处理代码，所以
and only process code so scaling and
在容器中缩放或复制它们是非常容易的
replicating them in containers is super easy
在这个视频中我会给你一个完整的
in this video i will give you a complete
kubernetes service的概述
overview of kubernetes services
首先，我将简要解释什么是kubernetes中的Service组件
first i'll explain shortly what service component is in kubernetes
等我们需要的时候，我们就
and when we need it and then we'll go
通过不同的service类型
through the different service types
ClusterIP类型，Headless类型，NodePort类型
cluster ip service headless service node port
以及LoadBalancer（负载均衡器）类型
and load balancer services i will
我会解释它们之间的区别
explain the differences between them
并说明什么时候用哪一个
and when to use which one so by the end
在视频最后你会有一个关于k8s的service的
of the video you will have a great
很全面的理解
understanding of kubernetes services
并且能够在实践中使用它们
and will be able to use them in practice
让我们开始吧
so let's get started
kubernetes中的service是什么
so what is the service in kubernetes and
我们为什么需要它
why do we need it
在kubernetes集群中，每个pod都有自己的
in a kubernetes cluster each pod gets its own
内部ip地址，但是在k8s中的pod都是暂态的
internal ip address but the pods in kubernetes
意味着它们来来去去会很频繁
are ephemeral meaning that they come and go very frequently
当pod重新启动或
and when the pod restarts or when old
一个老的pod死了，被新的pod取代
one dies and the new one gets
它会获得一个新的ip
started in its place it gets a new ip address
所以直接使用pod的ip地址是没有意义的
so it doesn't make sense to use pod ip addresses
因为那样你不得不
directly because then you would have to
每次pod被重建时都要调整
adjust that every time the pod gets recreated with the service
然而你有一个解决方案
however you have a solution
利用一个稳定的或静态的ip地址
of a stable or static ip address that stays
即使是在pod死掉的时候也能保持住
even when the pod dies so basically in
所以基本上在每个pod的前部
front of each pod
我们会设置一个service，它表示
we set a service which represents a persistent
持久的稳定的可访问该pod的ip地址
stable ip address access that pod
service还提供负载均衡
a service also provides load balancing
因为当你有pod的副本时
because when you have pod replicas
例如，你的微服务应用程序有三个副本
for example three replicas of your microservice application
或者mysql应用程序有三个副本
or three replicas of mysql application
service基本上会得到每一个
the service will basically get each request
指向mysql或你的微服务应用程序的请求
targeted to that mysql or your microservice application
然后转发到其中一个pod
and then forward it to one of those pods
这样客户端就可以调用一个稳定的ip地址
so clients can call a single stable ip
而不是调用单独的pod
address instead of calling each pod individually
因此，service起到松散耦合的作用
so services are a good abstraction for loose coupling
是集群内的通信的很好的抽象
for communication within the cluster so
不仅用于集群内的组件或pod通信
within the cluster components or pods inside the cluster but also
还可用于外部服务
from external services like if you have
如你有进入集群的浏览器请求
browser requests coming to the cluster
或者和外部数据库通信
or if you're talking to an external database for example
k8s中有几种类型的service
there are several types of services in kubernetes
第一个也是最常见的一个
the first and the most common one that you probably
可能是你将在大部分时间内使用的类型，ClusterIP
will use most of the time is the cluster ip type
这是service的默认类型
this is a default type of a service
即当你创建一个service
meaning when you create
但不指定类型时
a service and not specify a type
它将自动以ClusterIP为类型
it will automatically take cluster ip as
让我们看看
a type so let's see how
ClusterIP是如何工作的，以及在k8s的哪里使用它
cluster ip works and where it's used
想象我们在集群中
in kubernetes setup imagine we have
部署了一个微服务应用程序
a micro service application deployed in the cluster
所以我们有包含微服务的容器的pod
so we have a pod with microservice container
容器在其中运行
running inside that pod and beside that
除了微服务容器
microservice container we have
我们还有一个辅助容器，用来收集
a sidecar container that collects the
微服务的日志，然后发送到某个目标数据库
logs of the microservice and then sends that to
这两个容器
some destination database so these two
在pod中运行
containers are running in the pod
比如说你的微服务容器
and let's say your micro service
正在pod的端口3000运行
container is running at pod
而日志容器
3000 and your logging container
在端口9000上运行
let's say is running on port 9000
这意味着这两个端口将被打开
this means that those two ports will be now open
并且可以在pod内访问
and accessible inside the pod and pod
pod也会从被分配给节点的一个范围内
will also get an ip address
得到一个ip地址
from a range that is assigned to a node
它的工作方式是
so the way it works is that if you have
如果您的kubernetes集群中有三个worker节点
for example three worker nodes in your kubernetes cluster
每个工作节点将获得一个集群内部的
each worker node will get a range of ip addresses
ip地址的范围
which are internal in the cluster so for
比如node 1将获得ip地址范围是10.2.1.x
example the pod one will get ip addresses from a range of 10.2.1
第二个worker节点将获得这个ip范围
onwards the second worker node will get this ip range
第三个worker节点将得到这个
and the third worker node will get this
假设这个pod在node 2启动，因此它得到一个像这样的ip地址
one so let's say this pod starts on node2 so it get an ip address
如果你想查看集群中的pod的ip地址
that looks like this if you want to see the ip addresses
你可以实际上
of your pods in the cluster you can actually
使用kubectl get pod -o wide命令
check them using cube ctl get pod output
你会得到一些
wide command where you will get some
关于pod的额外信息
extra information about the pods
包括它的ip地址
including its ip address and here you
会看到它被分配的ip地址
will see the ip address that it got assigned
正如我提到的，这些都来自ip地址的一个范围
and as i mentioned these are from the ip address range
即集群中的每个worker节点会获得的范围
that each worker node in the cluster
这是从第一个worker节点的
will get so this is from the first worker node
这些是第二个worker节点的
and these are from the second worker node
现在我们可以利用这个ip地址和端口号
so now we can access those containers
访问这些pod内的容器了
inside the pod at this ip address
如果我们设置副本数为2
at these ports if we set the replica count to 2
我们将有另一个pod
we're going to have another pod which is
和第一个pod相同
identical to the first one
会和它打开相同的端口
which will open the same ports and it
但是得到不同的ip地址
will get a different ip address
假设它从worker节点1启动
let's say if it starts on worker node 1
你会得到一个看起来像这样的ip地址
you will get an ip address that looks something like this
现在我们假设这个微服务
now let's say this microservice is
可通过浏览器访问
accessible through a browser
我们已经配置好了Ingress
so we have ingress configured and
想发送到微服务的来自浏览器的请求
the requests coming in from the browser to the micro service
将由Ingress处理
will be handled by ingress how does this
传入请求是如何从Ingress
incoming request
峰回路转 转发到pod的呢
get forwarded from ingress all the way to the pod
这是通过ClusterIP类型的service实现的
and that happens through a service a cluster ip
或者所谓的k8s中的内部service
or so-called internal service a service in kubernetes
和pod一样是组件，但并不是一个线程
is a component just like a pod but it's not a process
它只是一个抽象层
it's just an abstraction layer that
表示一个ip地址
basically represents an ip address
service将会得到一个可被访问的ip地址
so service will get an ip address that it is accessible at
service也将在某些端口可被访问
and service will also be accessible at a certain port
假设我们将这个端口定义为3200
let's say we define that port to be 3200
所以ingress会和service对话
so ingress will talk to the service or
经由这个端口移交请求
hand over the request
到这个ip地址
to the service at this ip address at this
这就是
port so this is how service is
集群内的service是如何可访问的
accessible within the cluster so the way
工作方式就是
it works is that
我们定义了Ingress规则
we define ingress rules that forward the request
基于请求地址转发请求
based on the request address
到特定的service
to certain services and we define the service by its
我们通过名称和dns解析来定义service
name and the dns resolution
后者将该service名映射到一个ip地址
then maps that service name to an ip
service于是得到了分配
address that the service
这就是Ingress怎么知道
actually got assigned so this is how ingress
如何与service交谈的
knows how to talk to the service so once
一旦请求被移交给了这个地址的service
the request gets handed over to the service at this address
然后service就会知道要转发该请求
then service will know to forward that
到注册为service端点的众多pod之一
request to one of those parts that are registered as the service
现在有两个问题，service是怎么知道
endpoints now here are two questions how does service know
它管理哪些pod或
which pods it is managing or which parts
将请求转发给哪些pod
to forward the request to
第二个问题是service怎么知道
and the second one is how does service know which port
对于那个特定的pod，通过哪个端口将请求转发给它
to forward that request to on that specific pod
第一个是由selector(选择器)定义的
the first one is defined by selectors
一个service会使用selector属性
a service identifies its member pods or its
标识其成员pod或其端点pod
endpoint parts using selector attribute
所以在我们创建的yaml文件中的spec部分
so in the service specification in the yaml file
我们会
from which we create the service we
指定selector属性
specify the selector attribute
那里可以定义键值对列表
that has a key value pairs defined as a list
这些键值对基本上是标签（也就是label）
now these key value pairs are basically labels
标识了应该与选择器匹配的pod
that pods should have to match that selector
所以在pod配置文件中
so in the pod configuration file we
我们指定pod在metadata中的labels部分
assign the parts certain labels in the metadata section
这些标签可以是任意名称
and these labels can be arbitrary name
所以我们可以写my-app
so we can say
或者给它其它标签
my app for example and give it some other labels
这基本上是我们自己定义的
this is basically something that we
我们可以给它起任何想起的名字
define ourselves we can give it any name that we want
这些只是键值对
these are just key value pairs that
用于识别一组pod
identify a set of
在service的yaml文件中，我们
pots and in the service yaml file then we
定义了选择器
define a selector
来匹配任何有这些标签的pod
to match any part that has all of these labels
这意味着如果我们有一个deployment组件
this means if we have a deployment
创建了三个pod副本
component that creates three replicas of parts
标签是my-app
with label called app my app
类型为microservice
and type microservice for example
在service的selector属性中
and in the service selector attribute we
定义这两个标签
define those two labels
然后service就会匹配所有这三个pod的副本
then service will match all of those three
它会注册所有这三个pod副本
pod replicas and it will register all
作为它的端点
three parts as its endpoints
就像我说的，它应该匹配所有
and as i said it should match all the
而不止一个
selectors not just one
这就是service如何知道哪个pod属于它
so this is how service will know which parts
即向哪里转发请求
belong to it meaning where to forward that
第二个问题是
request to the second question was if a pod has
如果一个pod有多个不同的端口开放
multiple ports open where two different
不同的应用程序在pod内部不同端口监听
applications are listening inside the pod
service如何知道到哪个端口
how does service know which port to
转发请求
forward the request to
这在targetPort属性中定义
and this is defined in the target port attribute
这个targetPort属性
so this target port attribute so let's say target port
在我们的例子中是3000
in our example is three thousand what
这意味着当我们创建service时
this means is that when we create the service
它会找到所有与selector相匹配的pod
it will find all the parts that match this selector
这些pod会变成service的端点
so these pods will become endpoints of the service
当service收到请求时
and when the service gets a request it
会随机选择其中一个pod副本
will pick one of those
因为它是负载均衡器
pod replicas randomly because it's a load balancer
它将发送接收到的请求
and it will send the request it received
到那个特定的pod
to that specific pod on a port
通过由targetPort属性定义的端口号
defined by target port attribute
在这种情况下，是3000
in this case 3000 also note that
还需要说明的是，当你创建一个service时
when you create a service kubernetes creates an
k8s将会创建一个端点对象，和service本身具有相同名称
endpoints object that has the same name as
kubernetes将会使用这个端点对象
the service itself and kubernetes will use this
来追踪
endpoints object to keep track of which
哪个pod是service的成员
parts are members of the service or as i
或者说哪些pod是service的端点
said which parts are the end points
这是动态的
of the service and since this is dynamic
因为每当你创建一个新的pod副本
because whenever you create a new pod
或pod死亡时
replica or a pod dies
端点会被更新
the end points get updated so this
这个对象会跟踪到
object will basically track that
注意这里的port属性是任意的
and note here that the service port
您可以自己定义
itself is arbitrary so you can define it yourself
而targetPort不是任意的
whereas the target port is not arbitrary
它必须匹配
it has to match
容器内应用程序正在监听的端口
the port where container the application container inside the pod
假设我们的微服务应用程序
is listening at now let's say our microservice application
通过Ingress以及内部ClusterIP类型service
got its requests from the browser through ingress and
从浏览器获得请求
internal cluster ip service and now it
现在它需要与数据库通信
needs to communicate with the database
来处理请求
to handle that request for example and
在我们的例子中，我们假设
in our example let's assume that the
微服务应用程序使用mongodb数据库
microservice application uses mongodb database
集群中我们有mongodb的两个副本
so we have two replicas of mongodb in the cluster
它们也是对应service的端点
which also have their own service endpoint
mongodb对应service也是ClusterIp类型
so mongodb service is also of cluster ip
它有自己的ip地址，所以现在pod内的微服务应用程序
and it has its own ip address so now the microservice application
可以与mongodb数据库对话
inside the pod can talk to the mongodb database
也能使用service端点
also using the service endpoint so the
所以来自左面两个pod之一的获得请求的哪个pod
request will come from one of the parts
将会提交请求
that gets the request
到mongodb服务
from the service to the mongodb service
在service开放的ip地址和端口上
at this ip address and the port that
接着Service将再一次
service has open and then service will again
选择一个pod副本
select one of those pod replicas and
转发请求到指定pod
forward that request to the selected pod at
经由targetPort定义的端口号
the port the target port defined here
这是pod内部mongodb应用监听的端口
and this is the port where mongodb application inside the pod
让我们假设一下
is listening at now let's assume that
在mongodb pod里面有另一个容器正在运行
inside that mongodb pod there is another
在给prometehus监控程序选择监控指标
container running that selects the monitoring metrics for prometheus for example
并将是mongodb输出结果的地方(exporter)
and that will be a mongodb exporter and
这个容器正在9216端口运行
that container let's say is running at port 9216
这就是该应用程序可被访问的地方
and this is where the application is accessible at
在集群里我们有一个prometheus应用程序
and in the cluster we have a prometheus application
将下载监控指标
that scrapes the metrics endpoint from
从这个mongodb exporter容器
this mongodb exporter container from
从这个端点
this endpoint now that means that service
意味着service必须处理两个不同的端点请求
has to handle two different endpoint requests
同样意味着它有两个自己的端口开放
which also means that service has two of its own
来处理两个不同的请求
ports open for handling these two different
一个是从客户端来的请求
requests one from the clients that want
想要与mongodb数据库对话
to talk to the mongodb database
还有一个来自prometheus
and one from the clients like prometheus
想要与mongodb exporter程序对话
that want to talk to the mongodb
这是一个
exporter application and this is an
多端口service的示例
example of a multi-port service
注意，当你在一个service中
and note here that when you have multiple
定义了多个端口
ports defined in a service you have to name
你必须命名这些端口，如果只有一个端口的话
those ports if it's just one port then you can
就让它这样匿名
leave it so to say anonymous you don't
不必使用name属性
have to use the name attribute
此时它是可选的，但如果你有定义多个端口
it's optional but if you have multiple
就必须给它们中的每一个命名
ports defined then you have to name
这是ClusterIP的例子
each one of those so these were examples of cluster
现在让我们看另一个
ip service type now let's see another
service的类型
service type which is called
其被称为headless service
headless service so let's see what
让我们看看什么是headless service
headless service type is
正如我们看到的，到达service的每个请求都被转发到
as we saw each request to the service is forwarded to
注册为service端点的
one of the pod replicas that are
pod副本中的一个
registered as service endpoints
但想象一下如果客户想要选择性地
but imagine if a client wants to
与其中一个pod直接通信
communicate with one of the parts
或者如果
directly and selectively or what if the
端点pod彼此需要直接通信
endpoint parts need to communicate with each other
而不经过service
directly without going through the
显然在这种情况下，随机选择其中一个pod
service obviously in this case it wouldn't make sense to
进行service端点地对话是没有意义地
talk to the service endpoint which will randomly select
因为我们想要与特定的pod沟通
one of the parts because we want the communication
那还有一种情况
with specific parts now what would be such a use case
有必要用headless的情况是
a use case where this is necessary is
当我们在kubernetes中部署有状态应用时
when we're deploying stateful applications in kubernetes
有状态应用程序，如mysql数据库,mongobd,elasticsearch等等
stateful applications like databases mysql mongodb
对于这样的应用程序，pod副本是不尽相同的
elasticsearch and so on in such applications the pod replicas
每一个都有自己的状态
aren't identical but rather each one has its individual
和特征，例如
state and characteristic for example if
如果我们正在部署一个mysql应用程序
we're deploying a mysql application
你会有一个mysql的master实例
you would have a master instance of
和worker实例
mysql and worker instances of mysql application
master是唯一被允许
and master is the only pod allowed to
写数据库的
write to the database and the worker
worker pods必须连接到master
pods must connect to the master
在master pod对数据库进行更改后
to synchronize their data after masterpod has
同步他们的数据
made changes to the database so they get
从而获得最新的数据
the up-to-date data as well
当新的worker开始工作时，必须
and when new worker pod starts it must
直接与最近建立的worker节点联系
connect directly to the most
从那里克隆数据
recent worker node to clone the data from
同时还要更新数据状态
and also get up to date with the data state
这是最常见的
so that's the most common use case where you need
你需要直接与pod通信的用例
direct communication with individual pods
在这种情况下，客户端要连接到所有pod
for such case for a client to connect to all pods
它需要找到
individually it needs to figure out the
每个pod的ip地址
ip address of each individual pod
实现这一目标的一个方法是
one option to achieve this would be to
对kubernetes api服务器调用api
make an api call to kubernetes api
它将返回pod及其ip地址的列表
server and it will return the list of pods
但这样会
and their ip addresses but this will make your
让你的应用程序与kubernetes特定的api的耦合程度太高
application too tied to the kubernetes specific api
而且这也是低效的
and also this will be inefficient
因为每次你想
because you will have to get
连接到其中一个pod
the whole list of parts and their ip
都必须得到完整的pod清单和ip地址
addresses every time you want to connect to one of the pods but
作为另一种解决方案，kubernetes允许客户端
as an alternative solution kubernetes allows
通过dns解析查找pod的ip地址
clients to discover pod ip addresses
通常它的工作原理是
through dns lookups and usually the way
当客户端执行一个service的
it works is that when a client performs
dns解析时
a dns lookup for a service the dns
dns服务器返回属于service的单个ip地址
server returns a single ip address which belongs to the service
这将是ClusterIP类型service的地址
and this will be the services cluster ip address
我们之前看到过
which we saw previously however if you tell kubernetes
但是如果你通过在创建service时
that you don't need a cluster ip address of the service
设置ClusterIP字段为none
by setting the cluster ip field to none
来告诉kubernetes您不需要ClusterIP的地址
when creating a service then the dns
dns服务器将返回pod的ip地址
server will return the pod ip addresses instead
而不是service的ip地址，现在客户端可以
of the services ip address and now the client can
做一个简单的dns解析以获得
do a simple dns lookup to get the ip address
service成员pod的ip地址
of the pods that are members of that service
然后客户端可以使用该ip地址连接到
and then client can use that ip address to connect to
他想通信的指定pod，或者所有的pod
the specific part he wants to talk to or all of the parts
我们在service配置文件中
so the way we define a headless service
定义headless service的方式
in a service configuration file
基本上是将ClusterIP设置为None
is basically setting the cluster ip to none
所以当我们用这个配置文件
so when we create these service from
创建这些service时
this configuration file kubernetes
kubernetes不会为service分配ip地址
will not assign the service a cluster ip address
当我们列出service时
and we can see that in the output when i
我们可以在输出中看到这点
list my services
我有一个ClusterIP的service被创建用于微服务
so i have a cluster ip service that i created
以及一个headless service
for the microservice and a headless
请注意，当我们
service and note here that when we
在集群中部署有状态应用程序时
deploy stateful applications
以mongodb为例
in the cluster like mongodb for example
我们有正常的ClusterIP Service
we have the normal service the cluster ip service
处理基本的到mongodb通信
that basically handles the communication
或者在pod内的其他容器
to mongodb and maybe other container inside the pod
除了那个service我们还有headless service
and in addition to that service we have a headless service
所以我们总是有这两个service
so we always have these two services
互相扶持
alongside each other
这样就可以实现通常的对这类用例的负载平衡
so this can do the usual load balancing stuff for
而对那种用例
this kind of use case and for use cases
即客户端需要直接与
where client needs to communicate with
其中一个pod通信
one of those parts directly like a
比如master节点直接执行命令
master node directly to
或者pod之间互相交流
perform the right commands or the pods to talk to each other
用于数据同步
for data synchronization the headless
headless service将派上用场
service will be used for that
当我们定义service的配置时
when we define a service configuration
我们可以指定
we can specify
service的类型
a type of the service and the type attribute
type属性可以有三个不同的值
can have three different values it could
默认为ClusterIP
be cluster ip which is a default
这就是为什么我们不需要明确指明
that's why we don't have to specify that
此外还有NodePort和Load Balancer(负载均衡器)
we have a node port and load balancer
NodePort类型创建了一个service
so type node port basically creates a
该service在每个worker节点上
service that is accessible
可通过静态端口访问
on a static port on each worker node
现在来比较一下
in the cluster now to compare that to
我们之前的例子
our previous example
ClusterIP仅仅是在进群内部可访问的
the cluster ip service is only accessible
没有外部路由可以
within the cluster itself so no external traffic can
直接访问ClusterIP
directly address the cluster ip service
然而，NodePort类型的service使
the node port service however makes the
外部路由可以在每个worker节点
external traffic accessible on static
的静态端口实现访问
or fixed port on each worker node
所以在这种情况下，不用Ingress
so in this case instead of ingress the
浏览器请求将直接来到
browser request will come directly
该worker节点的端口
to the worker node at the port that
该端口由service中的spec部分定义
the service specification defines
而NodePort类service开放的端口
and the port that node port service type exposes
由nodePort属性定义
is defined in the node port attribute
这里注意nodePort的值
and here note that the node port value
有一个预定义范围
has a predefined range between thirty thousand
介于30000-32767之间
and thirty two thousand seven hundred seven
你可以从该范围中取一个值
so you can have one of the values
作为nodePort值
from that range as a node port value
任何超出这个范围的值都不会被接受
anything outside that range won't be
这就意味着NodePort类型的service
accepted so this means that
可以被外部路由，如浏览器的请求
the node port service is accessible for the external traffic
通过worker节点的ip地址
like browser request for example at ip address of the worker node
和这里定义的节点端口来访问
and the node port defined here however
然而就像在ClusterIP中一样
just like in cluster ip we have a port
我们有一个service的端口
of the service so when we create the
所以当我们创建NodePort时
node port service a cluster ip service
一个NodePort service可到达的ClusterIP
to which the node port service will route
也会自动被创建
is automatically created and here as you see
如果我列出了service
if i list the services the node port
NodePort会有一个ClusterIP地址
will have a cluster ip address
对于每个ip地址，它也将有开放的端口
and for each ip address it will also have the ports
也就是该service可被访问的地方
open where the service is accessible at
还要注意service包揽所有worker节点
and also note that service spends all the worker nodes
所以如果你有三个pod副本
so if you have three pod replicas
分别在三个不同的节点上
on three different notes basically the
service有能力处理
service will be able to handle that request
在任何worker节点上的请求
coming on any of the worker nodes and
然后转发给其中一个pod副本
then forward it to one of those
现在这种类型的service
pod replicas now that type of service
开放能力不是很有效，而且
exposure is not very efficient and also
不安全，因为你开放了
not secure because you are basically opening the ports
可以直接与每个worker节点的service对话的端口
to directly talk to the services on each worker node
所以外部客户端
so the external clients basically have
能够直接访问worker节点
access to the worker nodes directly
如果我们让所有的service
so if we give all the services this
都是NodePort类型
node port service type then we would have a bunch of
worker节点就会开放一堆端口
ports open on the worker nodes clients
可供客户端从外面直接通信
from outside can directly talk to
所以它不是很高效和安全的方式
so it's not very efficient and secure
有一种更好的选择
way to handle that and as a better
有一种负载均衡器service类型
alternative there is a load balancer service type
使用负载均衡器
and the way it works with load balance
使得service更容易从外部访问
or service type is that the service becomes accessible
通过云供应商的负载均衡器功能
externally through a cloud provider's
每个云供应商
load balancer functionality so each cloud provider
都有自己的原生负载平衡器实现
has its own native load balancer implementation
而那会在我们创建负载均衡器类型service时
and that is created and used whenever we
被创建并使用
create a load balancer service type
谷歌云平台、aws 、zure、openstack等等
uh google cloud platform aws azure leenode
它们都提供这样的功能
openstack and so on all of them offer this functionality
所以当我们创建一个负载均衡器类型Service
so whenever we create a load balancer service
NodePort和ClusterIP类型service
node port and cluster ip services are
由kubernetes自动创建
created automatically by kubernetes
云平台的外部负载均衡器
to which the external load balancer of the cloud
会将路由引向它们
platform will route the traffic to
这是我们如何
and this is an example of how did we
定义负载均衡器service的一个例子
define load balancer service configuration
所以不是NodePort类型，而是
so instead of node port type we have a
负载平衡器
load balancer and
同样的，我们有
the same way we have the port of the
属于ClusterIP的端口
service which belongs to the cluster ip
我们有nodePort，也就是
and we have the node port which is the port
在worker节点上开放的
that opens on the worker node but it's
但是它不能直接从外部访问
not directly accessible
只能通过负载均衡器本身访问
externally but only through the load balancer itself
所以入口点变成了一个负载均衡器
so the entry point becomes a load
它会将路由
balancer first and it can then
引导到worker节点的nodePort
direct the traffic to node port
以及内部的ClusterIP
on the worker node and the cluster ip the internal service
这就是负载均衡器service
so that's how the flow would work with
的工作流程
the load balancer service
换句话说，负载均衡器类型service
so in other words the load balancer
是NodePort类型的拓展
service type is an extension
而NodePort又是ClusterIP的拓展
of the node port type which itself is an extension
接着
of the cluster ip type and again
如果我创建一个负载均衡器类型
if i create a load balancer service type and
并列出所有service
list all the services you can see the
您可以看到对于每种service类型在显示上的差异
differences in the display as well
您可以看到ip地址、类型
where for each service type you see the ip addresses you see the type
以及开放的端口
and you see the ports that the service has opened
我应该在这里提一下
and i should mention here that in a real
在真实的kubernetes设置示例中
kubernetes setup example
您可能不会将NodePort用于外部连接
you would probably not use node port for external connection
你可能会用它来进行快速的测试
you would maybe use it to test some surveys very quickly
但不是用于生产用例
but not for production use cases so for
举个例子，如果你有
example if you have a
可通过浏览器访问的应用程序
application that is accessible through
要么可以为这样的请求
browser you will either configure
配置一个Ingress
ingress for each such request so you
这样你会有ClusterIP作为内部service
would have internal services the cluster ip services that
由Ingress转发到
ingress will route to or you would have
或者你也可以使用云平台
a load balancer that uses the cloud platform's
原生的负载均衡器实现
native load balancer implementation
恭喜你能坚持到最后
congratulations you made it till the end
我希望你学到了很多
i hope you learned a lot
并且从这门课中学到了一些有价值的知识
and got some valuable knowledge from
如果你想了解更多现代化的
this course if you want to learn about modern
devops工具，请务必查看我的
devops tools be sure to check out my
关于该主题的教程
tutorials on that topic
订阅我的频道以了解更多内容
and subscribe to my channel for more
如果你想与我保持联系
content also if you want to stay
你可以在社交媒体上关注我
connected you can follow me on social media
或者加入私人facebook群
or join the private facebook group i
我将在那里见到你
would love to see you there
谢谢大家的收看
so thank you for watching and see you in
下一个视频再见
the next video